<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>अथातो घुमक्कड़ जिज्ञासा</title>
    <description>Eternal Curiousity Of Traveler's Mind. Experiences of travel, mountaineering, trekking and other recreational activities or adventure sports.</description>
    <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2018 08:28:50 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2018 08:28:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kuari pass Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had been to Devariyatal — Chandrashila trek in November ‘16.
New year was coming.
One of my office colleague, Akash had shown interest to come along on a trek.
Another colleague Shweta, was also interested in trekking in Himalayas.
Shweta had done a trek with me before but Akash was new to this.
I thought of trekking to Kuari pass, which offers a close view of Nanda Devi, Dunagiri and Hathi - Ghoda parbat.
I had not been to this trek before.
It is also suitable for novice trekkers and many trekking organizations run batches along this route.
So, we wouldn’t be alone if we couldn’t find any guide for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started our journey from Delhi on Wednesday, 28th Dec, 2016 on train.
Upon reaching Haridwar Railway Station, we took a Uttarakhand Roadways bus to Joshimath.
Though trek starts from Auli, we figured that accommodation in Auli would cost us more due to increase in tourist influx around year end.
We needed to see if we could get a guide in Joshimath.
By evening of Thursday, 29th Dec, 2016, we reached Joshimath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this long journey we didn’t have much time left to get a guide and make arrangements of food on the trek.
Our topmost priority was to get a guide which would help us with the trek route.
We found one from a local tourist organization.
Immediately after that, he helped us get all the forest permits needed for camping and trekking.
With the consultation of our guide, we bought and packed all the ration needed for a seemingly 4 day long trek to Kuari pass from Auli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;First day of trek&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1901/44571704304_6af8935cc5_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Start of trek from Auli&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Start of trek from Auli&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next morning we started with our guide Nima Sherpa who was carrying the utensils, stove and kerosene.
By the time, we reached Auli in a cab it was 08:30 AM.
According to itinerary, we were to camp in Gorson Bugyal on first day of trek.
After reaching Gorson Bugyal, Nima kept on walking further and I figured that there is no nearby water source around to camp here.
I decided not tell others so early and was happy in way that we are saving time and I may get some days to go on another trek around here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gorson Bugyal offers a spectacular view of Nanda Devi. Though it was little cloudy, but I was happy to see Nanda Devi so clear.
Gorson Bugyal is too soon to camp for the day in my opinion. As we moved further through the meadow, clouds were all around us and we could no longer see peaks other than Hathi Ghoda and Dunagiri on our left.
Sun played hide and seek behind the clouds as we moved towards Chitrakantha forest area.
After a walk of 6 hours, we were entering into Chitrakantha forest.
Akash had some sign of tiredness but was elated when told that we didn’t stop at Gorson Bugyal due to nonavailability of water and are reaching Chitrakantha/Tali camping site in few minutes.
All this time he had been wondering about the distance travelled and the time to reach Gorson Bugyal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1936/31419831688_e3af38ef4d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Camps of Himalayan Snow Runners&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Camps of Himalayan Snow Runners&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camping sites of Chitrakantha forest was already full with the camps of Indiahikes and Himalayan Snow Runners.
We found a little space nearby where we could pitch our tents. Nima decided to stay in a cave like place nearby where he had set up the kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1944/44571700604_eaea0ce901_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kitchen&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kitchen&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had started from Auli after our breakfast and were hungry by the time we reached Chitrkantha around 2:30 PM. Nima quickly made tea for all of
us and then we went on exloring around. Meanwhile, Nima had started preparing for dinner.
When sun was about to set, we crammed around a little bonfire made by Nima discussing our next day plans.
Nima was planning to camp in Khullar next day before reaching Kuari pass.
Akash had some urgent work in office and was not in favour of reaching Kuari pass in 2 days.
Nima proposed an alternative plan to leave our tents pitched and start early morning to Kuari pass with our daypacks to come back before evening to Chitrkantha itself.
Everybody agreed to this plan.
I was little reluctant because I feared that we may not reach Kuari pass early morning to have a clear view of mountains around.
I gave up eventually.
I had ample time and didn’t want to rush it.
Nima had prepared Dal-Chawal.
The utensils were small and dal wasn’t enough for 4 people.
Nima insisted us to have all of the dal as he would fetch some more from the kitchen of Himalayan Snow Runners where his friends were working.
Our little bonfire was about to die, so we decided to call it a day and moved towards our tents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;second-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;Second Day of Trek&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1932/31419830198_6831985953_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hathi Ghoda Parvat and other peaks&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Hathi Ghoda Parvat and other peaks&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We woke up early in the morning and after little breakfasts and prepared a daypack with water and a jacket.
Akash decided to brush his teeth and was little behind so I asked Shweta and Nima to move ahead.
Few minutes later, I hastened with Akash to catch up with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1966/31419826428_c6349d31b0_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Near Khullar camping site, towards Kuari pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Near Khullar camping site, towards Kuari pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Near Khullar camping site, towards Kuari pass&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was past 7:30 in the morning. We were rushing to reach Kuari pass before it gets cloudy and passed others along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1971/44571697034_a1116d19de_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Second day of trek&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Second day of trek&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around 10:30 when we passed a glacial stream before the slope of Kuari pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1927/44571707924_9f869742d0_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A glacial stream before the slope of Kuari pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A glacial stream before the slope of Kuari pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The view of the huge valley and the Pangarchulla peak in the vicinity was very enticing.
I enquired Nima about the climb of Pangarchulla.
He told me to come after the snow.
Climb to Pangarchula is easier when there is snow as there are many boulders on the way.
The cold breeze had become strong and and cloud had started to cover the sun.
Soon we reached the top near Kuari pass to have complete 270deg view of surrounding.
I had an app “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peakfinder.org/?lat=30.4453&amp;amp;lng=79.5756&amp;amp;azi=47&amp;amp;zoom=4&amp;amp;ele=3805&quot;&gt;PeakFinder&lt;/a&gt;” installed to identify the peaks in view from any location.
I was little disappointed as array of clouds always covered the the peaks behind Dunagiri and Hathi Ghora.
We stayed there at the top for an hour or so while sun played hide and seek behind the clouds.
Even for a moment, the warmth of sun in such ice cold breeze was greatly appreciated by us.
It seemed that weather was not going to get any clearer and it might snow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1949/44571699164_8f544ae655_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kuari pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kuari pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a little stay there, we started back. The other group from some trek organization had been resting way behind the glacial stream.
While coming back, they met us near the glacial stream.
We suggested few of those trekkers to hurry as they might get caught in bad weather while coming back.
It looked like this group had many novice trekkers, not mentally prepared enough for adverse conditions which might come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wind was getting stronger and stronger and carried snowflakes along with it.
Shweta had developed knee pain while descending and was walking slow.
I asked Nima to go ahead and prepare lunch for us. We were walking little slow but reached Chitrakantha around 3 PM.
Lunch was served and Akash went ahead to take a nap while I stayed near the fireplace.
To pass time I decided to roast the rest of the tomatoes and potatoes and prepared “chokha” with great help of Shweta for all of us to be served
in dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1969/31419825288_0a34e56edb_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New year eve, dinner prepared&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;New year eve, dinner prepared&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway we were going back tomorrow.
We clicked pictures in the cave while Nima went off with some of his friends to celebrate new year.
Two goats were brought from the nearby village for 31st December night.
Akash was amused to think whether he could ask in their kitchen to share some of mutton with him.
Nima was back around 9 and asked us to have our dinner so that he could be free to be with his friends.
I was happy to hear some kind words about “chokha” from Nima.
We thought of keeping ourselves awake till 12 in night that day but our eyes were getting heavy by 10 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;third-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;Third Day of Trek&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was first day of year 2017, we had started back to Dhak from where we could take a cab to Joshimath.
It was 11:30 AM when everybody reached Dhak.
After waiting a while when we could not get any transport, I asked Nima to call a cab to pick us up which came after half an hour.
There weren’t any buses to Haridwar in afternoon so we decided to stay in Joshimath that night to catch an early bus to Haridwar next morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more photos, our &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/photos/BzfZadUGLftwrM8Y6&quot;&gt;Kuari pass album&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2017/01/22/kuari-pass-trek-log/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2017/01/22/kuari-pass-trek-log/</guid>
        
        <category>chamoli</category>
        
        <category>joshimath</category>
        
        <category>auli</category>
        
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Devariyatal - Chandrashila Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After my last trek to Hampta Pass, I couldn’t get any leave from office due to work and had lost precious trek months of August, September and
October. 
It was towards end of November, when I finally got a chance to plan a trek.
One of my office colleague, Shweta had been asking to go on a trek. 
She was eager to see what a trek would be like. 
I was little skeptical, since she had no prior experience of trek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had not been to Tungnath before, so I chose to trek to Chandrashila starting from Deoriyatal via Rohini Bugyal. 
It was also suitable trek in a way that it is not difficult for new trekkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1944/43478504700_4db80bbeb3_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tungnath&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Tungnath&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tungnath is the highest Shiva temple in the world and is one of the five and the highest Panch Kedar temples located in the mountain range 
of Tunganath in Rudraprayag district, in the Indian state of Uttarakhand. The Tunganath (literal meaning: Lord of the peaks) mountains form the 
Mandakini and Alaknanda river valleys. 
Located at an altitude of 3,680 m (12,073 ft), and just below the peak of Chandrashila, Tungnath temple is the highest Hindu shrine dedicated to 
Lord Shiva. 
The temple is believed to be 1000 years old and is the third (Tritiya Kedar) in the pecking order of the Panch Kedars. 
It has a rich legend linked to the Pandavas, heroes of the Mahabharata epic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started from New Delhi to Haridwar on Friday, 25th Nov’16 via train and we reached Haridwar at 4 in the morning. 
The bus stand was near by so we walked towards Bus stand soon after having tea at Railway station to catch a bus to Joshimath, Chamoli. 
After 6 hours of journey, we reached Rudraprayag. 
From there we took a cab to Sari village (Starting point of trek) as there aren’t frequent transport options towards Ukhimath road. 
Sari is located near Ukhimath in Rudraprayag district.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;first-day-of-trek-towards-devariyatal-fromsari&quot;&gt;First day of trek towards Devariyatal from Sari&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1947/45293509741_d3dd0ee92d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First day of trek towards Devariyatal from Sari&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;First day of trek towards Devariyatal from Sari&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reached the village Sari around 2 PM. We started off to Devariyatal immediately. 
Trek to Devariyatal is roughly 3 km climb from this village. 
In little more than an hour, we reached Devariyatal . 
There weren’t many people camping that day. 
In fact, there were only two tents pitched except ours. 
The lake Devariyatal is beauty of it’s own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1909/43478509650_5b5d90a179_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Deoriyatal Lake&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Deoriyatal Lake&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A clear view of peak like Mt. Chaukhambha, and reflections of surrounding trees in it’s calm water could hardly be matched by any other camping site. 
It is also unmatched in terms of it’s distance from nearest civilization with Sari village being just 2 km downhill. 
We put our bags and tents nearby the lake and decided to take stroll along the boundary of lake. 
The sun was about to set, and the surrounding peaks were getting a golden hue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1946/43478511470_a34a50f77e_b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;With every moment of setting sun, mountains were getting heavenly.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;With every moment of setting sun, mountains were getting heavenly.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rushed to a place to get a best possible view. 
We couldn’t have enough of it. 
It felt like as if it has been a long time since I had been away from mountains. 
Shweta also was very happy to be here. 
In her words, this place can make a person breathe a new life in themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1903/45293510531_436d597ced_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;View of Mt. Chaukhambha from Lake&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View of Mt. Chaukhambha from Lake&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before dark, we pitched our tents. 
The sky was soon filled with stars where we sat under in appreciation. 
After some time, we went to a nearby shop for dinner. 
There while having dinner, we asked about the route to Chandrashila via Rohini Bugyal from the shopkeeper. 
He told us to take a guide as there was very less or no water along the route and there was nobody going through that route these days. 
In my little experience of trekking, I had never taken a guide before but this time was different. 
I needed to be more responsible than before. 
I was not sure, how easy this was going to be for somebody new to trekking. 
We may have to keep on trekking if we couldn’t find water along the way till we find any. 
Shweta was ready to accept these difficulties. 
After talking to others in the shop, it was clear to us that water sources along the way had dried up and we may face difficulties because of that. Everybody except us, were going to Tungnath from Chopta which was too mainstream for me. 
While having dinner, I asked if I could get a guide for the rest of the trek. 
The shopkeeper told us that he knew someone in the village, who would take INR 1000 per day and we also have to rent a tent and sleeping bag for
him. 
We decided to think over it in night and went back to our tents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;second-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;Second day of Trek&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1975/45293507411_2ee15fda2c_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chaukhambha, early morning at Devariyatal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Chaukhambha, early morning at Devariyatal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We woke up early and packed our bags. 
There was a hut of forest guard nearby who gave us the required camping permits. 
We were ready by 7 AM. 
What mattered to me the most was to complete the trek without any unnecessary difficulties. 
While having breakfast I asked the shopkeeper to arrange for the guide he was talking about last night. 
Meanwhile he was on his way to Devariyatal from home (Sari village), we arranged for his tent and sleeping bag along with some utensils and food items which will be required in coming days. 
Being extra careful with water, we bought some extra bottles in case we didn’t find any water on the way.
Our guide, Umendra Singh Bhatt, turned up almost after an hour and we started as soon as he arrived. 
Our first stop was Rohini Bugyal and the trail leading to Rohini Bugyal was not long. 
It ascends moderately till Jhandi Dhar (a ridge with a flag at the top) and passes through a dense jungle thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1969/45293505071_01390cc226_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;On the way to Rohini Bugyal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;On the way to Rohini Bugyal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our right side, we constantly had a view of Sari village. 
Contrary to what was told, we encountered running streams on our way. 
After Jhandi Dhar, the jungle becomes dense and beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1930/45293506261_3e4122519d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;On the way to Rohini Bugyal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;On the way to Rohini Bugyal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1927/45293503531_d6e431c392_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every now and then I couldn’t stop myself from halting and clicking pictures on the way. 
We easily reached Rohini Bugyal in 4–5 hours. 
We decided to halt for the day and the place had few abandoned huts. 
People living there had left the place not more than a month ago. 
There was a small stream of water near the place where we decided to camp. 
Umendra collected some dry woods from nearby place and created a makeshift fireplace with some stones and started to prepare tea. 
After having tea, we went around to fetch some more wood for night and cooking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was curious to know about the places around, so soon after having tea and maggi, we went for a stroll. 
From our location the view of Trishul peak was blocked by a mountain. 
Umendra told us that on this mountain, there is a lake called Bisuri Tal which is a high altitude glacial lake.
I think it may’ve been known as Vasuki Tal originally. 
Though there already is one Vasuki Tal in Gangotri Valley and one in Kedarnath Valley.
From Rohini Bugyal, a straight trail leads to Bisuri Tal, whereas the trail on the right with initial ascent and then steep descent goes towards Akash Kamini stream coming from Chandrashila.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1969/43478508360_e33417f6bc_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rohini Bugyal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Rohini Bugyal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually it takes two more days from Rohini Bugyal to reach Bisuri Tal.
Bisuri Tal offers a very close view of Trishul peak and it is one of the less known treks. 
If time allowed, I was eager to go on this one as soon as we complete the Chandrashila trek. 
There isn’t much information on Bisuri Tal on internet.
We roamed around the meadow in the evening and as the sun was about to set, the cast it was creating on the mountains was giving such a fascinating view that it was literally a treat to watch. 
When it was finally dark, we sat near the fireplace to discuss the next course of actions and we decided to start early the next day so as to reach Bhurjgali early and continue trekking to Chandrashila after leaving our heavy rucksacks at the shop whoes owner was Umendra’s friend. 
With this plan, next day was going to be little long. 
It had more ascent than before. 
Umendra went to sleep early and we sat there talking near the fireplace till there was no firewood left. 
After sometime, with not much left to do, we went on towards our tents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;third-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;Third day of trek&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1968/43478506340_aa67f9f3cd_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got up early around 6 in the morning and packed our tents and bags.
Umendra had already started preparing tea for all of us. After having some tea and biscuit, we left Rohini Bugyal to start our last day of the
trek. 
Past Rohini Bugyal, trail descends steeply towards Akash Kamini stream. On this descend, Shweta started having problems with her knee which made her little slow.&lt;br /&gt;
She continued anyway and we soon reached the Akashkamini stream. 
It originates near the Chandrashila peak. 
After walking for around 2 hours we halted near lower Bhurjgali. 
There were few abandoned huts around where we stayed for a while and had some maggi. 
Umendra seemed to be a very good cook. We both agreed, that we never had maggi tastier than this. :yum:
It took nearly three hours for us to reach Bhurjgali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1948/45293512041_90d45ef3f3_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Near lower Bhurjgali&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Near lower Bhurjgali&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here onwards, this trail merges to the trail coming from Chopta. 
In fact Chopta was about a km from here. 
There was a shop nearby where we left our rucksacks and had some tea. 
Soon we left for Tungnath and Chandrashila. 
It is well laid path with carved steps and railings etc.
What disappointed me most was the amount of garbage on the way. 
The task of collecting garbage on the way became more difficult than any other of my treks. 
Umendra was also helping in collecting the garbage. 
We were discussing, what could Lord Tungnath offer to those who come and throw garbage around. 
In an hour or so, we reached Tungnath, though the temple was closed for the season. 
We offered our prayers and roamed around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1949/45293508461_d57875480c_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;With our guide Umendra Singh Bhatt&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;With our guide Umendra Singh Bhatt&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There we met other people who had come there from Chopta. 
We stayed there for a while and then started ahead for Chandrashila.
As there was no snow, so it didn’t take much time to reach Chandrashila.
There was a small temple up there. As soon as we reached there, all of us offered our prayers to the lord and went ahead with watching the amazing view of mountains. 
It had been a long time, that I had visited a place which offers such a panoramic view of mountains peaks. 
We could see a complete 180 degree view of majestic peaks of Garhwal. 
Umendra told about the various peaks we can see from there and the places around. 
I had been to the summit of Mt. DKD-II which could also be seen from there. 
Chandrashila also offers a clear view of Mt. Nanda Devi. 
From Jaonli to Nanda Devi, every peak was clear to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1916/43478512180_f55053bfeb_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A panoramic view from Chandrashila&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A panoramic view from Chandrashila&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was carrying my binoculars which also helped me explore these peaks more precisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1946/43478510220_d595bcf5ee_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this time of our stay at Chandrashila, we found ourselves sitting and watching the peaks around. 
When we were content enough, we started our descent towards Bhurjgali. After walking for almost an hour, we reached Bhurjgali and there we had our lunch and started descending towards Chopta. 
From Chopta we took a cab to Sari village which Umendra had already called. 
After a drive of almost 40–45 minutes, we reached Sari, where we stayed for the night before leaving for Haridwar next morning.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2017/01/22/devariyatal-chandrashila-trek-log/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2017/01/22/devariyatal-chandrashila-trek-log/</guid>
        
        <category>chopta</category>
        
        <category>tungnath</category>
        
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mountaineering Institutes in India</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Although there are many other institutes in India, but these two are the most sought ones. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indmount.org&quot;&gt;Indian Mountaineering Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, which is apex national body in this field lists 5 institutes on it’s webpage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hmidarjeeling.com/&quot;&gt;Himalayan Mountaineering Institute (HMI), Darjeeling, West Bengal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nimindia.net/&quot;&gt;Nehru Institute Of Mountaineering (NIM), Uttarkashi, Uttarakhand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adventurehimalaya.org/&quot;&gt;Atal Bihari Vajpayee Institute of Mountaineering and Allied Sports (ABVMAS), Manali, Himachal Pradesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jawaharinstitutepahalgam.com/&quot;&gt;Jawahar Institute of Mountaineering (JIM), Pahalgam, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iismgulmarg.in/&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Skiing and Mountaineering, Gulmarg, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than these 5, there are few more institutes which conducts courses
in mountaineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sonam Gyatso Mountaineering Institute (SGMI), Gangtok, Sikkim&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nimasdirang.com/&quot;&gt;Nation Institute of Mountaineering and Allied Sports, Dirang, West Kameng, Arunachal Pradesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pnsmti.org&quot;&gt;Pt. Nain Singh Rawat Mountaineering Institute, Munsiyari, Uttarakhand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from this, there are some internation organisations working in similar domain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nols.edu&quot;&gt;The National Outdoor Leadership School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/10/15/mountaineering-institutes-in-india/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/10/15/mountaineering-institutes-in-india/</guid>
        
        <category>Manali</category>
        
        <category>Darjeeling</category>
        
        <category>Uttarkashi</category>
        
        <category>Gulmarg</category>
        
        <category>West Kameng</category>
        
        
        <category>organised</category>
        
        <category>course</category>
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>mountaineering</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hampta Pass and Chandratal Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was exploring some extended weekend treks as my office colleagues also wanted to come along on my next trek. 
After searching and negotiating a lot, no agreeable trek couldn’t be decided and now that I have to travel
solo, I finally decided to go for Hampta Pass and Chandratal.. 
Hampta pass trek starts from Manali, Himachal Pradesh. 
It is a small pass on Pir Panjal range of Himalayas, between Lahaul and Kullu valley in Himachal Pradesh. 
Vertical rock walls, water falls, hanging glaciers, tiny lakes, peaks rising above 6000 m are main characteristics of this
trek. 
I was very excited about this trek because I was finally getting another chance to see Chandratal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kiran was also in town and ready for a weekend trek. 
We left Delhi on Thursday, 14 July so that we had an extra day before next week starts.
Bus to Manali was running late and we reached there around 11A.M. 
After having heavy dinner around noon, we took a cab for Jobra. 
It takes an hour and forty hairpin bends to arrive at Jobra. 
It was around 2 PM when we reached there. 
We left immediately, as we had planned to reach Balu Ka Ghera on our first day of trek and it was already late. 
It had rained earlier in the day and path was slippery till Chika village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1927/45243668192_77b56aef6b_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In few hours of trek, crossing few streams we reached Jwara. 
Clouds were all around us and visibility was very poor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1954/45243661482_a07ff1b414_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balu ka ghera was still like an hour far from Jwara. 
There wasn’t much daylight left and it could rain anytime. 
We decided to pitch our tents in Jwara. 
In the backdrop, we had a vertical rocky cliff with a nice view of waterfall. 
There was a shop in Jwara from where we got ourselves nice dinner for the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1926/31418933588_a2f962e624_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Our tents in Jwara&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Our tents in Jwara&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1918/45243667192_879f49476e_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Campsite at Jwara&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Campsite at Jwara&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was Saturday, June 16th. We started for Balu ka Ghera early morning
next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1938/30354220177_9b40139bd4_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It was all misty from the beginning which was giving the whole
valley a mystic look.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;It was all misty from the beginning which was giving the whole valley a mystic look.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started raining heavily when we reached Balu Ka Ghera. 
We got 4 parathas packed from there to have lunch later in the day. 
After more than an hour wait in Balu Ka Ghera, when the rain didn’t stop; we prepared ourselves to walk in rain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1921/45243663902_2eb5e3a18a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Open Valey near Balu ka Ghera&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Panaromic View of Open Valey near Balu ka Ghera&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a Dutch couple, whom we had met in Jwara. 
They also arrived Balu Ka Ghera when we were about to leave. 
We started from Balu Ka Ghera together. 
They were thinking of returning back from the pass but we had plans to go further. 
Before the ascent to pass starts, there is a big lake where we bid them goodbye and continued our journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1941/31418931088_cb010c559a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Small lake on the way up to pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Small lake on the way up to pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In heavy rain, the stream beside us was ferocious which actually accompanied us all along the trek in the valley. After crossing the some boulders, we reached the glacier. 
In such low visibility, it was getting difficult to find our way forward. Kiran was incessantly asking whether we are on the right path or not. 
I followed the tracks of mules on the glacier and reached the plateau. 
It was real cloudy and it seemed that I had lost my way here. 
We had a pack of biscuit there and decided to look closely for tracks. 
It seemed, that we had to go back and follow the track more closely. 
On our left was a vertical rocky cliff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1905/45243665242_dbee6381d5_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The valley, clouds ahead on the pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The valley, clouds ahead on the pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was there when I heard some sound of mules walking somewhere nearby. 
I rushed towards the noise, though between so dense clouds, it was being difficult to figure out. Following the mule sound, I heard voice of a man controlling the mules. 
We shouted and asked whether anybody is there. 
The mules were gone and lost in the clouds by then. 
After few minutes, someone replied to our hello. When we rushed towards the sound, it was the same dutch couple with their guide. 
The lady told me, that they decided to cross the pass same day. 
The lady was was kind enough to offer us chocolates. 
We were just few meters away from the trail, but without their help we definitely would’ve gone in the wrong direction.
This could’ve lost us at least few precious hours. 
We were actually few meters away from the trail. 
It’s just that the trail makes an unusual bend towards left while going up at the highest point of trek which we
would have easily figured out in clearer sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1944/30354221347_cdc869abd1_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Towards Shiagoru From Hampta Pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Towards Shiagoru From Hampta Pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With them, we started our descent to Shiagoru. 
It’s a steep descent which was little slippery due to rains. 
The rain was little slow at this part of valley (Lahaul). If it was a normal day, we could’ve had a nice view of Indrasan peak which was right to us while climbing down. 
We were descending to Lahaul Valley. 
The arrangements were already there for the night in Shiagoru for the Dutch couple. 
We decided to trek further down to Chhatru. 
Kiran had to go back next day for Delhi on Sunday to join office. 
The stream in Shiagoru had grown strong due to continuous rain that day. 
It’s a flat area fed from glacier; it wasn’t deep but certainly was cold. 
Having crossed the stream with our hands joined, we took off for Chhatru. 
From Shiagoru to Chhatru, it’s a long walk but easy descent. 
The sun was about to set when we reached Chhatru roadhead. 
Chhatru is on the way to Kaza from Manali. We pitched our tents, and were invited for dinner by trek organizers from Bikat adventures who were also camped there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1943/31418932038_7346bfa310_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Before Chhatru&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Before Chhatru&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early morning, we had a quick breakfast in Chhatru. 
There were few truck drivers having tea. 
When they were about to leave, I asked them for a drop to Batal. 
I started my journey ahead with them after saying goodbye to Kiran who was waiting for a conveyance that he can get to Manali.
Chhatru to Batal isn’t very far, but due to road conditions it was already afternoon when I reached Batal. 
After having lunch in Batal, I enquired for the directions to Chandratal. People suggested me to go to Kunzum pass and start a near downhill trek from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1954/45243660572_e0e46021cf_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took there advice, as it was clear that the road from Batal to Chandratal was only preferred for vehicles. 
Those truck drivers were still there having lunch. I joined them again when they left for Kaza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was raining in Kunzum la, when I reached there. 
There was no one who could tell me the way to Chandratal, though there was a board with signboard of Chandratal. 
I just decided to follow the path behind the board. 
It was well laid trail till I reached a point from where I had a view of valley. 
At this point the trail ended and I had nowhere to go. I could see tents far in the valley, but there was a very steep descent. I tried to go down that path, but had to to turn back as it was very slippery. 
When many attempts to find a better way to the valley failed I had to retrace the path back so as to find some alternative way. I was sure that I was on right path to Chandratal. 
After few meters of travelling back, there was a trail sharp left climbing towards the nearby hill. 
I took that and climbed the hill to see around. 
From there, I could see the trail going further inside the valley. Thanking god, I trotted down the trail. 
All along the way, the weather was clear and I had a nice view of valley and Chandra river valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1968/45243666192_3c907bf02c_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chandra river valley&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Chandra river valley&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the Chandratal was in sight. 
I aimed to reach Chandratal with some buffer time to explore. 
It was not allowed to camp there but there were many people camping around Chandratal. 
There was no authority to control this. 
While trekking from Kunjum La to Chandratal, I did not find any kiosk or office where one could find any kind camping permits etc. 
The visitors of Chandratal, mostly were with some trek organization on four wheelers with exceptions of few bikers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1948/31418928728_2991bfc2b9_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chandra Taal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Chandra Taal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite that, Chandratal was still very beautiful, clean and peaceful.
The small stream emanating from Chandratal and a wooden bridge looks like a setting from a fairy tale. I sat there around half an hour. 
When sun had set, I turned back towards Batal road looking for a place to camp. 
Most of the good places nearby were completely occupied by private organizations which was little disheartening. 
Anyhow I was able to find a place to camp besides some Paragon camping site. 
Next day returned back to Batal. 
On the way to Batal from Chandratal, I was offered a lift by a jeep accompanying bikers. 
In Batal, I was able get hold of a jeep going towards Manali. 
Buses are not very reliable on this route. 
The driver of the jeep was in his teens and he was determined to reach Manali by lunch time. 
By afternoon, I was in Manali where I had lunch and explored the market until it was time for bus to Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/07/18/hampta-pass-and-chandratal-trek-log/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/07/18/hampta-pass-and-chandratal-trek-log/</guid>
        
        <category>chandratal</category>
        
        <category>hampta pass</category>
        
        <category>Manali</category>
        
        <category>Spiti</category>
        
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Indrahar Pass Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In our previous treks we had been travelling light and walking long miles a day thus helping us do treks with less leaves from work.
Planning first trek of 2016, I was thinking of something in Himachal Pradesh and then I got my hands on Depi Chaudhary’s Himalaya trek maps.
It’s very detailed one and I spent hours studying it. Hoping to combine two short duration treks, I thought of Indrahar pass(4350 m) in Dhauladhar Range between Kangra and Chamba valleys, and Kugti Pass (5050m) in Chamba. 
Indrahar pass is popular among trekkers but Kugti pass is less travelled with altitude of significant 5000+ meters and
this required some travelling on road as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also thought of doing Minkiani pass from Laka cave after coming down from Indrahar pass. 
Depi Chaudhary’s map was showing a route to Minkiani pass from Laka cave which is little beyond Snow point cafe but we zeroed
down on Indrahar pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1950/45244309202_ae64aefd4d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kiran in the back, Akshay in the left and me in the right&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kiran in the back, Akshay in the left and me in the right&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My always ready travel buddies Kiran and Akshay were willing to join for this trek though Akshay wasn’t much updated on the diversions which I and Kiran were planning to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1927/44381470365_b1fe49ddd9_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With thought to first reach Indrahar pass and later decide what next, we left on Thursday, 12th May. 
Akshay wanted to see Bhagsu waterfall, so we started our day with that. We were told about a path leading to Triund via Upper Bhagsu village. 
There was a small puddle where it used to be a pond. 
We started for Triund around 12. It was a steep climb till we merged into Triund trek route. 
It was a hot day and there weren’t enough trees for shade. 
We had our lunch in Triund and soon decided to leave for Snowline Cafe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Akshay was little reluctant to walk that day and I was slowly giving up hope to reach Lahesh cave the same day. 
I sincerely wished that we reach Lahesh cave on the same day after halting for a while at Snowline cafe for food but by the time everybody reached Snowline, we decided to camp there and leave for Indrahar pass early next morning. 
We all were carrying our separate tents but the night got very windy and Kiran had to sleep in Akshay’s tent as his tent fell due to wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1927/44571403854_65bc4a75cf_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Snowline Cafe&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Our camp at Snowline Cafe&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the night we were informed of snow conditions on the trail and were advised to take a guide. 
We were told that an ice axe might be needed to carve out steps in a glacier which falls very steep from peak. 
There was small group of people who attempted to reach Indrahar pass a day before with a guide but they had to come back from few 100 meters before pass due to snow condition and weather. 
Though, short on money we couldn’t have been able to afford guide that day and we started little late around 8:30 AM on Friday contrary to what we had planned. 
There were two more people leaving that day from Snowline Cafe for the pass. 
They even had an ice axe and were even planning to cross the pass that day. 
One of them was Ken from Japan. 
I was hopeful that if we followed them, we would be able to get to the top. 
They left before us. Akshay was not willing to continue, though he came along us for a stroll till Laka Cave area. 
Negotiating the Laka glacier took a little time and Akshay didn’t want to continue, so he decided to walk back from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1973/44571401674_aaf7d0fa08_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;it look a little time .. though it was fun&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;it look a little time .. though it was fun&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1912/44571402614_5749d2327a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;waterfall near lahesh cave&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;waterfall near lahesh cave&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We followed the trail and cairns on the way. The path was not very clear, sometimes I had to look around to be sure that we are on the right track. 
We continued our walk but Ken and his friend were nowhere to be seen by now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1979/44381469845_ef12ddec4a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were steps carved in glacier. 
Kiran hesitantly crossed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slowly and steadily, we were making progress. 
I was finding it difficult to follow the track, though I was sure that it was the right path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top seemed very close. I saw a severed head of what looked like a goat and blood patches on the trek. 
I couldn’t think of any reason of what killed it that way. 
Kiran was uneasy after seeing that and was feeling tired so he asked me go ahead without him. 
It was past noon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1978/44381471795_1c5bca5013_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The top seemed very close.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The top seemed very close.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weather seemed to coming in heavily. Suddenly it was all dark and cloudy. 
It was difficult to see what lies ahead. Kiran was far behind and I was not able to find trail further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1973/44381471155_3712c2e739_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Seems close&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markers were pointing towards a glacier which was very steep. 
It wasn’t very wide but there were no footsteps. 
Suddenly it started to hail. 
I feared of it getting worse as there was no place for me to hide so I decided to turn back and be content with the progress made on the trek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With time, the hailing slowed down but there wasn’t much time to change the decision for that day. 
Few hours after we reached Snowline Cafe, Ken and his friends also came back and they managed to reach the top. 
I sat there and pondered what went wrong. 
Why did I turn back when I knew there wasn’t much left till the top, I was almost there. 
While talking to the cafe owner, he suggested that had we started little early, we could’ve got company of local Gaddi people, who crossed that pass frequently with their goats and sheeps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1916/44571403194_78cbe4917f_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;At center is the severed head of goat&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;At center is the severed head of goat&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recollecting all what I have seen on the way, I asked the shop owner at cafe about the severed head of goat. 
He told me that Gaddi’s kill the goat which walk slowly because if they are left behind, these goats may die with hunger.
We returned back from Snowline next day on Saturday to McLeodganj. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/photos/BKgE4Gx6LAX5YYnc9&quot;&gt;Here is our shared photo album&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;next-attempt&quot;&gt;Next Attempt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It had been two weeks since my last unsuccessful attempt to complete the trek, the thought of not able to complete that trek was constantly bothering me. 
With a constant feeling of “ I shouldn’t have given up so easily “, I knew I won’t be able to plan any other trek unless I
complete this one so I decided to make another attempt to reach the top atleast. 
It was Friday, 3rd of June when I left alone for McLeodganj. 
My only camera; my mobile gave in due to charging problems. 
I didn’t even carry my tent this time and decided to stay in caves only. 
There was another cave on the other side near Chatta where I would be staying, if I were to cross the pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the thoughts and will, I started off for Lahesh cave on Saturday Morning. Rested for a while at snowline cafe, I left for Lahesh cave after having lunch. 
I was in luck as there few gaddis who were to cross that pass tomorrow. Next morning, I heard calls of those shepherds while I was getting ready and I tagged along with them. 
Those sheeps were really slow while walking. 
I was following them and sometimes tried to help them controlling the sheeps. 
When I reached the point from where I turned back last time; I had to go ahead of these sheeps as they were nearly came to a halt. 
Few local people were coming down from the top where they had gone to offer prayers. 
They also offered me prasad. 
Walking further more for around half an hour I was at the top. 
The lead shepherd was sitting there and enjoying the view of Chamba valley.
Breathing lively and cherishing what beautiful the view was, there is another thought going in back of my mind and I was wondering what would be the view of the other side from the top. 
Heavenly it was, much more than what I imagined. 
The steep descent from pass goes to a vast flat plateau covered with snow. 
From there one can see Pir panjal range and Mani Mahesh peak. 
Few minutes later another group joined us. 
We all stayed around for an hour and roamed around to see the view of valley from different spots. 
After an hour, clouds started rising from the valley and with rising clouds, we too started back. 
And in a short while, it started hailing and raining heavily. 
We continued our descent slowly and cautiously as the path was now slippery due to rain. 
And then we heard the sound of loud thunder and saw frequent lighting around. 
It continued all along the way and rain got heavier.
We had to take shelter and Lahesh cave was nearest to our rescue. 
After an hour it stopped raining and we again started walking down to Snowline cafe. 
I was having lunch over there when it started raining again, actually this time it was pouring. 
When it slowed down, I too started my journey back slowly towards Mcleodganj. 
It was already dark when I reached the town and I had to no other option than to stay over night in Mcleodganj due to non-availability of bus. 
I was happy that I reached the pass which gave me many sleepless nights because I left it incomplete last time. 
I still wished to cross the pass to see what lies on the other side; but I was travelling too light for that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/06/06/indrahar-pass-trek-log/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/06/06/indrahar-pass-trek-log/</guid>
        
        <category>indrahar</category>
        
        <category>lahesh - chamba</category>
        
        <category>minkiani</category>
        
        <category>laka</category>
        
        <category>chata</category>
        
        <category>dharmshala</category>
        
        <category>kinnaur</category>
        
        <category>mcleodganj</category>
        
        <category>triund</category>
        
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
        <category>self</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Har ki Doon Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Just a week left for the year to change to 2016 and holidays were lined up, I was in the search of a winter trek, had Kauri pass and Har ki doon in my mind.
A month ago Kiran and I had just been to Hemkund Sahib and Valley of Flowers.
Another friend Dalima, was also willing to join us in our next trek as she needed an escape from city life.
Har ki doon is well known as one of the most popular winter treks in Uttarkashi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started from Delhi to Dehradun on the night of 26th December. 
After reaching Dehradun, we couldn’t find any conveyance to Sankri so we travelled ahead to Rishikesh and from there we took a bus to Sankri.
It was long ride of around 11 hours and by the time we reached Sankri, sun was about to set.
Sankri is a small and quiet place.
Due to heavy trekking season, accommodations were already full but after some search we were able to find a place to stay.
After enjoying dinner and some talks with fellow trekkers, we headed for some last minute purchase, booked the jeep to Taluka (Starting point of our trek).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around 8 AM, when we reached Taluka. 
It was a cold morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1974/43478712280_4fea6269d9_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;River&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;River&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the trails goes along the river Supin. 
The gentle sound of river all along the first day trek is very comforting and refreshing. 
The trail is also very beautiful. 
River is very approachable from most of the first day trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1954/43478711330_903a22cff2_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Trail goes along the river&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Trail goes along the river&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around 4 PM when we reached Osla village. 
It was a steep climb after crossing the bridge. 
The village was very picturesque.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1928/43478712870_3567a0db98_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Osla Village&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Osla Village&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the river bed it seems as if people have made nests in the mountains. 
All houses of same color and made of wood which mixes with background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We haven’t had anything to eat till now. 
Dalima’s knee was giving her a tough time. 
Children of the village flocked around us asking different questions. 
I got some maggi and biscuits from a shop in the village. 
The local people seemed very helpful and nice. 
A man from village offered to prepare it for us while we talked to the children. 
There aren’t many men in the village. 
Those with whom I talked, were very keen on having us as their guest. 
We had tents but we did need food. We decided to have dinner with the old man who prepared maggi for us and pitched our tent
outside his home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1902/43478710730_4c24f61108_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The contrast of Seema and Osla&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The contrast of Seema and Osla&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was another family insisting to stay in their home. 
It was cold out there and Dalima stayed with them. 
It was very peculiar to see how these houses are made of wood and housed a hearth made of mud in the room. 
Just above the hearth roof open to make room for smoke. 
There is a place to store wood and hay below the house.
Dalima’s knee problem had aggravated and she decided to take some rest next day. 
The house owner was happy to have her as guest. 
Children were very curious excited around her and constantly chatting.  
We enquired about the logistics which we need to take and arrangements for food during the rest of the trek. 
We promised Dalima to be back as soon as we can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On tuesday, We started off early in the morning and wrapping up our tents. 
Crossing Kalkatiyadhar campsite, we reached Har ki doon in afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1950/43478709010_44f3a46fc4_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Trail after Osla Village&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Trail after Osla Village&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a sunny day and there weren’t much trees on the trail. 
The trail just before the Har ki doon was enchanting and covered with snow with beautiful little streams joining Tons river and trees around. 
Har ki doon valley is a big amphitheatre which lies in the valley of majestic Swargarohini peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1921/43478714530_f1efb39a9f_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Har Ki Doon&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Har Ki Doon&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an inexplicable experience to see such a close view of Swargarohini peak. 
This trail is believed to be taken by Pandavas who attempted to go to heaven with their bodies. 
Kiran had some phaphda which we had with pickles. 
We took water and essential stuff in our daypack and went exploring towards Juandhar glacier in the valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1944/43478713930_5692be0047_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Juandhar Glacier&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Juandhar Glacier&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t take my eyes off from the Swargarohini peak and was immersed in the thoughts of how Pandavas who attempted to climb the peak in Mahabharata era. 
The first ascent of Swargarohini was done by team of NIM(Nehru Institute Of Mountaineering) instructors in 1990, Uttarkashi
from where I once did my AMC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We walked inside the valley until sun started to set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1917/43478709830_c60123676b_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sunset in Har Ki Doon&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sunset in Har Ki Doon&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had to come back to pitch our tent to make arrangements of dinner and pitch our tents. 
We pitched our tents beside the forest rest house there and requested for dinner to the caretaker of the rest house. 
We watched the setting sun sitting on the big boulder near campsite. 
It was very cold and windy in the night. 
We spent most of the time in the kitchen before going to sleep. 
We talked about what lies further on the trail and treks in the area. 
I promised myself to cross the Borasu pass next time which lies further on the trail and take a diversion to Ruinsaira
tal which is around 14 km from Osla village. Update: I went to Bali Pass which goes via Ruinsaira Taal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was already 7 when we woke up next morning. We wrapped our tents and left at once after having tea. 
We started our retreat around 8. 
It was an easy descent and we walked on scout’s pace. 
Dalima was eagerly waiting for us in the village where we had lunch around 11. 
After paying all the dues, we left for Taluka around 12. 
It was not long when we reached Taluka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still had two spare days left and we could’ve attempted for Kedarkantha trek as well. 
New year parties with friends in Delhi are also cool; we thought and left for Delhi next morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/photos/xyArwdXxLzjtvKWDA&quot;&gt;Here is the link to our shared album.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2015/12/30/har-ki-doon-trek-log/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2015/12/30/har-ki-doon-trek-log/</guid>
        
        <category>winter trek</category>
        
        <category>swargarohini</category>
        
        <category>ruinsaira</category>
        
        <category>osla</category>
        
        <category>har ki doon</category>
        
        <category>puani garaat</category>
        
        <category>sankri</category>
        
        <category>tons</category>
        
        <category>borasu</category>
        
        <category>uttarkashi</category>
        
        <category>seema</category>
        
        <category>kedarkantha</category>
        
        <category>juandhar</category>
        
        <category>kalkatiyadhar</category>
        
        <category>supin</category>
        
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
        <category>self</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Valley of Flowers and Hemkund Sahib Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Having completed a quick trek to Roopkund in Dussehara vacations, I
hoped to do another in Deepawali. I had no plans of going home from
Noida in vacations. Kiran was also in Gurgaon itself. This time if we
took one day leave from office, we could have 5 days to do something. I
proposed going to Joshimath and doing some of treks among Kauri
Pass(Curzon Trail), Hemkund Sahib and Valley Of flowers over there.
Though Valley of flowers and Hemkund Sahib were already closed by then
for the winter season. Since we were only two, we decided to minimize
the expense using bus travel instead cab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were very few buses on the route due to Deepawali that day.  We
managed our way to Joshimath by changing buses and eventually booking a
cab from Karnaprayag. It was night when we arrived Joshimath. To start
trekking for Valley Of Flowers &amp;amp; Hemkund Sahib early morning, it would
have been better if we stayed in Govind ghat that night. The cab driver
was asking for a lot for Govind ghat so we had to stay in Joshimath and
went to Govind ghat next morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1901/44542585784_288a21c4ea_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Trail&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Trail&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After asking about the route, we left Govind ghat around 8 in morning.
Govind ghat is situated at the confluence of rivers Alaknanda and
Lakshman Ganga. The route going through Bhyundar valley is well paved
and goes through a dense forest with Bhyundar Ganga on the right side.
After 3-4 hours walk we reached Bhyundar village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1908/45214702512_d1220bb7da_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Along Bhyundar village to Ghangharia&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Along Bhyundar village to Ghangharia&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no one in the village except one shop and 3-4 labours working
on a home. Having our lunch we enquired upon further trail ahead. The
shopkeeper told us that there is absolutely no one beyond this point in
Ghangharia or Hemkund Sahib and everything is closed. He also warned us
about the bears and leopards in the area and gave us 2 crackers and some
kerosene to light up fire in night.
After getting few chapatis packed with pickle, soon we left for
Ghangharia. On our way, two dogs tagged along us after getting lured by
Kiran with biscuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1923/30325745437_e1d440dcf0_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hathi Parbat as seen from Bhyundar Village&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Hathi Parbat as seen from Bhyundar Village, A trail to Kakbhushundi lake starts from here towards this mountain&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking through the dense forest, it was past 2 P.M. when we reached
Ghangharia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1944/30325743477_fe4cba760a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ghangharia&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Ghangharia&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a significant place along this trek with lots of houses along
the both sides of street; but everything was closed. It gave the whole
place an eerie appearance. After hiding our bags in the gallery of a
rest house, we left for Valley of Flowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1968/45264796211_8a26135876_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Towards Valley Of Flowers From Ghangharia, The Pushpawati river gorge&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Towards Valley Of Flowers From Ghangharia, The Pushpawati river gorge&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trek goes through the dense forest on left side and Pushpawati river
gorge on the right. The Pushpawati river joins Bhuyandar Ganga near
Ghangharia to form Lakshman Ganga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dogs chased grey langurs herds whenever they see them. Climbing our
way after crossing Pushpawati river, and walking through the dense
forests with some snow along the trail; we reached Valley of Flowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1955/43450314680_44d2905d6f_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Valley of Flowers in mid November&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Valley of Flowers in mid November&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flora in the valley was completely dried except few green patches
here and there. We roamed inside the valley enjoying the view and
clicking pictures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1936/44542575914_3aab105d33_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some walk inside the valley, we rested near the grave of Joan
Margaret Legge (1885 - 1939) who died while collecting samples here. The
sun was about to set, so we turned back towards Ghangharia. It was
completely dark when we reached there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We picked some woods from the street and lit up a fire with the help of
kerosene. Sitting there, the dogs occasionally barked and ran along the
street. Kiran feared that something is around and tried to look towards
the way these dogs ran with torch. We only had 6 chapatis to eat. I
suggested to eat next morning for breakfast as we needed enough energy
to climb Hemkund Sahib. Kiran agreed to it and suggested to share our
chapatis with the dogs dutifully protecting us in the night. After few
hours of warming ourselves with fire, we decided to get some sleep. I
kept the fire burning and pitched our tents in the gallery of the rest
house. Dogs kept barking and running all night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1940/43450309710_29e5de7a8b_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The footsteps&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The footsteps&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After sharing our breakfast with dogs, we started for Hemkund Sahib. It
is a continuous 6 km climb till the top. After 3 kms, treeline ends and
the path was snowy. The bridge on the way was disassembled so we found
an alternate route nearby to go further. After the bridge there are
stairs and there also is an alternate way. The stairs were steep and
completely covered with snow but the alternate path is longer and not so
steep. There was snow everywhere. After crossing the nullah, when I
started on the stairs, I noticed foot steps of some big animal which
walked before us on that path. Kiran found the path slippery and decided
to take the alternate route. I climbed the stairs cautiously, wondering
if some bear is waiting for me above. Later, I was assured that this
could not be the case as the dogs went ahead and waited for me at the
end of stairs. Kiran continued negotiating the snow, while I reached the
gurudwara. After few mins, Kiran reached there and meanwhile I roamed
around the serene Homkund lake taking pictures with my mobile which
still retained it’s juice in airplane mode. With the gentle breeze, the
crystal clear rippling water of the lake was making sounds. We sat there
on a stone by the lake for few minutes and watched around. The dogs were
lying on the snow basking in the sun. Kiran wondered if they were very
tired and are sleeping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1905/45264793711_6da7566a6f_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Homkund Lake&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Homkund Lake&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 11 AM, started trekking back for Govind ghat. It was a long way
ahead and we both were hungry. We picked our bags up from Ghangharia
from where we stayed last night and continued the descent. We talked
about having big lunch at Bhyundar. The shopkeeper was waiting for us;
when we we reached there in noon. After lunch and little rest in
Bhyundar, we returned the kerosene and the crackers which we didn’t use.
It was necessary to reach Govind Ghat by evening, if we wanted to have
dinner and stay in Joshimath. Around 6 PM, when we reached Govind Ghat
it was dark. With some luck, we managed to catch a jeep coming from
Badrinath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still had a day left after these two trek days. Kauri pass was at
least 28 km one way which I didn’t think could be managed in the
remaining time. Next day we ended our trip after visiting Badrinath
temple and stayed overnight in Joshimath.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2015/11/18/valley-of-flowers-and-hemkund-sahib-trek/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2015/11/18/valley-of-flowers-and-hemkund-sahib-trek/</guid>
        
        <category>govind ghat</category>
        
        <category>ghangharia</category>
        
        <category>valley of flowers</category>
        
        <category>chamoli</category>
        
        <category>joshimath</category>
        
        <category>pushpawati</category>
        
        <category>bhyundar</category>
        
        <category>hemkund</category>
        
        <category>bhyundar ganga</category>
        
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
        <category>self</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Roopkund Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my friend asked me if I had any plans for Dussehara vacations.
For one day leave, we were getting 4 days in our hand. He was planning
for Roopkund trek as much as it can be done in two days which we would
left with after taking out the travel time from Delhi. A day before, he
got little sick and there were three of us for the trek. Kiran was from
Bombay and Silva was from Brazil. We hadn’t met before. Kiran was full
of enthusiasm and wanted to complete this trek at any cost. I was
supportive of this opinion and we chalked out our trek plan to make it
possible. Silva had done a trek to Tungnath with Kiran and my friend
Akshay few week back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We left on Wednesday evening; the cab picked me up around 10:30 in
night. After a whole night and day drive, next day we reached village
Wan around 5 p.m. To make most of our lost time, we needed to cover some
of trek that day. In few minutes, after arranging for our driver’s
accomodation; we left for the trek. We did get few advices for not
leaving for trek at such time, but we went on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out morales were pretty boost up. Calling ourselves bad mofos; we went
past the wan village down to the bridge on river Neelganga. By then it
was completely dark. Holding our torches, we started to climb. Our aim
was to reach Bedini around 11 in night. Even though, we were advised
against it in the village, we thought that it is better to utilize this
time in trek than to stay. It was around 10 p.m.; when we reached first
camping site Gharoli Patal. Bedini was still 3 km. We had still enough
juice left to reach Bedini that night. But after staying few mins for
tea there; we decided to camp there only. It was very cold and windy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1972/44571862604_02c22b0ffb_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A view from Bedini Bugyal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A view from Bedini Bugyal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next morning around 6, we left for Bhojbasa after having maggi for
breakfast. We were happy that stopping at Gharoli Patal, previous night
didn’t cost us much time when we reached Bedini. After half an hour of
admiring the beauty of vast meadows, and few clicks; we left for our
next stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1956/30355258427_8553d501d3_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;On the way to Patharnachuni&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;On the way to Patharnachuni&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1936/44571860264_683a71889a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;On the way to Patharnachuni&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around 2 PM when we reached Patharnachuni where we had our lunch.
Soon after, we left for our final stop, Bhojbasa. One the steep ascent
to Kalu Vinayak, Silva was walking a bit slow. After few wait and move
ahead; Kiran and me discussed if he could walk with Silva and I’ll come
back to carry the bag from Bhojbasa. I tried walking fast and reached
Bojbasa early where I left the bag and rushed back towards Kalu Vinayak.
Kiran and Silva were resting at Kalu Vinayak, which they had already
climbed. Silva was feeling better now and didn’t let me carry his bag.
We came back from Kalu Vinayak together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all managed to reach Bhojbasa well before evening. Silva was having
some headaches, I suggested him to have more tea and drink as much water
as he can. We did a little walk around the campsite for acclimatization
and had tea. We pitched our tents inside the forest hut. Although a lot
colder, it was less windy than Bedini here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1920/44571862004_9149484e92_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Beyond Junargali&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Beyond Junargali&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next morning after having tea, we left for Roopkund around 6. We packed
our tents and left our bag there in the hut. It was very cold and windy
on the way. Some ice started to appear inside water bottle. After one
and a half hour walk, we reached Roopkund. Silva was little behind. It
was his first experince of such altitude and cold. There was some
firewood left from previous fire; which I lit and warmed ourselves while
waiting for Silva. Some dry sticks dry grass was around which I
collected. When Silva was about to reach Roopkund; we left for
Junargali. After few minutes of climb, we reached Junargali. Silva still
was behind Roopkund. He would stop after few steps to catch a breath. It
was windy was clear in Junargali with magnificent view of Mt.
Trisul(7120m) and Nandaghunti(6309m).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1975/45244744532_f78f0de022_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jorawar Gali Pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Jorawar Gali Pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thought came to my mind for going ahead from there to Homkund. The
door like structure with bell hanging by it looked very inviting. We
didn’t have that much time. We needed to move back as soon as we can if
wanted to make it back to Wan village by night. After few minutes, Silva
was in Roopkund. I asked Silva if really wanted to climb up to Junargali
to which he said Yes. We waited for him there. Collecting litter there
left by previous trekkers, we waited there on the stairs towards Shila
Samudra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about an hour or so stay at Junargali, we started our way back to
Bhojbasa. It was already 12 when we left there. After some tea and
noodles, we left Bhojbasa around noon. There was another group of three
people who was also on had similar plans as us. There also wanted to go
back to Wan on that day itself. I was planning to go via Ali Bugyal; but
it seemed, that it was too late for that. When we reached Pattahrnachuni
in an hour or so, Silva was walking good. We decied against taking Ali
Bugyal route, we needed at least 2-3 more hours than our usual. It was
now sunset time when we reached Gharoli Patal. After taking a lot of
shortcuts on descents; my legs were tired. I was exhausted and had very
less control on my legs. It was now dark when I reached Neelganga
bridge. I was out of water and thirsty till that time. I waited with
other group for Kiran and Silva. After few mins they arrived. Silva had
got blisters in his foot. We started our last patch of trek to Wan
village. When we reached the village from Neelganga bridge, it seemed
that we lost our way which we took before. After asking for directions
and wasting around 2 hours, we managed to reach roadside around 9:30
p.m. where our cab driver was waiting for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took little more than two trek days for this trek from Wan village to
Roopkund. In retrospect, I think that if we had one more day, one day
stay at Ali Bugyal would have been perfect finishing of the trek while
coming back.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2015/11/17/roopkund-trek/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2015/11/17/roopkund-trek/</guid>
        
        <category>nanda ghunti</category>
        
        <category>bedini</category>
        
        <category>roopkund</category>
        
        <category>junargali</category>
        
        <category>trishul</category>
        
        <category>chamoli</category>
        
        <category>pataharnachuni</category>
        
        <category>gharoli patal</category>
        
        <category>lohajung</category>
        
        <category>wan</category>
        
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
        <category>self</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>HMI, Darjeeling vs. NIM, Uttarkashi</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is one of those questions which comes to mind when going for a mountaineering course in India. 
Having done my &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2009/04/11/basic-mountaineering-course-hmi/&quot;&gt;BMC from HMI&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2014/10/14/advance-mountaineering-course-nim/&quot;&gt;AMC from NIM&lt;/a&gt;, I got some idea about the training in these two institutes. 
Here is what I thought of HMI and NIM in terms of :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;organization&quot;&gt;Organization&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both HMI and NIM are run by Ministry of Defence, GOI in collaboration
with respective state governments. So, in terms and objective and
philosophy and in training programs both are same. In my personal
opinion, the past principals and the present principal (Col. Ajay
Kothiyal) of NIM  seem more active and devoted to the institute. NIM
played major role in rescue and rehabilitation work in the time 2013
Uttarakhand disaster. This was also widely covered in media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rock-climbing-area&quot;&gt;Rock Climbing area&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest asset of NIM is that it has a vast rock climbing area in
Tekhla. In this area, there are variety of rock features of varying
degree of difficulty. Trainees have plenty of time to practice rock
climbing techniques on these features. In HMI, there weren’t much rock
faces to climb. For rock climbing, it has Tenzing Rock and Gombu Rock in
the outskirts of Darjeeling. They try to compensate this later in the
course with the big boulders available around the base camp. So rest of
the training in rock craft happens in Base camp area of HMI which is in
Chaurikhang, Sikkim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMI’s artificial wall seem definitely bigger than those in NIM and
everything else is more or less same. Maybe because HMI installed these
walls after NIM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;glacier-for-training-of-ice-climbing-techniques&quot;&gt;Glacier for training of ice climbing techniques&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rathong glacier, training area of HMI has lot more ice walls to
practice than the Dokrani glacier of NIM. Both the glaciers are receding
very fast and trainees need to walk to the training area everyday which
takes some time and energy. Dokrani glacier of NIM, has lot of moraine
covering the ice walls and around the snout of the glacier where most of
the training happens there isn’t much blue ice. I saw plenty of smoking
blue ice in Rathong glacier. It has big fields of blue ice around the
training area. Although advance courses in NIM goes to a different
training area upwards in the glacier for 2 days for their advance ice
craft which has sufficient ice walls and relatively cleaner ice.
Overall, in terms of ice walls available on which we get to train, HMI
has lot better than NIM. Maybe in future, NIM may think of to change the
base camp to get better area for ice craft. It would be more appropriate
for NIM, to move the base camp to the place where they have their
advance base camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;technical-equipments-and-training&quot;&gt;Technical Equipments and Training&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was unanimously established among my course-mates of AMC who did
their BMC from HMI that NIM provides more and advance technical
equipments than HMI. In case of HMI advance techniques or use of advance
equipments are mostly demonstrated by instructors but in NIM you’ll get
a chance to practice with/on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;trek-to-base-camp&quot;&gt;Trek to Base Camp&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a fact that, to reach the base camp; the trek in HMI is tougher
than that in NIM. In both institutes, it takes 3 days to reach base
camp. The trek in HMI goes on relatively higher altitude than NIM and
are longer on everyday. Situated on higher altitude than NIM, the base
camp of HMI offers more splendid view of surrounding peaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;accomodation&quot;&gt;Accomodation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hostel of HMI and NIM are both well maintained and have all the
required facilities. If you are pursuing basic course, you get to stay
in barrack made of metal sheets and wood in HMI. It’s all tent in NIM
for both basic and advance courses outside the campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;location-of-institute&quot;&gt;Location of Institute&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, roaming in and around Darjeeling has better experience
than Uttarkashi. So, location wise, HMI wins and it also has bigger area
with a zoo in it’s campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;hmi-contact-info&quot;&gt;HMI Contact Info:&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;POSTAL ADDRESS&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
PRINCIPAL &lt;br /&gt;
Himalayan Mountaineering Institute &lt;br /&gt;
Jawahar Parvat&lt;br /&gt;
Darjeeling-734 101 (WB), India&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
TRAINING OFFICE: 0354 2254087/2254299 &lt;br /&gt;
PRINCIPAL : 91 354 2254083&lt;br /&gt;
FAX No:91 354 2253760&lt;br /&gt;
Email: hmi_darj@rediffmail.com/hmidarj@gmail.com &lt;br /&gt;
Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://hmidarjeeling.com/&quot;&gt;https://hmidarjeeling.com/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;nim-contact-info&quot;&gt;NIM Contact Info&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;POSTAL ADDRESS&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
PRINCIPAL, &lt;br /&gt;
Nehru Institute Of Mountaineering &lt;br /&gt;
Uttarkashi - 249193, &lt;br /&gt;
Uttarakhand (India) &lt;br /&gt;
Tel: +911374 - 222123, 224663, 223580 &lt;br /&gt;
Fax: +911374 - 222344 &lt;br /&gt;
Email: nimutk2004@gmail.com &lt;br /&gt;
Website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nimindia.net/&quot;&gt;http://www.nimindia.net/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2014/10/22/hmi-darjeeling-vs-nim-uttarkashi/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2014/10/22/hmi-darjeeling-vs-nim-uttarkashi/</guid>
        
        <category>Darjeeling</category>
        
        <category>Uttarkashi</category>
        
        <category>BMC</category>
        
        <category>NIM</category>
        
        <category>HMI</category>
        
        <category>AMC</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>mountaineering</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Advance Mountaineering Course, NIM</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After doing Basic Mountaineering Course from HMI, Darjeeling in 2009;
whenever I thought of doing Advance Mountaineering Course it was always
difficult to squeeze out one month time from job. After around 4 years
of job when I was firm that I’ll do it at any cost and it’s now or
never, I chose &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nimindia.net/&quot;&gt;NIM, Uttarkashi&lt;/a&gt;. Mostly
because it was giving me chance to explore different part of Himalayas
and also because I’d heard that NIM has better equipments and focuses
more on technical aspect of training. I applied in June 2013, but due to
long queue I had to accept my enrollment in 148th AMC which was in
September 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NIM is considered to be one of the best mountaineering institutes in
Asia which is run by Ministry Of Defense, India and has similar
organizational structure as HMI, Darjeeling or JIM, Pahalgam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived Uttarkashi on 12th September 2014, a day before the date of
course commencement. An institute bus was waiting at Uttarkashi bus
stand in the afternoon. After some name check at temporary reception
made at Bhandari Hotel, Uttarkashi , a bus full of students left for the
institute. We checked ourselves in the institute hostel (Tapovan). A
prep talk was scheduled that evening which introduced us about schedule,
and dos and don’t of the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The A.M.C. of 28 days in NIM is typically divided in 4 phases:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rock Craft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ice Craft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Snow Craft&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Height Gain &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;phase-1-rock-craft&quot;&gt;Phase 1: Rock Craft&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-1&quot;&gt;Day 1&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the first day of course, there was an early morning P.T. session. All
39 of us were divided in different groups aka ropes; each 5 or 6 person
strong. Our rope instructor was Subhash Thakur from Himachal Pradesh.
After lunch time everybody was issued with personal, technical and
common equipments. Two climbing ropes were also issued per rope which we
the rope members will take turns to carry for the remainder of the
course. Later that day, there was only theory classes on expedition
planning and first aid in auditorium. We’re told that we need make a
file for expedition planning and submit it at the end of the course. One
of the aim of the course is to make leaders in mountaineering so
planning an expedition is something everybody should be aware of. Each
ropes were given a peak for which they were to plan an expedition and
prepare a report. Some of the information e.g. rate list of equipments
etc were provided by instructors to each rope and information about the
peak is supposed to be gathered from books in NIM library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-2&quot;&gt;Day 2&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This day, we went for a hill walk on a nearby hill with all of our
issued gears in rucksack. This walk was all ascent, ascent and ascent.
After hill walk there was session for revision of knots. Later on that
day, all of were allowed to go out for shopping for necessary equipments
like sunglasses, sunscreen lotions, poncho etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-3-to-day-6&quot;&gt;Day 3 to Day 6&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These four days we trekked to Tekhla rock climbing area which is around
8-9 km from institute as told. We carried all the issued load these 4
days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1968/44380244735_5aeb81f670_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Walk to Tekhla Rock Climbing Area&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Trek to Tekhla Rock Climbing Area&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was told that few AMC batches used to camp in Tekhla for five days.
Beware of leeches here. NIM has vast and beautiful area for rock
climbing and it is far better than the rock climbing area of HMI in my
opinion. We used to have our rock climbing lectures, demonstrations and
practices here whole day. These tekhla days allowed us to learn and
practice many techniques of rock craft.
These five days, we used to to start our trek early morning to Tekhla.
When we reach there we do some stretching exercises and then there was
breakfast. After breakfast we start our rock climbing lessons with our
instructors at 9:30 AM. We get lunch at 1 PM in Tekhla itself and
continued our training till 5 PM. We used to get back to our institute
by bus in evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-7&quot;&gt;Day 7&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On day 7 after morning P.T. we did some climbing on different indoor and
outdoor artificial walls in the institute. It was relatively easier and
a fun day for everybody.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-8&quot;&gt;Day 8&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1963/44380245155_f5749cab98_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tyrolean Traverse @ Asiganga river&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Tyrolean Traverse @ Asiganga river&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was river crossing practice day. We went to a nearby village by bus
on the bank of Asi ganga river. Here we were taught to make and use
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tyrolean_traverse&quot;&gt;tyrolean traverse&lt;/a&gt;.
Later that day we were given time to try our snow boots and crampons so
that we get it changed if they doesn’t fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-9&quot;&gt;Day 9&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This day, we left the NIM campus for first camp in Tela. This day we
started our journey by bus from NIM campus early morning after offering
prayers in the temple of NIM campus to Bukki which is on the way to
Gangotri. During this bus journey, we could witness the aftermath of
previous year Uttarakhand disaster. It took around 2 hours to reach
Bukki by bus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;From Bukki, we’ll be trekking through Dingad Valley, named so after a
glacial stream Dingad (gad=stream)  originating from Dokrani Bamak
(bamak = glacier)  which is our training area. The stream originating
from the glacier’s melting water later joins many other snow / ice
melted streams and finally merges into Bhagirathi river near Bukki
village. Bukki village is 2 km from the bus terminus situated on the
right bank of Bhagirathi river. On way to Dokriani glacier, one has to
walk 23 km from the road (Bukki village). After crossing the Bhagirathi
river a footpath flows along the steep mountain slopes up to Tela camp
(2500 m), from Tela to Gujjar hut a 12 km run along the Dingad stream is
a route offered to cross the several up and down ridges, many small and
big streams and dense mixed forests of deodar, rhododendron (burans),
oak, pine etc. provide an atmosphere of perfect peace and tranquility.
Gujjar Hut (a summer camp of Gujjars with their cattles) is located at a
height of 3500 m, just 5 km below the Dokriani glacier. Gujjar Hut is
the gateway of the valley.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The valley has a gentle slope with different land features formed by
the glacier and surrounded by snow-covered peaks. This place is good for
camping and one can walk up to the glacier and adjoining areas and climb
the small peaks. Only Gujjar huts and a base camp (near the glacier
snout) of Wadia Institute of Himalayan Geology, Dehradun lie on the way.
The best season to visit is through out summer and autumn. Besides the
above two glaciers, Kedar, Rudugaira and Jaonli are some other glaciers
which are approachable by the same way.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started our trek to Tela camping site (altitude 8200 ft. )from Bhuki
around 10 AM.This trek is around 8 kms. This was decent trek through
dense jungles and was not very tiring except the last few minutes which
was long continuous ascent.  Daily treks to Tekhla had made us stronger.
We reached Tel camp around 1:30 PM and after little cooling down
stretching exercises we had our lunch prepared by NIM cooking staff.
Later we pitched our tents and went for acclimatization walk to a nearby
hill in the evening. It was a beautiful walk through jungle which has
meadows and at the top there was beautiful view of surroundings. At Tel
near our campsite there were few houses of Gujjars and they have cattles
which were tied nearby. Here there is also a small tower installed by
Wadia Institute, Dehradun for weather monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-10&quot;&gt;Day 10&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1940/44380246105_50632cf681_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Near Khera Taal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Near Khera Taal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This day we had this very long trek from Tel camp to Gujjar Hut
(altitude 11200 ft.). It counts as toughest day so far. We started
around 7:30 AM after cleaning Tel campsite and reached Gujjar Hut at
2:30 PM. From Gujjar hut, we started getting nice view of nearby peaks
like Jaonli (6630 meters). The place Gujjar hut was given this name
because of few huts of Gujjars nearby who stay here in summers. We went
for our acclimatization walk to nearby lake Khera Tal (Serpent Lake)
which is a small lake between a vast and very beautiful meadow. Vast
ground surrounded by tall trees with an opens on one side for
magnificent view of peaks Jaonli (6630 meters) and DKD-II (5670 meters).
DKD-II is the peak which we hoped to climb as part of our height gain
phase later in this course. Khera in local language means snake. There
is a story about this lake and a snake living around it which was
previously poisoning a nearby stream Hurra Nala (Nala = a stream )  and
thereby causing deaths in the village which depended on it. There is
also a temple nearby the lake. People of Bhuki village sometimes come
here to offer prayers and stay here overnight. In Feb-April this whole
area is covered with snow. We were told that in month of June, this
valley is full of flowers and there are many butterflies around here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-11&quot;&gt;Day 11&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1961/44569945224_52c42c8494_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Base Camp&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Base Camp&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In morning at Gujjar Hut, we had a class of map reading and get to
practice using GPS devices. Everybody was given three co-ordinates to
point out on map and follow these points using GPS device. These points
were on the way to NIM Base Camp (12300 ft.). Every rope moved ahead
with their instructors to Base Camp with the routes set using three
waypoints given. This trek is relatively small and is around 2.5 km.
Treeline vanishes on the way and we could see only shrubs around there.
After reaching base camp, we pitched our tents and did some cleaning of
the area, cut the grass etc. There was not much for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;phase-2-ice-craft&quot;&gt;Phase 2: Ice Craft&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-1213&quot;&gt;Day 12,13&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this day, our training of ice craft started. The Dokrani glacier is
bit far from base camp. Seems as if glacier has receded a lot. Groups barely found decent walls to
practice. All of the ice was covered with moraine. We cleaned it up for
practicing. Our instructor Subhash Sir found a decent wall to practice
we practiced different climbing positions on ice and climbing using ice
pitons etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1959/43477444630_42202bfb22_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Base Camp Ice climbing practice&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Base Camp Ice climbing practice&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, NIM’s ice craft area is much less in comparison of HMI.
It may be the time, when NIM may have to shift the base camp further up
to Advance Base Camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two days. it was mostly revision of  ice craft taught in basic
course. In the second half on the second day, we were involved in
checking of tents, which we’ll be carrying to advance base camp (ABC) be
used in high altitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-14&quot;&gt;Day 14&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1950/44569945654_256880b5d1_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Advance Base Camp&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Advance Base Camp without snow&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we ferried load from base camp to advance base camp (13500 ft.).
With fairly heavy load the trek was tiring and I was huffing and puffing
on the way. It like the last flat piece of of very picturesque land in
cirque ahead. The surroundings form an amphitheater of mountains which
from north-east-south constitutes of Machha ki Dhar, Jaonli, Draupadi ka
Daanda, Choro ki Dhar and Rakhua Top. We dumped all the load like food
items, tents etc in a shelter made of rock and came back to the base
camp. It felt like a long walk. Back in the base camp this day, we had a
lecture on mountain terminology after lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-15&quot;&gt;Day 15&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We moved to ABC with our personal belongings. We were allowed to leave
few of our things which we thought would not be required above in ABC
and further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1917/43477444130_28e21aa375_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking towards BC, from ABC&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Looking towards BC, from ABC&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reached ABC at 10:30 AM after leaving and wrapping up tents at base
camp past 8 AM. After some stretching exercises, we started pitching our
tents. We erected volleyball net and a stone shelter where kitchen staff
could heat water for us. Everybody was entitled for one hot bottle of
water every morning and evening for drinking purposes at base camp and
advance base camp. It was a lot of fun playing volleyball at ABC in the
surroundings it offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1925/44569947804_9c381b036d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dokrani glacier: Further ahead is our training area&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Dokrani glacier: Further ahead is our training area&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-16-17&quot;&gt;Day 16, 17&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started the day by marching up to upper part of Dokrani glacier. Most
of the trek is on moraine and glacier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1964/44569946954_eabcc92f4e_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Advance Ice Craft @ Dokrani Glacier&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Advance Ice Craft @ Dokrani Glacier&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training area is not very far from the campsite and there are ample ice
walls for all of us to practice. After demonstration of technique by our
instructors, we practiced the same.
We learned few advanced ice climbing techniques. This includes two piton
climbing, aid climbing on ice wall. In month of September, there wasn’t
much snow on these ice walls. Very soon gloves would get and dirty with
fast melting ice and supra glacial moraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1971/31418060778_b1a9c7c0e9_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was continuously hailing in the in the second half of the day. It
started snowing heavily in the evening which lasted till late night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1966/31418061288_096d8a312d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Advance Ice craft Training&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Advance Ice craft Training&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the duration of our stay at base camp we took ropewise turns to
prepare dinner our everybody, which was part of our training as told.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also had a class on high altitude cooking with different kind of
fuels and stoves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;phase-3-snow-craft&quot;&gt;Phase 3: Snow Craft&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-18&quot;&gt;Day 18&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1952/31418060328_4f187a9c56_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Out tents in ABC in the morning after snow&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Out tents in ABC in the morning after snow&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since our phases of rock and ice craft was over, it was turn of snow
craft. In our time there wasn’t much snow. It was decided to practice
snow craft on thin layer of packed snow patch with elevation of arounf
60 to 70 on a ridge of Machha ki Dhar which had ice beneath. Few people
including me found difficult to maintain balance and practice on this
patch. I had a fall which I couldn’t arrest with ice axe while
practicing and twisted my ankle. It wasn’t severe, but it got me
limping. It snowed again later in the afternoon. This completes our
training part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;phase-4-height-gain&quot;&gt;Phase 4: Height Gain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-19&quot;&gt;Day 19&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our height gain we hoped to summit DKD-II if weather allowed. We
were warned that if weather doesn’t allow we may not be able to reach
the summit and return halfway. Anyway at this we ferried load to our
Camp 1 (15800 ft.) which was also our summit camp. Loads included high
altitude tents butane gas cans, burners, technical gears and other
eatables.  It was an arduous task to ascent on continuous ice and
moraine. I had OTG (over the glass) snow goggles which were too foggy to
see and made the trek difficult. I had to walk without snow goggles most
of the time. After reaching there, we set up tents for kitchen and store
room and dumped our loads. The camp 1 area is a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cirque&quot;&gt;cwm&lt;/a&gt; (pronounced &lt;em&gt;coom&lt;/em&gt;). 
This is a relatively flat area completely on glacier and many crevasses around.
We could see all kinds of features of ice which we were told around. Ice
tables, serac, bergschrund, crevasses, overhanging glaciers. If we’re
facing towards east, we had DKD on our right, but summit wasn’t visible
from there. Jaonli was towards north or our left. Jaonli (6632 meters)
seemed so close as if we could walk over the summit. But standard way to
the Jaonli was from behind (relatively may be from north face). The
glaciers from Jaonli and DKD meet here to form the Dokrani glacier
(around 5 km long).
While returning from camp 1, weather got really bad. It was complete
whiteout. We trekked back in continuous snowfall. Drenched in sweat from
inside and wet from outside with snow and hail, we walked back to
advance base camp. After seeing this weather I really saw the dwindling
chance for the summit, as there was now a good chance that we may not be
going for the summit. If the weather doesn’t clear soon, our chance to
summit DKD is going to be feeble. It snowed whole day. Windproofs were
completely wet. I kept my half wet clothes etc in sleeping bag to keep
them warm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-20&quot;&gt;Day 20&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We packed our bags early morning from ABC and did routine cleaning of
tent area before leaving. We reached camp 1 around 10:30 AM and started
pitching our tents on the glacier. There was some snow over the ice
which we beat to make the area for tent flat. We were getting tired
easily with heavy movement like lifting stones for preparing the camp
and other staff tents, kitchen etc. We could hear the water flowing
through the deep crevasses. There was hole dug in the ice which stored
some melted water in the day which we used for cooking maggi for lunch
and warming water. Each tent which accommodated some 5 people was given
a butane stove for cooking. With tents facing to each other on the ice
in a row, and everybody cooking outside; it looked like as if we’ve
established a small market on the glacier. After this, few handpicked
people (around 6 to 7) along with two instructors left for the recce and
route opening for tomorrow’s summit attempt. Following them, rest of us
also left for making the moraine part of route a bit stable. We all made
cairns and fixed loose rocks along the way in the evening. We were told
that we’ll have to wake up at 2 AM and leave for the summit attempt at 4
AM sharp. Anybody gets late will be left there only. It was freezing
cold in the night inside the tent. There wasn’t much space inside the
tent and we kept our snow boots in the vestibule. Thinking of going to
loo instilled fear. There wasn’t much time to sleep. I was guessing the
time between short naps. Our tent was continuously making flapping
sounds in wind. In night we could hear continuous deep noises of glacier
moving beneath us. I couldn’t sleep in night. Sleeping bag got wet from
one side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-21&quot;&gt;Day 21&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1939/31418060488_5e6e0e71a9_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Summit walk&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Summit walk&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We woke up in hurry after 2 AM and prepared ourselves for summit attempt.
Chilling wind was blowing as we equipped ourselves with the harness set
and other technical gear. I kept the breakfast in the bag and left for
the summit attempt. It was dark and everybody was wearing head torches. 
We started the ascent in the lateral moraine spanning high up towards
our way with the helps of cairns established last evening. Everybody was
walking briskly as if there was a very narrow time window for the summit.
We’re told that if somebody gets too late he may have to return from
there only. After completing the ascent on moraine we put on crampons to
walk on the ice. It looked very beautiful to see these many people
ascending through the icy ridge with head-torches in the night.
Everybody was walking silently. The cold and the wind was making talking
difficult. At dawn, we reached a relatively flat area full of snow from
where we could the peak of DKD-II. Behind us we could see the peaks of
Gangotri valley. It was a magnificent view with the rising sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1907/44569946544_c7ff9c5642_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sunrise @ Summit&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sun rise @ Summit&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ahead of us ropes were being fixed by our ropemate Deepak Rana and our
instructor Subhash Thakur. It was a steep climb with unfathomable snow.
It was very difficult to walk on the steep ascent this much powdery
snow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1926/44569946234_79fb03081b_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Summit&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Summit&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We self anchored ourselves to the established fixed rope and started the
ascent. Trying to move ahead one step was making slide down further. But
somehow, I learned the trick to make proper steps and walk up. The sun
was rising. There were few crevsses hidden in deep snow which opened up
their faces with people moving over. Everybody was moving slow. At some
point we had to go one by one. After more than an hour of steep climb on
snow like quick sand I could see the last rope to the summit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1906/44569944794_8dd3a30740_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;View from DKD-II&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View from DKD-II&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reached there around 8:15 AM. Opening the route, Deepak and Subhash
sir reached there around 7:45 am.We congratulated each other for our
successfully summit. It was blissful moment. We could the surrounding
peaks protruding upside from the quilt of clouds. Senior instructor
Jagmohan Singh Rawat introduced us to the surrounding peaks. We could
see Shrikanth, Bandarpoonch Range, Kala Nag, Rudragaira, Gangotri Range, 
Jaonli, Nanda Devi, Kedar Dome, Kedarnath Valley DKD-I.
After that everybody got busy posing and clicking pictures. After some
15-20 mins, we started our descent. It was fairly difficult to
descending in steps in such steep snow. When we climbed down the major
part part, we were given few mins break for breakfast. There wasn’t any
break before that. Common equipments like ropes changed hands and we
started climbing down with happiness on our faces. While we were
climbing down we could see the basic course guys at our camp 1, who were
there for there height gain phase. At cam 1, we were congratulated by
the kitchen staff and Chief Instructor for our successful climb. 
Everybody was completely exhausted after this arduous climb.After
reaching I pulled out the packed breakfast and shared it with my
ropemates. In our rope, I and one of my ropemate were little feverish
and went back to sleep. Everybody was really happy that we’ll  be going
back to base camp tomorrow. Most of us were planning a grand party after
this course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-21-1&quot;&gt;Day 21&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wrapped up our camp 1 and cleaned up the tent area. Trekked back to
base camp passing through advance base camp and depositing the technical
and other stuff  issued for camp 1. At base camp, we were greeted by all
the basic course instructors and basic course guys who were clapping for
our us. They congratulated us for our successful summit. We pitched our
tents at base camp and cleaned and dried wet equipments clothes etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-22&quot;&gt;Day 22&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was exam day. There were few objective and few short answer
subjective questions. After that we were competing for our map reading
exam. We’re given 2 points to which we had to reach. We were mostly
running as one point was at Gujjar Hut and second was little off on the
way to ABC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-23-24&quot;&gt;Day 23, 24&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trekking back first from BC to Tela and then Tela to Bhuki. We were all
happy to see other people and civilization. A bus from NIM was waiting
to take us to the institute. It was like 10 in the morning. Soon after
reaching there most of us got busy with writing the expedition report
which had to be submitted the next day. After bath and lunch in the
institute we submitted our equipments. In evening, we were allowed to go
to the market to get the expedition report printed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;day-25-to-end-of-course&quot;&gt;Day 25 to end of course&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had graduation ceremony and there was a cultural event in which our
course-mates participated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;nim-contact-info&quot;&gt;NIM Contact Info&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;POSTAL ADDRESS&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
PRINCIPAL,&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nimindia.net/&quot;&gt;Nehru Institute Of Mountaineering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Uttarkashi - 249193,&lt;br /&gt;
Uttarakhand (India)&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Tel: +911374 - 222123, 224663, 223580&lt;br /&gt;
Fax: +911374 - 222344&lt;br /&gt;
Email: nimutk2004@gmail.com&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2014/10/14/advance-mountaineering-course-nim/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2014/10/14/advance-mountaineering-course-nim/</guid>
        
        <category>AMC</category>
        
        <category>NIM</category>
        
        <category>Uttarkashi</category>
        
        
        <category>course</category>
        
        <category>organised</category>
        
        <category>mountaineering</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
