<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>अथातो घुमक्कड़ जिज्ञासा</title>
    <description>Eternal Curiousity Of Traveler's Mind.</description>
    <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 09:32:40 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 09:32:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pindari Trek</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2018/10/23/pindari-glacier/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2018/10/23/pindari-glacier/</guid>
        
        <category>bageshwar</category>
        
        <category>pindari</category>
        
        <category>khati</category>
        
        <category>jaikuni</category>
        
        <category>phurkiya</category>
        
        <category>kharkiya</category>
        
        <category>kapkot</category>
        
        <category>glacier</category>
        
        <category>nand khat</category>
        
        <category>sundardhunga</category>
        
        <category>kafni</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pin Parvati Pass Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It was around midnight when I woke up with the sound of susurration. Eyes closed, I hoped it to be the glacial stream flowing nearby. I was wide awake, when I heard someone beating on the tent nearby. There was no doubt that it was snowfall. Our plan to cross the Pin Parvati pass tomorrow was in serious jeopardy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since past few years, I had been looking forward to go on Pin Parvati Pass trek. In fact, whenever my friends offered me come along to Kheerganga or Kasol, I had been politely declining by telling them that I’ll walk on that trail only when I am going for Pin Parvati Pass. I’ve always loved crossing the passes because of the transitions it offers in terms of the culture and sometimes landscapes. It has always felt to me like crossing from one country to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pin Parvati Pass, is one of those treks in the Himalayas which offers a variety of landscapes, chance to witness different cultures and of course a decent enough altitude. It is supposed to be difficult than any other normal Himalayan trek because of the long trail and crevasses near the pass. I had been to Tarsar Marsar Lake just a few days ago. I still had some leaves left and it was an apt time for going on such a trek. It’s mid-September and trekking season in the Himalayas was nearing to an end. Very few organizations were running this trek. I chose to go with Bikat because I had been to Bali Pass with them before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;start-of-the-trek&quot;&gt;Start of the trek&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was the last one to reach Barsheni. Rohit, our trek leader was waiting for me at Pulga Dam. After a short hike, we reached Kalga, a small village from where we were to start this trek the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The dam at Pulga is part of Parbati Hydroelectric Project (Stage-II). It is a run-of-the-river scheme proposed to harness the hydro potential of the lower reaches of the river Parbati. The river is proposed to be diverted with a Concrete Gravity Dam at Village Pulga in Parbati valley through 31.52 Km long Head Race Tunnel and the Power House shall be located at village Suind in Sainj valley. Thus the gross head of 863 m between Pulga and Suind will be utilized for generating 800MW power. The diverted discharge of the river Parbati has been further augmented by diverting the discharge of various nullahs falling along the HRT alignment.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a round of introduction among trek mates. In our introduction, it was noticeable that most people are experienced trekkers. Some had a very impressive list of treks in their kitties and some had mountaineering experience as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next morning before starting for Kheerganga, the first camping site; we were introduced to our trek guides Hari and Chetramji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial 6 days are supposed to 5-6 hours of walk with not more than 500 meters of altitude gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started from Kalga, with Parbati river on our left. On the other side of the river which receives more sunlight in the morning, Nakthan village. There were patches of cannabis plantation on the other side of the river.
From Kalga, the trail climbs to a temple and small dhaba at Rudra-Nag waterfall, which is named after its resemblance of a snake. Our guide Hari tells us that local &lt;em&gt;Devi-Devta&lt;/em&gt;(deities) come for a bath every year. Beyond Rudra-Nag waterfall, the trail ascends further through thick pine forests to the spiritual site of Kheerganga where Shiva is said to have meditated for 3000 years. The hot springs at Kheerganga are extremely important for Hindu and Sikh pilgrims as well as many others who believe the waters have sacred healing properties. The trail from Kalga to Kheerganga was broken at few places. There are always many people hiking towards Kheerganga. In the afternoon, we went for a bath in hot spring after pitching tents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1955/44600168814_9420f3d3bc_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kheerganga Hot spring&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kheerganga Hot spring&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;khirganga-2789m-to-tunda-bhuj-3285m&quot;&gt;Khirganga (2789m) to Tunda Bhuj (3285m)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1906/44600158944_8ac82b6c65_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vijay measuring thickness of a pine tree&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Vijay measuring thickness of a pine tree&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Kheerganga to Tunda Bhuj (3285m) the Parvati river cuts a steep-sided gorge through the mountains and as the altitude increases, the thick, coniferous forest gradually gives way for patches of meadowland scattered with boulders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1930/43507805430_d7403accc1_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near Tunda Bhuj, on the other side of the river many waterfalls emanating from steep mountains join the river.
On those steep faces, shepherds in search of green pastures for their flock were seen passing across the waterfalls which we wondered if anyone would dare to traverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1957/45324200671_005b23d62a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Waterfalls joining Parbati River&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Waterfalls joining Parbati River from steep slopes of mountains on our left side.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tunda-bhuj-3285m-to-thakur-kuan-3560m&quot;&gt;Tunda Bhuj (3285m) to Thakur Kuan (3560m)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the river flow close to the trail and one could hear the sound of it crashing its way through the rocks. The treeline begins to diminish and only some patches of bushes are to be seen. Along the trail, some Bhoj(Birch) trees could also be seen on the slopes of mountains which gives the name to the Tunda Bhuj campsite. After reaching Thakur Kuan campsite, we went for an acclimatization walk on a nearby hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1962/43507801820_8600d2f355_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Thakur Kuan campsite from nearby hill&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Thakur Kuan campsite from nearby hill&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was another shepherd tent nearby with a big flock of sheep and goats. In our conversation, when we told that we have come from far places to trek in the valley, he was little surprised on why would someone make such effort and spend money to come this far and what is there to gain for us.
Some of us were amused by the expression of faces of sheep and goats made good use of their mobile cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;thakur-kuan-3560m-to-odi-thatch-3879m&quot;&gt;Thakur Kuan (3560m) to Odi Thatch (3879m)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail goes across the river just after few minutes of walk. We had three hurdles to cross, a traverse along the steep rock face by the river and two natural bridges on the river. Our trek leader suggested us that we don our helmets as the traversal of the rock face and crossing the bridge could be tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bridges called as Pandu Pul, is a huge boulder placed right on the river. Local legend says it was placed by Bheem, one among Pandavas. The river flow beneath the rock through the small passage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pccofvns/45274004802/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;Parbati flow beneath the natuaral bridge&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1980/45274004802_77146c3226_b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;576&quot; alt=&quot;Parbati flow beneath the natuaral bridge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rope was fixed on the bridge to prevent any slips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1919/44600165114_20b9363350_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pandu Pul I&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Pandu Pul I&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were also accompanied by a dog who had been following us from Kheerganga, even after several attempts by Hari and Chetramji, our local guides to leave it behind. During our short stops during the trek, many of us esp. Peter and Pratibha could be seen petting her. In return, she joined us for the nice pictures. It was even given a name “Jackie” and upon realizing the gender, some identified her by “Jacqueline” so that the name “Jackie” can still be relevant as hypocorism. Amusing, how we urban people in India, name our dogs. Names like Sheru and Moti become less and less relevant. Anyway, Jackie a faithful mountain dog whom we thought that she may not be able to cross the Pandu-Pul, and this is where we say our goodbye to her, traversed the slippery boulders like a cakewalk to join us. Everyone was cheerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pccofvns/45274005952/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;Jackie crossing Pandu Pul I&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1945/45274005952_b1f22015e5_s.jpg&quot; width=&quot;75&quot; height=&quot;75&quot; alt=&quot;Jackie crossing Pandu Pul I&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After crossing the bridge, the valley opens up and is very wide with a more or less flat ground throughout. Glacial streams from both sides of the valley join the Parbati river. Odi Thatch(thatch = meadow), a wide flat ground by the side of Parbati River, could’ve been our campsite if water source was available in the vicinity. Porters had already gone ahead of Odi Thatch because of unavailability of water near the campsite. We followed them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1941/43507804690_8e2442cd82_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Odi thatch&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Odi thatch&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continued further for an hour for our next camping site which was small flat land between the boulders, by the mountainside and very windy in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1911/44600171324_b65e314123_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Camping site ahead of Odi thatch&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Camping site ahead of Odi thatch&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;odi-thatch-3876-m-to-mantalai-4100m&quot;&gt;Odi Thatch (3876 m) to Mantalai (4100m)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On today’s trail, valley expands further and the Parbati River now on our right side is calmer than before. In fact, we reach a point where the river flows on an almost flat bed of the wide valley creating sandbanks alongside. It is like any big river in plains with pebbles and sand around. In the sunny weather, it felt as if it was some kind of wonderland. Elated by the sight of the valley, we spent some quiet moment by the side of the river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1935/45274006722_5ddaa3ef9c_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;group photo&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Omkar, Anshul, me, Ashish aka RawHash, Vijay, Petri Ultich (Peter), Sanjay Gupta, Chetram, Hari, Kannan Kasturi, Satyajit Patnaik, Pratibha Rahi.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a perfect spot for a group photo and in fact, everyone was posing around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1965/43507803430_f47b77f421_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of us went ahead and some decided to walk barefoot on the riverbed and enjoy while it lasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1919/44600166834_e593c6712a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Everyone wanted to stay a little more.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The wide exapanse of valley and calm flow of Parbati river was intoxicating and satisfying at the same time. Everyone wanted to stay a little more.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1941/43507803850_136caebc96_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Parvati River at its widest&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Parvati River at its widest&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1977/43518884390_8a809352ca_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The valley closes in front of us with snow laden peaks.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The valley closes in front of us with snow laden peaks.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far the weather was with us, but when we were nearing the Mantalai Lake, the starting point of Parbati River, the weather suddenly started closing in on us. It turned cloudy and windy which was giving us chills. While waiting for others, we visited the temple by the lake which houses a Shivling in the open air surrounded by cairns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1919/44600167174_acacc28001_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mantalai Temple and lake behind&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mantalai Temple and lake behind&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we moved towards the next camping site, further up by the lake, a light rain started. As soon as we reached the campsite weather was again clear. Many of us attributed this sudden change in weather to the ritualistic prayers offered at the temple by the lake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1946/44600169604_d5900fcaab_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The sunset was beautiful and the reflection of peaks in the lake drew us to our cameras.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The sunset was beautiful and the reflection of peaks in the lake drew us to our cameras.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mantalai-4100m-to-parbati-base-camp-4940m&quot;&gt;Mantalai (4100m) to Parbati Base Camp (4940m)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weather was clear in the morning, and we were all ready for our highest altitude gain(~ 800m) of the trek. We start by climbing the mountain slope alongside the lake. It is a continuous climb and from the top we get the see the panoramic view of the lake. It was fascinating to see the different colors of small lakes formed in the Mantalai glacier. One would wonder how is it possible that these small lakes are so close to each other but have such difference in color. Some of these ponds seem to have turquoise blue and some were green in color and some had muddy appearance. I wonder about the physics and geology behind that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1955/43507806210_85fb71af65_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Glacial lakes formed in the Mantalai&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Glacial lakes formed in the Mantalai&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After climbing the mountaintop by the lake, we pushed further through the morains crossing a stream coming from the glacier near the pass. The weather was with us so far. It was a bright sunny day when we reached base camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1906/43507806710_5aaea677a5_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Parvati Valley side base camp&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Parvati Valley side base camp&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The campsite was some rocky patch between the boulders just before the thick tabletop like glacier. I took some time to wash in the glacial stream nearby while the sun was still with us. The peak overlooking the Mantalai lake was playing hide and seek in clouds and some of us amused by it, were busy capturing it in a time-lapse video. Sitting on a boulder, Ashish was busy creating a 360-degree view of the campsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were left with only 300m of climb and everything seemed to be in our favor so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around midnight, I woke up with a sound of susurration. I really hoped that sound to be of a stream flowing nearby. Maybe, the sound of the stream is more clear in the night, I thought. This is when I heard someone beating on the tent nearby. My worst fears had come true. It is snowfall! I had been waking every hour since then and the continued snowfall was adding to my fears. In such weather, they might actually decide to turn back and not cross the pass. It would’ve disappointing to turn back after coming this far and after so many days of trekking. I hoped that they decide to use the reserve day which we had in our plan if it is not advisable to cross the pass tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1975/45274706342_9996331b44_b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Base camp in morning&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Base camp in morning&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;parbati-base-camp-4940m-via-pin-parbati-pass-5300m-to-shepherds-camp--4300m&quot;&gt;Parbati Base Camp (4940m) via Pin Parbati Pass (5300m) to Shepherds camp (~ 4300m)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was all rocky and dry yesterday, was covered with snow in the morning. Snowfall was incessant. Rohit, Hari, and Chetramji decided to march ahead instead of waiting the snow out. I overheard someone saying that we don’t have much kerosene oil left with us as well and going back will take longer. It is better to cross the pass before snow piles on. My hands were freezing in unpitching the tents and my thin fleece gloves were not helping either. We continued as per the plan. Hari was leading the way prodding along with a stick. After a few minutes on the snow, when glacier started, he suggested that we rope ourselves up as it’s become very difficult to identify the crevasses. It would’ve slowed the whole group if everyone was roped up, so three of us (Rohit, Har and me) roped up to move ahead making way for others. Hari was leading the way. It was complete whiteout below the pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1971/43507800510_23cdf4ce58_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Roped up&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After negotiating the first crevasse, Cheeku who was the leader of the porter group was called upon by Hari to lead the way. Cheeku was crossing this pass sixth time this year. He knew this terrain as a back of his hand and was very instrumental in identifying the path and crevasses too. However, some porters who went ahead behind Cheeku did go in the crevasse but were pulled out in time. We were trying our best to negotiate the crevasses with the support of the makeshift arrangement of fixed ropes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1957/44600162944_55bddf87c0_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Porters marching ahead in green and yellow&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Porters marching ahead in green and yellow&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While working with the ropes, my thin fleece gloves were completely wet and I had to squeeze the water out of the gloves. It was freezing, and I hoped I didn’t get frostbite. Around 11:30, we touched the pass. There wasn’t much to see around in this incessant snowfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1961/45274002712_1df192d218_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;At Pin Parvati Pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;At Pin Parvati Pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a long way ahead, so we hurried towards the other side of the pass in Pin Valley without staying much on the pass. There are many crevasses in the glacier at this side of the pass as well and these were now completely hidden by the snowfall. Whenever Cheeku identified a crevasse, a shout goes out to us three to take up positions on both sides of crevasse to fix the rope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had already decided to skip the usual camping site (Pin Basecamp) and keep going down to reach the next one, Shepherd’s camp. By the time we crossed the Pin river, our shoes and clothes were completely wet and it was becoming difficult to stand. I didn’t even bother to remove the socks to cross the river. It was better to keep walking to keep warm. When we reached the campsite, the dinner tent was set up. A stove was put to keep us warm. Snowfall was nowhere to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had hoped that Spiti would be dry at this time of year, but the weather was defying all the odds. We didn’t want to bother with pitching our tents and everyone except few decided to spend the night in dinner tent. In the night, Rohit came to us and said that he will start early next morning for Mudh and try to arrange a conveyance to pick others midway. I asked Rohit if I can be of any help and can accompany him to which he said yes. Before sleeping, I noticed that my sleeping bag along with everyone others was soaking wet too. I had put it in a dry pack which didn’t help. For tomorrow, we had decided to go to Mudh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;shepherds-camp--4300m-to-mudh-3800-m&quot;&gt;Shepherds Camp (~ 4300m) to Mudh (3800 m)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per the plan, I started with Rohit around 8:30 towards Mudh. There was someone from porter group as well to show us the way. Hari and Chetramji were to follow the course with other members after some time. We needed to hurry to reach Mudh, else vehicle wouldn’t reach near the roadhead in time to pick others. The sandy and fragile soil in the mountains of Spiti Valley were frequently showing signs of landslide and sometimes we had to cross active landslides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1926/43508483600_6f2a0f4c02_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our shoes were already wet and clothes were wet again. Around 11:30 we touched the roadhead. This is under construction road in the valley, and Mudh village is way ahead. Some more kilometers ahead from roadhead, there is a &lt;em&gt;nullah&lt;/em&gt; (Pagal Nala) which flows over the road and the stream is so ferocious and strong that vehicles coming from Mudh can’t cross this stretch. We were supposed to bring the vehicle to this point. We crossed the Pagal Nala with on a small makeshift footover bridge down the stream. We had reached a landmark. On a normal day, this trek would’ve successfully ended here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started freezing when we stopped for lunch near Pagal Nallah. Ahead on the road of Pagal Nala, there were many small landslides and we wondered if a vehicle could reach here or not. It was a long and arduous walk and felt tougher than yesterday. Today was a definitely a long stretch, more than 25KM and it was again freezing in the afternoon.
After hours of walking on the road along with Pin River, Mudh village was finally on the sight. Nevertheless, it took another hour to reach the village.
There was another wide and ferocious stream was waiting for us just before the village. The sheer muddy color and the sound of it sent chills down the spine. Rohit took the lead and we held each other’s hand to cross the stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reached Mudh around 3:30 PM. The only phone(BSNL satellite phone) available in the village wasn’t working. It had been snowing in the valley since last two days and phone works with solar-powered batteries only, which are dead by now. We asked the owner of the public telephone, who also owned a homestay (Tara) for help in arranging a vehicle to pick others along the trail. People in the village were surprised to listen to our story and even enquired if someone is already dead. Some went on to suggest that we were foolish to cross the pass. There were others stuck since 2 days waiting to go anywhere outside the village. The owner of Tara cafe muttered, “&lt;em&gt;agar Gadi nhi gayi to wo log to mar jayenge&lt;/em&gt;”. He rushed to arrange two tractors and a JCB excavator to clear up the road. Rohit was frantically trying to contact Hari over the walkie-talkie. He was able to connect to Hari around 5:30 and Hari told us that everyone is safe. By 6:30, 3 more of trek mates along with some porters have arrived in the village but many were still left way behind. I was told by these guys that the tractor won’t be able to come back as there had been recent landslides. The helpful people of the village were waiting with tea and hot water on the road. They immediately took these guys in their homes and even offered dry clothes.  It was already dark. I went with the JCB excavator again to see if I can be any help. I was already feeling guilty for not going along with the tractor. Riding the JCB, wading through the raging nullah; we caught up the tractors around a kilometer ahead waiting for help to come. There were two big landslides completely covering the road. While JCB started clearing the road, I walked ahead to see others. The guys on tractor told that everyone else has taken a shortcut to reach the village and must’ve reached the village by now. These guys were not willing to leave the tractor behind on the road in fear of landslides which may occur anywhere in the stretch. I waited till the JCB cleared the road and tractors (one without a headlight) were shown its way to the village. When I reached village again, everyone had reached already. The dog Jackie, who was following us had also reached in the village running behind the tractor and was safe in the village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;two-days-of-waiting-in-mudh-village&quot;&gt;Two Days of waiting in Mudh Village&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1970/43507800260_509e232ee3_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A view from Mudh village after weather clears&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A view from Mudh village after weather clears&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The snowfall had never stopped, but Rohit was able to convey the information about our safety the next day. We started getting news about the havoc this weather had created. The roads were closed everywhere and we had no other option than to wait till the road to Kaza(A popular place in Spiti and headquarter of Spiti subdivision) opens. These two days, we had a good time in the village enjoying what was available for us. After a day, the cafe was serving only their homestay guests as food had become scarce in the village. The weather was now clear after two days in Mudh. The road was getting repaired and we made our way to Kaza. The road to Manali via Rohtang pass was broken at many places and there was no sign of it getting repaired in near future. The road to Shimla via, Reckong Peo was open the next day and we made our way home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this last stretch of my road trip, I was heading back having collected the most memorable and cherishable memories, must say, a long due present to my own self.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2018/09/30/pin-parvati-pass/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2018/09/30/pin-parvati-pass/</guid>
        
        <category>kullu</category>
        
        <category>spiti</category>
        
        <category>kaza</category>
        
        <category>mudh</category>
        
        <category>himachal</category>
        
        <category>manali</category>
        
        <category>sangla</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        
        <category>organised</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Tarsar Marsar Lakes Trek</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2018/09/05/tarsar-marsar-lakes-trek/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2018/09/05/tarsar-marsar-lakes-trek/</guid>
        
        <category>kashmir</category>
        
        <category>pahalgam</category>
        
        <category>tarsar</category>
        
        <category>kohloi</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        <category>anantnag</category>
        
        
        <category>organised</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gomukh Tapovan Trek</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2018/06/07/gomukh-tapovan-trek/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2018/06/07/gomukh-tapovan-trek/</guid>
        
        <category>uttarakhand</category>
        
        <category>uttarkashi</category>
        
        <category>gangotri</category>
        
        <category>gomukh</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        <category>tapovan</category>
        
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bali Pass Trek</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2017/10/17/bali-pass-trek/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2017/10/17/bali-pass-trek/</guid>
        
        <category>uttarakhand</category>
        
        <category>uttarkashi</category>
        
        <category>yamunotri</category>
        
        <category>runsaira</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        <category>sankri</category>
        
        
        <category>organised</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Rupin Pass Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The scree so far held tight till sunrise started rushing in from all around us in the steep narrow gully of Rupin Pass with the rising sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For once, I thought that some lizards just started running around. There were many at the start of trek in Dhaula village near Naitwar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sooner when I realized it to be stones falling from side cliffs, I looked at Akash who was at the foot of the pass gauging the climb, unaware of the hazard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hollered at him to hurry and allowed myself some time to breathe. Pass was just few meters away. Our guide had just reached the pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting from Rupin valley, Uttarakhand and ending in Sangla valley, Himachal; Rupin Pass trek gives you a chance to witness a complete transition of culture in around 60 kms of distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a moderate-difficult trek, it is suggested by few to go as to prepare for little difficult ones like Pin Parvati.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got to know about it, when I went to Har Ki Doon trek an year ago. In my research of it, I found out, many people praising the sheer beauty of the trail all over the internet. We started for the same in the month of September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-1&quot;&gt;Day 1&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, it was me and Akash for this trek. We had taken the last bus to Sankri which reached Naitwar by evening, nearest town from where the trek starts. Till this time, it had become very clear to me that we should take a guide with us on this trail. There were no other groups going on this trek this season. Many trekking organizations had cancelled their batches. So, in case we are not able to follow the trail, guide would be very instrumental in such situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While entering the Govind Pashu Vihar National Park region in the evening, the forest official had pointed me to a list on a wall. It had names and numbers of some odd 20-25 registered local guides in the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not stopping in Naitwar to continue to Dhaula where the trek actually starts, we went further up to Sankri village which was home to the most of the guides in aforementioned list. With the help of shop owner there, I was able to get hold of a guide. He came by the shop after some time. He himself wasn’t available for us, as he was currently engaged with some trek organization on Kedarkantha trek. He suggested someone who he said had been to that trail before. I was fine with anyone who knew the trail and made a deal with him for the guide and his vehicle to drop us till Dhaula village. He also let us rent a tent, sleeping bag for the guide and cooking utensils and stove for the trek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-2&quot;&gt;Day 2&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous night, we had purchased all the necessary things for the trek from local market and were waiting for the guide to start our journey. He came in early with his vehicle and we settled our business by giving him the advance rent for equipments/utensils we hired.  Another guy in his vehicle, was our guide for the trek. We introduced ourselves. We were not taking porters and decided to distribute everything related to food supplies (bought from Jhaka)/utensils among ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1909/30692127717_ce6ace8895_k.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rupin river at Dhaula village, starting point of trek&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Rupin river at Dhaula village, starting point of trek&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some tea in Naitwar, we reached Dhaula around 11. This place was teeming with lizards all over the trail. With every step they were running away towards the bushes with head held high. After lunch in Dhaula, our trek finally commenced around 12:00 in the noon. It was a bright sunny day which was making the climb tiring. Our guide had taken a shortcut and we followed him on a path without trail for some time. After initial climb, the slope was gradual and we started following the trail. Walking briskly, we reached Sewa village by 14:30. Hanging on a guest house by a peculiar Kinnauri style temple, which is most noticeable structure of the village, was a banner of Bikat Adventure. This guest house was supposed to be the stay of Bikat Adventures trekkers, but the batches were cancelled for this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1935/44908436344_6999da13ca_h.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kath-Khuni (Cator and Cribbage) construction technique&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kath-Khuni (Cator and Cribbage) construction technique&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sup&gt;Kath-khuni is a type of cator-and-cribbage building which employs locally available wood and stone as prime materials for construction.&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;The origin of the term is explained by O.C. Handa (2008) as ‘…combination of two local terms: kath and kuni.&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;The word kath is a dialectal variation of the Sanskrit word kashtth, which means wood, and kuni is again a dialectical variation of the Sanskrit word kona, that is, an angle or a corner.&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;Obviously, the kath-khuni wall implies it should have only wood on its corner or angles.’&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;sup&gt;There are several variations observed from region to region. It is also known as kath-kona, kath-ki-kanni, koti banal in Uttarakhand etc.&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still had time left before the sunset, so continued further. Now the trails goes through a deep forest by the river. We crossed a wooden bridge on Rupin, which is near the very boundary of Uttarakhand and Himachal and entered the Dodra Kwar region of Shimla district in Himachal. After crossing the river, the trail snakes up, beautifully carved in a near vertical face of a hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1961/44719412045_970c8deded_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;After crossing the river, the trail snakes up, beautifully carved in a near vertical face of a hill.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;After crossing the river, the trail snakes up, beautifully carved in a near vertical face of a hill.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some walk, in this dense forest, so we exited into completely different region. This was Gusangu, first inhabited place of Himachal we encounter. A road-head out of nowhere one would’ve imagined. It was evening time, children were coming back from school. After having some snacks from a shop nearby, we continued for Jiskun which was our planned stop of the day. From Gusangu, road climbs sharply up to Jiskun after a long flat walk on the road. Now, we had started feeling the fatigue and sun was about to set. Around 18:30, we reached Jiskun. By now, it was getting dark. Walking on the road felt more tiring than walking on a trail. Today’s was around 20 km walk. Overnight in a homestay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-3&quot;&gt;Day 3&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This day we aimed to continue our pace and reach Dhanderas thatch. Around, 13:00 we stayed for lunch in Jhaka. We also bought some food supplies, sticking to the basic food (rice, pulses etc.), just sufficient enough for us to last for 4 days considering 2 meals a day. Around 14:30, we reached Saruwas Thatch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we faced an obstacle. A strong stream of Rupin river in front of us to negotiate. To continue further to Dhanderas thatch, we needed to cross it and walk along it’s left side. Today, Akash was relatively slower and further behind. I asked him to wait for a while till me and the guide find a way to cross the river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spend some time walking up and down the river bolder strewn bed hoping to find a spot to cross the river. There was no easy spot and it seemed that we may have to enter this intimidating stream. This proposal was not really welcomed by Akash. Our guide suggested to stay the night, hoping that tomorrow early morning the stream might be less fierce. I cut some grasses on the slope with ice axe to make the spot good to pitching our tents. Our guide started preparing for our early dinner. It was a dense jungle and we were just beside the river bed. High slopes were all around us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we retired to our tents after dinner, our guide came to our tent and said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bhai mujhe darr lag rha hai, mai Akash bhai ke sath so jata hun; ap mere wale tent me so jao.&lt;/em&gt; That made us all laugh, wondering what might be his fears. Anyway, I switched places with him and was happy to get more bed space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-4&quot;&gt;Day 4&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I woke many time in the early morning with the sound of rain. Our plan to cross the river even today was in jeopardy. We waited for the rain to stop. It was around 11:00, when we were finally ready to go after having breakfast cum lunch for the day. We found a spot up on the river bed, where one could cross the river if jumped across with our full force. The stream there was little narrow and fast. So, if someone failed to jump, it would have definitely been dangerous. Our guide jumped across first and I threw across all of our bags to him. That really required serious shot put skills given the weight of our bags. After crossing the river, there was no turning back and even a chance to help other in jumping across. I remained this side and asked Akash to jump. He was little doubtful about his jump. Our guide had put some stones on the other side in case the jump falls short. Finally Akash jumped, with his full force, but the jump fell little short of expectation. He landed on a loose rock on which he slipped and his one leg went into the water and he fell sidewise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1908/30692139037_1e22290160_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Akash, before jumping across the river. Wait for my cue before you jump.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Akash, before jumping across the river. Wait for my cue before you jump.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our guide who was waiting for him onto the other side quickly caught him though he was out of danger. He thanked his mobile in his pocket for saving him from any injury. I also followed the course with the thought in mind that it is ok if my steps doesn’t land in the right place; I should clear the stream at any cost. Well, I flew just overshot myself. And it was really fun. We continued further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After few hours of walk, valley really opened up. Now, it was wide with very little or no slope. We were walking besides the river bed which had soft grass all around. There, the land has gotten so flat that river wasn’t even flowing in one stream and it had different branches which were converging further down from where we’re passing by. Any depression further up would’ve clearly converted the whole area in a lake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wide and long Rupin valley converges in a mountain further up in front of us and on the mountain there is a cascading waterfall with two major cascades. Down from the valley, it is difficult to see anything further behind the mountain top in front of us. Hovering on the mountain top, there was some dark cloud formation. Sunlight falling on the top of mountain, was putting a spotlight on the waterfall. All of it would make you feel as if the river is just pouring down from sky on the mountain and forming this beautiful waterfall. From our right flank of the mountains, many more waterfalls joined the Rupin. The soft carpet of green grass all around on this flat land was making everything so colorful and vivid and no words could really explain what one would feel about it. I might just use all the cliched words for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1949/30692123527_5156043c9d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rupin waterfall from the valley&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Rupin waterfall from the valley.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had we came in the month of August, it would’ve been even more wonderful when the flowers would’ve been around on the hill slopes on our side. This was the most perfect spot for camping. We chose one nice spot for camp, settled for the day&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-5&quot;&gt;Day 5&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we realized that we hadn’t planned our food rations very well or some really got lost. All we were left with now was rice. It seems that we had bought pulses in little amount as compared to rice. So, we have now had to resort to rice with some maggi masala or salt and onions. We started our day around 10:00 and started walking towards waterfall. Trails were nowhere to be found now and and we were forcing our way into the tall and dense flowers on the left side slope of river valley. Our guide was quick to negotiate the area and we were watching our steps through the chest-height grass before taking them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1963/30692135997_e7f36cc2f4_k.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wading in the grass to find a way, behind me is Akash&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Wading in the grass to find a way, behind me is Akash&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes Akash was behind and playing catch up with us and the the process even dropped his bag on the slope. Luckily the bag stopped in the grass, else it would have been a long journey downward to pick the bag from gap between slope and huge snow bridge on Rupin river. In few minutes, we reached the lower water fall and and crossing it wasn’t as difficult as expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1916/30692125177_12253f23ee_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wading in the grass to find a way, behind me is Akash&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Rupin valley from waterfall&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only thing which was making us slow in this trek now was the continuous climb with good amount of weight. Our guide was walking fast and I had to wait in the middle sometimes to keep everyone together. After upper water fall, Akash used to get behind a lot and we waited for him more frequently. I made good use of my whistle which I was carrying to keep each other aware of general direction most of the times. It was getting cloudy, and visibility was very low. Trails were faded or sometimes not visible at all because very few people might be crossing the pass this season. Seeing the bad weather and unawareness of the distance of next campsite, I was trying to make Akash hurry up. I didn’t do a very good job in motivating and Akash was really tired. He was taking frequent and long stops. When he was left behind, echoing whistle was confusing him in poor visibility and sometimes he even lost track of trail. Because of this we also had to take frequent stops. This way we might get caught in hail or rain, I thought. After some persuasion, at one stop, Akash allowed me to take his bag. I was little afraid of weather turning bad and we needed to make it to campsite before it happens, so I pushed forward with guide and asked Akash to try his best to follow us. It was a difficult walk now. I could imagine, this whole scenery around us could’ve been more beautiful and picturesque, given the weather didn’t turn against us this way. Trudging up on the gradual slope besides with Rupin stream flowing slowly on our right, when we reached &lt;em&gt;Rata-Pheri&lt;/em&gt; around 14:00, wind had now become chilly. Without wasting any time, we pitched our tents. It had started raining. We all took refuge in one tent and cozied up in sleeping bags. Around sunset, the rain subsided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;day-6&quot;&gt;Day 6&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was D-Day. Last night we had planned to start early. Morning was chilly and hands were getting quickly numb while un pitching our tents. With our best effort to start early, we started for pass little before 8 AM. Starting from &lt;em&gt;Rata Pheri&lt;/em&gt;, we entered in the glacial cirque, just before Rupin pass. Our guide pointed us towards the point where pass was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1948/30692129417_f42a12fdce_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Trail towards Rupin pass and the gully leading to the pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Trail towards Rupin pass and the gully leading to the pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopping big boulders along the path was little difficult without snow, and we trudged along with our guide towards the pass. The trail was not visible and everyone was taking the shortest possible way towards the place where pass starts. It was not far, and everyone was visible, so we all moved at our own pace. At the foot of the pass, we all assembled for little water and rest but started climbing soon afterwards. The last stretch towards pass is a steep narrow gully filled with scree and loose rocks on both sides of cliffs. During the time we were climbing, there was no snow. Sun had risen when we were at the foot of the pass.The rocks exposed to light start to slide or fall off with the rising sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it was not scary, but Akash was far behind. Without saying much about why, I suggested Akash to hurry as it is not that far and moved up after staying a while. On reaching top, our guide went back to catch and help Akash, though he had also reached on his own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1939/31760797778_0ca4b5f014_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Towards Rupin, From Rupin Pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Towards Rupin, From Rupin Pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 09:30, we all were at the pass, basking in the sun, congratulating ourselves for the all the efforts we made in past few days. We indulged ourselves in little celebration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1934/45582546972_a3f39f73e3_k.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Towards Sangla, from Rupin Pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Towards Sangla, from Rupin Pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except for weather, it was an easy climb. The other side of pass also didn’t have much snow except on the slopes of higher mountains.
The weather was now good and it was downhill all the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1912/43815367110_16e2222f81_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Panoramic View of Rupin Pass from Sangla Side&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Panoramic View of Rupin Pass from Sangla Side&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had planned to reach all the way to Sangla today so it was a long way to go. Stopping only to enjoy the view of valley in front of us we scurried downhill. Trail was clear and always visible, so everyone was walking at their own pace only to stop when we get separated and some confusing point was encountered. After few hours, when we reached the first village we were really hungry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1920/30692132977_cd16a6cf4e_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First village after Rupin Pass, Sangla Kanda&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;First village after Rupin Pass, Sangla Kanda&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way, there were many apricot trees. We fed ourselves with the fallen ones and moved along. We had started feeling tired and more hungry walking through long village route. We even discussed if we can borrow some apples on the trees which was very tempting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the thought that Sangla is not very far, and we can have a sumptuous meal over there; we continued walking. By 14:30, we reached the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1928/31760801458_9d77255688_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A temple in Sangla&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A temple in Sangla&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After keeping our bags in a hotel of our guide’s acquaintance, we had a nice warm &lt;em&gt;thali&lt;/em&gt; of &lt;em&gt;dal, chawal, roti, sabzi&lt;/em&gt; (such a delight it is after so many days of good food).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now it was time for all of us to bid happy goodbyes, while we were still deciding between staying one more day so as to visit Chitkul or to leave the same day but our guide wanted to leave on same day. So upon deciding to leave, we took a bus to Delhi in the evening and reached the next morning having one of the most blissful sleep the entire journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Richard_Hughes15/publication/228983379_Cator_and_Cribbage_Construction_of_Northern_Pakistan/links/557055d208aeccd77741a19d/Cator-and-Cribbage-Construction-of-Northern-Pakistan.pdf&quot;&gt;Cator and Cribbage Construction of Northern Pakistan by &lt;em&gt;Richard Hughes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sahapedia.org/the-himalayan-vernacular-kath-khuni-architecture&quot;&gt;The Himalayan Vernacular: Kath-Khuni Architecture by &lt;em&gt;Mansi Shah and Jay Thakkar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2017/09/14/rupin-pass/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2017/09/14/rupin-pass/</guid>
        
        <category>uttarkashi</category>
        
        <category>sankri</category>
        
        <category>naitwar</category>
        
        <category>rupin</category>
        
        <category>sangla</category>
        
        <category>himachal</category>
        
        <category>uttarakhand</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kuari pass Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had been to Devariyatal — Chandrashila trek in November ‘16.
New year was coming so was planning to celebrate in a different way and what better can it be than mountains and their evenings.
One of my office colleague, Akash had shown interest to come along on a trek.
Another colleague Shweta, was also interested in trekking in Himalayas.
Shweta had done a trek with me before but Akash was new to this.
I thought of trekking to Kuari pass, which offers a close view of Nanda Devi, Dunagiri and Hathi - Ghoda parbat and also its suitable for novice trekkers and many trekking organizations run batches along this route.
So, we wouldn’t be alone if we couldn’t find any guide for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started our journey from Delhi on Wednesday, 28th Dec, 2016 on train.
Upon reaching Haridwar Railway Station, we took a Uttarakhand Roadways bus to Joshimath.
Though trek starts from Auli, we figured that accommodation in Auli would cost us more due to increase in tourist influx around year end.
We needed to see if we could get a guide in Joshimath.
By evening of Thursday, 29th Dec, 2016, we reached Joshimath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this long journey we didn’t have much time left to get a guide and make arrangements of food on the trek.
Our topmost priority was to get a guide which would help us with the trek route.
We found one from a local tourist organization.
Immediately after that, he helped us get all the forest permits needed for camping and trekking.
With the consultation of our guide, we bought and packed all the ration needed for a seemingly 4 day long trek to Kuari pass from Auli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;First day of trek&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1901/44571704304_6af8935cc5_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Start of trek from Auli&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Start of trek from Auli&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next morning we started with our guide Nima Sherpa and by the time, we reached Auli via cab, it was 08:30 AM.
According to itinerary, we were to camp in Gorson Bugyal on first day of trek.
Soon we reached Gorson Bugyal but Nima kept on walking further and I figured that there is no nearby water source around to camp here.
I decided not tell others so early and was happy in way that we are saving time and I may get some days to go on another trek around here (As always, I get greedy when it comes to mountains) .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gorson Bugyal offers a spectacular view of Nanda Devi. Though it was little cloudy, but I was happy to see Nanda Devi so clear.
Gorson Bugyal is too soon to camp for the day in my opinion. As we moved further through the meadow, clouds were all around us and we could no longer see peaks other than Hathi Ghoda and Dunagiri on our left.
Sun played hide and seek behind the clouds as we moved towards Chitrakantha forest area.
After a walk of 6 hours, we were entering into Chitrakantha forest.
Akash had some sign of tiredness but was elated when told that we didn’t stop at Gorson Bugyal due to nonavailability of water and are reaching Chitrakantha/Tali camping site in few minutes.
All this time he had been wondering about the distance travelled and the time to reach Gorson Bugyal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1936/31419831688_e3af38ef4d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Camps of Himalayan Snow Runners&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Camps of Himalayan Snow Runners&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camping sites of Chitrakantha forest was already full with the camps of Indiahikes and Himalayan Snow Runners.
We found a little space nearby where we could pitch our tents. Nima decided to stay in a cave like place nearby where he had set up the kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1944/44571700604_eaea0ce901_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kitchen&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kitchen&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had started from Auli after our breakfast and were hungry by the time we reached Chitrkantha around 2:30 PM.
Nima quickly made tea for all of us and then we went on exploring around, while Nima had started preparing dinner.
When sun was about to set, we crammed around a little bonfire made by Nima discussing our next day plans.
Nima was planning to camp in Khullar next day before reaching Kuari pass.
Akash had some urgent work in office and was not in favour of reaching Kuari pass in 2 days.
Nima proposed an alternative plan to leave our tents pitched and start early morning to Kuari pass with our daypacks to come back before evening to Chitrkantha itself.
Everybody agreed to this plan.
I was little reluctant because I feared that we may not reach Kuari pass early morning to have a clear view of mountains around.
I had ample time and didn’t want to rush it but I gave up eventually.
Nima had prepared Dal-Chawal that night.
The utensils were small and dal wasn’t enough for 4 people.
Nima insisted us to have all of the dal as he would fetch some more from the kitchen of Himalayan Snow Runners where his friends were working.
Our little bonfire was about to die, so we decided to call it a day and moved towards our tents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;second-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;Second Day of Trek&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1932/31419830198_6831985953_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hathi Ghoda Parvat and other peaks&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Hathi Ghoda Parvat and other peaks&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We woke up early in the morning and after little breakfasts and prepared a daypack with water and a jacket.
Akash decided to brush his teeth and was little behind so I asked Shweta and Nima to move ahead.
Few minutes later, I hastened with Akash to catch up with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1966/31419826428_c6349d31b0_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Near Khullar camping site, towards Kuari pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Near Khullar camping site, towards Kuari pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Near Khullar camping site, towards Kuari pass&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was past 7:30 in the morning. We were rushing to reach Kuari pass before it gets cloudy and passed others along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1971/44571697034_a1116d19de_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Second day of trek&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Second day of trek&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around 10:30 when we passed a glacial stream before the slope of Kuari pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1927/44571707924_9f869742d0_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A glacial stream before the slope of Kuari pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A glacial stream before the slope of Kuari pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The view of the huge valley and the Pangarchulla peak in the vicinity was very enticing.
I enquired Nima about the climb of Pangarchulla.
He told me to come after the snow.
Climb to Pangarchula is easier when there is snow as there are many boulders on the way.
The cold breeze had become strong and and cloud had started to cover the sun.
Soon we reached the top of Kuari pass to have complete 270deg view of surrounding.
I had an app “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peakfinder.org/?lat=30.4453&amp;amp;lng=79.5756&amp;amp;azi=47&amp;amp;zoom=4&amp;amp;ele=3805&quot;&gt;PeakFinder&lt;/a&gt;” installed to identify the peaks in view from any location.
I was little disappointed as array of clouds always covered the the peaks behind Dunagiri and Hathi Ghora.
We stayed there at the top for an hour or so while sun played hide and seek behind the clouds.
Even for a moment, the warmth of sun in such ice cold breeze was greatly appreciated by us.
It seemed that weather was not going to get any clearer and it might snow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1949/44571699164_8f544ae655_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kuari pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kuari pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a little stay there, we started back. The other group from some trek organization had been resting way behind the glacial stream.
While coming back, they met us near the glacial stream.
We suggested few of those trekkers to hurry as they might get caught in bad weather while coming back.
It looked like this group had many novice trekkers, not mentally prepared enough for adverse conditions which might come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wind was getting stronger and stronger and carried snowflakes along with it.
Shweta had developed knee pain while descending and was walking slow.
I asked Nima to go ahead and prepare lunch for us. We were walking little slow but reached Chitrakantha around 3 PM.
Lunch was served and Akash went ahead to take a nap while Shweta and I stayed near the fireplace.
To pass time I decided to roast the rest of the tomatoes and potatoes and prepared “chokha” with great help of Shweta for all of us to be served
in dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1969/31419825288_0a34e56edb_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New year eve, dinner prepared&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;New year eve, dinner prepared&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway we were going back tomorrow.
We clicked pictures in the cave while Nima went off with some of his friends to celebrate new year.
Two goats were brought from the nearby village for 31st December night.
Akash was amused to think whether he could ask in their kitchen to share some of mutton with him.
Nima was back around 9 and asked us to have our dinner so that he could be free to be with his friends.
I was happy to hear some kind words about “chokha” from Nima.
We thought of keeping ourselves awake till 12 in night that day but our eyes were getting heavy by 10 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;third-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;Third Day of Trek&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got up on the morning of this very beautiful new year 2017 (elated), we had started back to Dhak from where we could take a cab to Joshimath.
It was 11:30 AM when everybody reached Dhak.
After waiting a while when we could not get any transport, I asked Nima to call a cab to pick us up which came after half an hour.
There weren’t any buses to Haridwar in afternoon so we decided to stay in Joshimath that night to catch an early bus to Haridwar next morning.
We reached Joshimath in the evening, where we freshend up, had a sumptuous meal and roamed around this small little paradise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more photos, our &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/photos/BzfZadUGLftwrM8Y6&quot;&gt;Kuari pass album&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/12/28/kuari-pass-trek-log/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/12/28/kuari-pass-trek-log/</guid>
        
        <category>chamoli</category>
        
        <category>joshimath</category>
        
        <category>auli</category>
        
        <category>uttarakhand</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Devariyatal - Chandrashila Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After my last trek to Hampta Pass, I couldn’t get any leave from office due to work and had lost precious trek months of August, September and
October.
It was towards end of November, when I finally got a chance to plan a trek.
One of my office colleague, Shweta had been asking to go on a trek.
She was eager to see what a trek would be like.
I was little skeptical, since she had no prior experience of trek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had not been to Tungnath before, so I chose to trek to Chandrashila starting from Deoriyatal via Rohini Bugyal.
It was also suitable trek in a way that it is not difficult for new trekkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1944/43478504700_4db80bbeb3_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tungnath&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Tungnath&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tungnath is the highest Shiva temple in the world and is one of the five and the highest Panch Kedar temples located in the mountain range
of Tunganath in Rudraprayag district, in the Indian state of Uttarakhand. The Tunganath (literal meaning: Lord of the peaks) mountains form the
Mandakini and Alaknanda river valleys.
Located at an altitude of 3,680 m (12,073 ft), and just below the peak of Chandrashila, Tungnath temple is the highest Hindu shrine dedicated to
Lord Shiva.
The temple is believed to be 1000 years old and is the third (Tritiya Kedar) in the pecking order of the Panch Kedars.
It has a rich legend linked to the Pandavas, heroes of the Mahabharata epic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started from New Delhi to Haridwar on Friday, 25th Nov’16 via train and we reached Haridwar at 4 in the morning.
The bus stand was near by so we walked towards Bus stand soon after having tea at Railway station to catch a bus to Joshimath, Chamoli.
After 6 hours of journey, we reached Rudraprayag.
From there we took a cab to Sari village (Starting point of trek) as there aren’t frequent transport options towards Ukhimath road.
Sari is located near Ukhimath in Rudraprayag district.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;first-day-of-trek-towards-devariyatal-fromsari&quot;&gt;First day of trek towards Devariyatal from Sari&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1947/45293509741_d3dd0ee92d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First day of trek towards Devariyatal from Sari&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;First day of trek towards Devariyatal from Sari&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reached the village named Sari around 2 PM and soon we started off to Devariyatal.
Trek to Devariyatal is roughly 3 km climb from this village.
In little more than an hour, we reached Devariyatal .
There weren’t many people camping that day.
In fact, there were only two tents pitched except ours.
The lake Devariyatal is beauty of it’s own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1909/43478509650_5b5d90a179_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Deoriyatal Lake&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Deoriyatal Lake&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A clear view of peak like Mt. Chaukhambha, and reflections of surrounding trees in it’s calm water could hardly be matched by any other camping site.
It is also unmatched in terms of it’s distance from nearest civilization with Sari village being just 2 km downhill.
We put our bags and tents nearby the lake and decided to take stroll along the boundary of lake.
The sun was about to set, and the surrounding peaks were getting a golden hue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1946/43478511470_a34a50f77e_b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;With every moment of setting sun, mountains were getting heavenly.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;With every moment of setting sun, mountains were getting heavenly.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rushed to a place to get a best possible view but couldn’t have enough of it.
It felt like as if it had been a long since I was away from mountains.
Shweta also was very happy to be here.
In her words, this place can make a person breathe a new life in themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1903/45293510531_436d597ced_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;View of Mt. Chaukhambha from Lake&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View of Mt. Chaukhambha from Lake&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before dark, we located a site near the lake and pitched our tents.
The sky was soon filled with stars where we sat under in appreciation.
I have one thing to admit, you can see the most beautiful night sky in the mountains.
You never get to see a sky full of stars in city and it is such a treat to the eyes and soul.
Sitting there for a long, the night was turning cold and breezy, but we really didnt want to go anywhere.
But since everthing closes early in mountain, we started for dinner in a nearby shop.
There while having dinner, we asked about the route to Chandrashila via Rohini Bugyal from the shopkeeper.
He told us to take a guide as there was very less or no water along the route and there was nobody going through that route these days.
In my little experience of trekking, I had never taken a guide before but this time was different.
I needed to be more responsible than before.
I was not sure, how easy this was going to be for somebody new to trekking.
We may have to keep on trekking if we couldn’t find water along the way till we find any.
Shweta was ready to accept these difficulties.
After talking to others in the shop, it was clear to us that water sources along the way had dried up and we may face difficulties because of that.
Everybody except us, were going to Tungnath from Chopta which was too mainstream for me and it never gives me a feeling of fulfillment to take such routes.
While having dinner, I asked if I could get a guide for the rest of the trek.
The shopkeeper told us that he knows someone in the village, who would take INR 1000 per day and we also have to rent a tent and sleeping bag for
him.
We decided to think over it in night and went back to our tents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;second-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;Second day of Trek&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1975/45293507411_2ee15fda2c_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chaukhambha, early morning at Devariyatal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Chaukhambha, early morning at Devariyatal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We woke up early and packed our bags and tents.
There was a hut of forest guard nearby who gave us the required camping permits.
What mattered the most was to complete the trek without any unnecessary difficulties.
While having breakfast, I asked the shopkeeper to arrange for the guide he was talking about last night.
Meanwhile he was on his way to Devariyatal from home (Sari village), we arranged for his tent and sleeping bag along with some utensils and food items.
Being extra careful with water, we bought some extra bottles in case we didn’t find any water on the way.
Our guide, Umendra Singh Bhatt, turned up almost after an hour and we started as soon as he arrived.
Our first stop was Rohini Bugyal and the trail leading to Rohini Bugyal was not long.
It ascends moderately till Jhandi Dhar (a ridge with a flag at the top) and passes through a dense jungle thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1969/45293505071_01390cc226_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;On the way to Rohini Bugyal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;On the way to Rohini Bugyal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our right side, we constantly had a view of Sari village.
Contrary to what was told, we encountered running streams on our way.
After Jhandi Dhar, the jungle becomes dense and beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1930/45293506261_3e4122519d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;On the way to Rohini Bugyal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;On the way to Rohini Bugyal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1927/45293503531_d6e431c392_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail was so rewarding and beautiful that every now and then, I just couldn’t stop myself from halting and clicking pictures on the way.
We easily reached Rohini Bugyal in 4–5 hours and we decided to halt for the day.
While roaming around the campsite, we could see that this place had few abandoned huts which were left not more than a month ago.
There was a small stream of water near the place where we decided to camp.
Umendra collected some dry woods from nearby place and created a makeshift fireplace with some stones and started to prepare tea.
After having tea, we went around to fetch some more wood for night and cooking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was curious to know about the places around, so soon after having tea and maggi, we went for a stroll.
From our location the view of Trishul peak was blocked by a mountain.
Umendra told us that on this mountain, there is a lake called Bisuri Tal which is a high altitude glacial lake.
I think it may’ve been known as Vasuki Tal originally.
Though there already is one Vasuki Tal in Gangotri Valley and one in Kedarnath Valley.
From Rohini Bugyal, a straight trail leads to Bisuri Tal, whereas the trail on the right with initial ascent and then steep descent goes towards Akash Kamini stream coming from Chandrashila.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1969/43478508360_e33417f6bc_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rohini Bugyal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Rohini Bugyal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being one of the lesser know trek, Bisuri Tal offers a very close view of Trishul peak and it usually takes two more days from Rohini Bugyal to reach Bisuri Tal.
If time allowed, I was eager to go on this one as soon as we complete the Chandrashila trek.
There isn’t much information on Bisuri Tal on internet.
We roamed around the meadow in the evening and as the sun was about to set, the cast it was creating on the mountains was giving such a fascinating view that it was literally a treat to watch.
Soon it turned dark and we returned near the camp, where we sat near the fireplace to discuss the next course of actions and we decided to start early the next day so as to reach Bhurjgali early and continue trekking to Chandrashila after leaving our heavy rucksacks at the shop whoes owner was Umendra’s friend.
With this plan, next day was going to be little long.
It had more ascent than before.
Umendra went to sleep early and we sat there talking near the fireplace till there was no firewood left.
After sometime, with not much left to do, we went on towards our tents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;third-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;Third day of trek&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1968/43478506340_aa67f9f3cd_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got up early, around 6, in the morning and packed our tents and bags.
Umendra had already started preparing tea for all of us. After having some tea and biscuit, we left Rohini Bugyal to start our last day of the
trek.
Past Rohini Bugyal, trail descends steeply towards Akash Kamini stream. On this descend, Shweta started having problems with her knee which made her little slow.&lt;br /&gt;
She continued anyway and we soon reached the Akashkamini stream.
It originates near the Chandrashila peak.
After walking for around 2 hours we halted near lower Bhurjgali.
There were few abandoned huts around where we stayed for a while and had our lunch maggi.
Umendra seemed to be a very good cook. We both agreed, that we never had maggi tastier than this. :yum:
It took nearly three hours for us to reach Bhurjgali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1948/45293512041_90d45ef3f3_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Near lower Bhurjgali&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Near lower Bhurjgali&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here onwards, this trail merges in a trail coming from Chopta.
In fact Chopta was about a km from here.
There was a shop nearby where we left our rucksacks and had some tea.
Soon we left for Tungnath and Chandrashila.
It is well laid path with carved steps and railings etc.
What disappointed me most was the amount of garbage on the way.
The task of collecting garbage on the way became more difficult than any other of my treks.
Umendra was also helping in collecting the garbage.
We were discussing, what could Lord Tungnath offer to those who come and throw garbage around.
In an hour or so, we reached Tungnath, though the temple was closed for the season.
We offered our prayers and roamed around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1949/45293508461_d57875480c_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;With our guide Umendra Singh Bhatt&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;With our guide Umendra Singh Bhatt&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There we met other people who had come there from Chopta.
We stayed there for a while and then started ahead for Chandrashila.
As there was no snow, so it didn’t take much time to reach Chandrashila.
There was a small temple up there. As soon as we reached there, all of us offered our prayers to the lord and went ahead with watching the amazing view of mountains.
It had been a long time, that I had visited a place which offers such a panoramic view of mountains peaks.
We could see a complete 180 degree view of majestic peaks of Garhwal.
Umendra told about the various peaks we can see from there and the places around.
I had been to the summit of Mt. DKD-II which could also be seen from there.
Chandrashila also offers a clear view of Mt. Nanda Devi.
From Jaonli to Nanda Devi, every peak was clear to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1916/43478512180_f55053bfeb_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A panoramic view from Chandrashila&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A panoramic view from Chandrashila&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was carrying my binoculars which also helped me explore these peaks more precisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1946/43478510220_d595bcf5ee_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this time of our stay at Chandrashila, we found ourselves sitting and watching the peaks around.
When we were content enough, we started our descent towards Bhurjgali. After walking for almost an hour, we reached Bhurjgali and there we had our lunch and started descending towards Chopta.
From Chopta we took a cab to Sari village which Umendra had already called.
After a drive of almost 40–45 minutes, we reached Sari, where we stayed for the night before leaving for Haridwar next morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to admit, though we went in an off season, Devariyatal - Chandrashila was by far one of the most beautiful trails I have ever trekked and was contended wiht the beauty i saw in such a short trek.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/11/25/devariyatal-chandrashila-trek-log/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/11/25/devariyatal-chandrashila-trek-log/</guid>
        
        <category>chopta</category>
        
        <category>tungnath</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        <category>uttarakhand</category>
        
        <category>panchkedar</category>
        
        <category>chandrashila</category>
        
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mountaineering Institutes in India</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Although there are many other institutes in India, but these two are the most sought ones.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indmount.org&quot;&gt;Indian Mountaineering Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, which is apex national body in this field lists 5 institutes on it’s webpage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hmidarjeeling.com/&quot;&gt;Himalayan Mountaineering Institute (HMI), Darjeeling, West Bengal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nimindia.net/&quot;&gt;Nehru Institute Of Mountaineering (NIM), Uttarkashi, Uttarakhand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adventurehimalaya.org/&quot;&gt;Atal Bihari Vajpayee Institute of Mountaineering and Allied Sports (ABVMAS), Manali, Himachal Pradesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jawaharinstitutepahalgam.com/&quot;&gt;Jawahar Institute of Mountaineering (JIM), Pahalgam, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iismgulmarg.in/&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Skiing and Mountaineering, Gulmarg, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than these 5, there are few more institutes which conducts courses
in mountaineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sonam Gyatso Mountaineering Institute (SGMI), Gangtok, Sikkim&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nimasdirang.com/&quot;&gt;Nation Institute of Mountaineering and Allied Sports, Dirang, West Kameng, Arunachal Pradesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pnsmti.org&quot;&gt;Pt. Nain Singh Rawat Mountaineering Institute, Munsiyari, Uttarakhand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from this, there are some internation organisations working in similar domain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nols.edu&quot;&gt;The National Outdoor Leadership School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/10/15/mountaineering-institutes-in-india/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/10/15/mountaineering-institutes-in-india/</guid>
        
        <category>manali</category>
        
        <category>darjeeling</category>
        
        <category>uttarkashi</category>
        
        <category>gulmarg</category>
        
        <category>mountaineering</category>
        
        <category>gangtok</category>
        
        <category>uttarakhand</category>
        
        <category>sikkim</category>
        
        <category>himachal</category>
        
        <category>kashmir</category>
        
        <category>bengal</category>
        
        
        <category>organised</category>
        
        <category>course</category>
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>mountaineering</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hampta Pass and Chandratal Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was exploring some extended weekend treks as my office colleagues also wanted to come along.
After searching and negotiating a lot, no agreeable trek couldn’t be decided and now that I have to travel
solo, I finally decided to go for Hampta Pass and Chandratal.
Hampta pass trek starts from Manali, Himachal Pradesh.
It is a small pass on Pir Panjal range of Himalayas, between Lahaul and Kullu valley in Himachal Pradesh.
Vertical rock walls, water falls, hanging glaciers, tiny lakes, peaks rising above 6000 m are main characteristics of this trek.
I was very excited about this trek because I was finally getting another chance to see Chandratal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kiran was also in town and ready for a weekend trek.
We left Delhi on Thursday, 14 July so that we had an extra day before next week starts.
Bus to Manali was running late and we reached there around 11A.M.
After having heavy lunch around noon, we took a cab for Jobra.
It takes an hour and forty hairpin bends to arrive at Jobra, time would have been 2 PM by then.
As soon as we arrived we left, as we had planned to reach Balu Ka Ghera on our first day of trek and it was already late.
It had rained earlier in the day and path was slippery till Chika village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1927/45243668192_77b56aef6b_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In few hours of trek and after crossing few streams we reached Jwara.
Clouds were all around us due to which visibility was very poor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1954/45243661482_a07ff1b414_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balu ka ghera was still like an hour far from Jwara.
There wasn’t much daylight left and it could rain anytime.
We decided to pitch our tents in Jwara.
In the backdrop, we had a vertical rocky cliff with a nice view of waterfall.
There was a shop in Jwara from where we got ourselves nice dinner for the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1926/31418933588_a2f962e624_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Our tents in Jwara&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Our tents in Jwara&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1918/45243667192_879f49476e_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Campsite at Jwara&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Campsite at Jwara&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was Saturday, June 16th. We started for Balu ka Ghera early morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1938/30354220177_9b40139bd4_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It was all misty from the beginning which was giving the whole
valley a mystic look.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;It was all misty from the beginning which was giving the whole valley a mystic look.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we reached Balu Ka Ghera, it started raining heavily.
After more than an hour of wait and meanwhile having lunch (the one we packed from the shop when we camped a night before) in Balu Ka Ghera, when the rain didn’t stop; we prepared ourselves to walk in rain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1921/45243663902_2eb5e3a18a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Open Valey near Balu ka Ghera&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Panaromic View of Open Valey near Balu ka Ghera&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After few hours of walk, we arrived at Balu Ka Ghera.
There was a Dutch couple already there, whom we met in Jwara.
We started from Balu Ka Ghera together.
They were thinking of returning back from the pass but we had plans to go further.
Before the ascent to pass starts, there is a big lake where we bid them goodbye and continued our journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1941/31418931088_cb010c559a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Small lake on the way up to pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Small lake on the way up to pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In heavy rain, the stream beside us was ferocious which actually accompanied us all along the trek in the valley.
After crossing some boulders, we were welcomed by the glacier.
In such low visibility, it was getting difficult to find our way forward.
Kiran was incessantly asking whether we are on the right path or not.
We followed the tracks of mules on the glacier and reached the plateau.
It was real cloudy and it seemed that we had lost our way there.
Trying to look closely for tracks and deciding which we to go, we were munching on the biscuits we had and it seemed, that we had to go back and follow the track more closely.
On our left was a vertical rocky cliff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1905/45243665242_dbee6381d5_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The valley, clouds ahead on the pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The valley, clouds ahead on the pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was there when I heard some sound of mules walking somewhere nearby.
I rushed towards the noise, though between so dense clouds, it was being difficult to figure out. Following the mule sound, I heard voice of a man controlling the mules.
We shouted and asked whether anybody is there.
The mules were gone and lost in the clouds by then.
After few minutes, someone replied to our hello. When we rushed towards the sound, it was the same dutch couple with their guide.
The lady told me, that they decided to cross the pass same day.
We were just few meters away from the trail, but without their help we definitely would’ve gone in the wrong direction.
This could’ve lost us at least few precious hours.
We were actually few meters away from the trail.
It’s just that the trail makes an unusual bend towards left while going up at the highest point of trek which we would have easily figured out, had the sky been clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1944/30354221347_cdc869abd1_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Towards Shiagoru From Hampta Pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Towards Shiagoru From Hampta Pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With them, we started our descent to Shiagoru which was steep and little slippery due to rains.
The rain was little less in this part of valley (Lahaul). If it was a normal day, we could’ve had a nice view of Indrasan peak which was right to us while climbing down.
We were descending to Lahaul Valley.
The arrangements were already there for the night in Shiagoru for the Dutch couple.
We decided to trek further down to Chhatru.
Kiran had to go back next day for Delhi on Sunday to join office.
The stream in Shiagoru had grown strong due to continuous rain that day.
It’s a flat area fed from glacier; it wasn’t deep but certainly was cold.
Having crossed the stream with our hands joined, we took off for Chhatru.
From Shiagoru to Chhatru, it’s a long walk but easy descent.
The sun was about to set when we reached Chhatru roadhead.
Chhatru is on the way to Kaza from Manali. We pitched our tents, and were invited for dinner by trek organizers from Bikat adventures who were also camping there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1943/31418932038_7346bfa310_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Before Chhatru&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Before Chhatru&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early morning, we had a quick breakfast in Chhatru.
There were few truck drivers having tea.
When they were about to leave, I asked them for a drop to Batal.
I started my journey ahead with them after saying goodbye to Kiran who was waiting for a conveyance that he can get to Manali.
Chhatru to Batal isn’t very far, but due to road conditions it was already afternoon when I reached Batal.
After having lunch in Batal, I enquired for the directions to Chandratal. People suggested me to go to Kunzum pass and start a near downhill trek from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1954/45243660572_e0e46021cf_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took there advice, as it was clear that the road from Batal to Chandratal was only preferred for vehicles.
Those truck drivers were still there having lunch. I joined them again when they left for Kaza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon I was in Kunzum la, and it was raining when I reached there.
There was no one who could tell me the way to Chandratal, though there was a board with signboard of Chandratal.
I just decided to follow the path behind the board.
It was well laid trail till I reached a point from where I had a view of valley.
At this point the trail ended and I had nowhere to go. I could see tents far in the valley, but there was a very steep descent. I tried to go down that path, but had to to turn back as it was very slippery.
When many attempts to find a better way to the valley failed I had to retrace the path back so as to find some alternative way. I was sure that I was on right path to Chandratal.
After few meters of travelling back, there was a trail sharp left climbing towards the nearby hill.
I took that and climbed the hill to see around.
From there, I could see the trail going further inside the valley. Thanking god, I trotted down the trail.
All along the way, the weather was clear and I had a nice view of valley and Chandra river valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1968/45243666192_3c907bf02c_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chandra river valley&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Chandra river valley&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the Chandratal was in sight.
I aimed to reach Chandratal with some buffer time to explore.
It was not allowed to camp there but there were many people camping around Chandratal.
There was no authority to control this.
While trekking from Kunjum La to Chandratal, I did not find any kiosk or office where one could find any kind camping permits etc.
The visitors of Chandratal, mostly were with some trek organization on four wheelers with exceptions of few bikers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1948/31418928728_2991bfc2b9_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chandra Taal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Chandra Taal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chandratal was still very beautiful, clean and peaceful.
The small stream emanating from Chandratal and a wooden bridge looks like a setting from a fairy tale. I sat there around half an hour.
When sun had set, I turned back towards Batal road looking for a place to camp.
Most of the good places nearby were completely occupied by private organizations which was little disheartening.
Anyhow I was able to find a place to camp besides some Paragon camping site marking the end of yet another trek of mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next day was the journey back home day and I started my return walk to Batal.
On the way to Batal from Chandratal, I got a lift by a jeep accompanying bikers till Batal and from there I was able get hold of another jeep going towards Manali.
Buses are not very reliable on this route.
By afternoon, I was in Manali where I had lunch and explored the market until it was time for bus to Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/07/18/hampta-pass-and-chandratal-trek-log/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/07/18/hampta-pass-and-chandratal-trek-log/</guid>
        
        <category>chandratal</category>
        
        <category>hampta pass</category>
        
        <category>manali</category>
        
        <category>spiti</category>
        
        <category>himachal</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        <category>indrasan</category>
        
        <category>trekking</category>
        
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
