<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>अथातो घुमक्कड़ जिज्ञासा</title>
    <description>Eternal Curiousity Of Traveler's Mind.</description>
    <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 18:04:01 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 18:04:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.4</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Pin Parvati Pass Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It was around midnight when I woke up with the sound of susurration. Eyes closed, I hoped it to be the glacial stream flowing nearby. I was wide awake, when I heard someone beating on the tent nearby. There was no doubt that it was snowfall. Our plan to cross the Pin Parvati pass tomorrow was in serious jeopardy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since past few years, I had been looking forward to go on Pin Parvati Pass trek. In fact, whenever my friends offerred me come along to Kheerganga or Kasol, I had been politely declining by telling them that I’ll walk on that trail only when I am going for Pin Parvati Pass. I’ve always loved crossing the passes because of the trasitions it offer in terms of the culture and sometimes landscapes. It has always felt to me like crossing from one country to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pin Parvati Pass, is one of those treks in Himalayas which offers a variety in landscapes, chance to witness different cultures and of course a decent enough altitude. It is supposed to be difficult than any other normal Himalayan trek because of the long trail and crevasses near the pass. I had been to Tarsar Marsar Lake just few days ago. I still had some leaves left and it was apt time for going on such a trek. It’s mid September and trekking season in Himalayas was nearing to an end. Very few organizations were running this trek. I chose to go with Bikat because I had been to Bali Pass with them before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;start-of-the-trek&quot;&gt;Start of the trek&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was the last one to reach Barsheni. Rohit, our trek leader was waiting for me at Pulga Dam. After a short hike we reached Kalga, a small village from where we were to start this trek next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The dam at Pulga is part of Parbati Hydroelectric Project (Stage-II). It is a run-of-the-river scheme proposed to harness hydro potential of the lower reaches of the river Parbati. The river is proposed to be diverted with a Concrete Gravity Dam at Village Pulga in Parbati valley through 31.52 Km long Head Race Tunnel and the Power House shall be located at village Suind in Sainj valley. Thus gross head of 863 m between Pulga and Suind will be utilized for generating 800MW power. The diverted discharge of the river Parbati has been further augmented by diverting the discharge of various nallahs falling along the HRT alignment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a round of introduction among trekmates. In our introduction, it was noticeable that most people are experienced trekkers. Some had very impressive list of treks in their kitties and some had mountaineering experience as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next morning before starting for Kheerganga, the first camping site; we were introduced to our trek guides Hari and Chetramji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial 6 days are supposed to 5-6 hours of walk with not more than 500 meters of altitude gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started from Kalga, with Parbati river on our left. On the other side of the river which recieves more sunlight in the morning, Nakthan villgae. There were patches of cannabis plantation on other side of the river. 
From Kalga, the trail climbs to a temple and small dhaba at Rudra-Nag waterfall, which is named after its resemblance of a snake. Our guide Hari tells us that local &lt;em&gt;Devi-Devta&lt;/em&gt;(deities) comes for a bath every year. Beyond Rudra-Nag waterfall, the trail ascends further through thick pine forests to the spiritual site of Kheerganga where Shiva is said to have meditated for 3000 years. The hot springs at Kheerganga are extremely important for Hindu and Sikh pilgrims as well as many others who believe the waters have sacred healing properties. The trail from Kalga to Kheerganga was broken at few places. There are always many people hiking towards Kheerganga. In afternoon, we went for a bath in hot spring after pitching tents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1955/44600168814_9420f3d3bc_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kheerganga Hot spring&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kheerganga Hot spring&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;khirganga-2789m-to-tunda-bhuj-3285m&quot;&gt;Khirganga (2789m) to Tunda Bhuj (3285m)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1906/44600158944_8ac82b6c65_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Vijay measuring thickness of a pine tree&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Vijay measuring thickness of a pine tree&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Kheerganga to Tunda Bhuj (3285m) the Parvati river cuts a steep-sided gorge through the mountains and as the altitude increases, the thick, coniferous forest gradually gives way for patches of meadowland scattered with boulders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1930/43507805430_d7403accc1_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near Tunda Bhuj, on the other side of river many waterfalls emanating from steep mountains join the river.
On those steep faces, shepherds in search of green pastures for their flock were seen passing across the waterfalls which we wondered if anyone would dare to traverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1957/45324200671_005b23d62a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Waterfalls joining Parbati River&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Waterfalls joining Parbati River from steep slopes of mountains on our left side.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tunda-bhuj-3285m-to-thakur-kuan-3560m&quot;&gt;Tunda Bhuj (3285m) to Thakur Kuan (3560m)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the river flow close to the trail and one could hear the sound of it crashing its way through the rocks. The treeline begins to diminish and only some patches of bushes are to be seen. Along the trail, some Bhoj(Birch) trees could also be seen on the slopes of mountains which gives the name to the Tunda Bhuj campsite. After reaching Thakur Kuan campsite, we went for an acclimatization walk on a nearby hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1962/43507801820_8600d2f355_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Thakur Kuan campsite from nearby hill&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Thakur Kuan campsite from nearby hill&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was another shepherd tent nearby with a big flock of sheeps and goats. In our conversation, when we told that we have come from far places to trek in the valley, he was little surprised on why would someone make such effort and spend money to come this far and what is there to gain for us. 
Some of us were amused by the expression of faces of sheeps and goats made good use of their mobile cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;thakur-kuan-3560m-to-odi-thatch-3879m&quot;&gt;Thakur Kuan (3560m) to Odi Thatch (3879m)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail goes across the river just after few minutes of walk. We had three hurdles to cross, a traverse along the steep rock face by the river and two natural bridges on the river. Our trek leader suggested us that we don our helmets as the traversal of the rock face and crossing the bridge could be tricky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bridges called as Pandu Pul, is a huge boulder placed right on the river. Local legend says it was placed by Bheem, one among Pandavas. The river flow beneath the rock through the small passage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pccofvns/45274004802/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;Parbati flow beneath the natuaral bridge&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1980/45274004802_77146c3226_b.jpg&quot; width=&quot;1024&quot; height=&quot;576&quot; alt=&quot;Parbati flow beneath the natuaral bridge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rope was fixed on the bridge to prevent any slips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1919/44600165114_20b9363350_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pandu Pul I&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Pandu Pul I&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were also accompanied by a dog who had been following us from Kheerganga, even after several attempts by Hari and Chetramji, our local guides to leave it behind. During our short stops during the trek, many of us esp. Peter and Pratibha could be seen petting her. It return, she joined us for the nice pictures. It was even given a name “Jackie” and upon realizing the gender, some identified her by “Jacqueline” so that the name “Jackie” can still be relevant as hypocorism. Amusing, how we urban people in India, name our dogs. Names like Sheru and Moti become less and less relevant. Anyway, Jackie a faithful mountain dog whom we thought that she may not be able to cross the Pandu Pul, and this is where we say our goodbye to her, travsersed the slippery boudler like a cakewalk to join us. Everyone was cheerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&quot;true&quot; href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/pccofvns/45274005952/in/dateposted-public/&quot; title=&quot;Jackie crossing Pandu Pul I&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1945/45274005952_b1f22015e5_s.jpg&quot; width=&quot;75&quot; height=&quot;75&quot; alt=&quot;Jackie crossing Pandu Pul I&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After crossing the bridge, the valley opens up and is very wide with a more or less flat ground throughout. Glacial streams from both sides of valley join the Parbati river. Odi Thatch(thatch = meadow), a wide flat ground by the side of Parbati River, could’ve been our campsite if water source was available in vicinity. Porters had already went ahead of Odi Thatch because of non availibility of water near the campsite. We followed them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1941/43507804690_8e2442cd82_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Odi thatch&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Odi thatch&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continued further for an hour for our next camping site which was small flat land between the boulders, by the mountain side and very windy in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1911/44600171324_b65e314123_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Camping site ahead of Odi thatch&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Camping site ahead of Odi thatch&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;odi-thatch-3876-m-to-mantalai-4100m&quot;&gt;Odi Thatch (3876 m) to Mantalai (4100m)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On today’s trail, valley exapnds further and the Parbati River now on our right side is calmer than before. In fact, we reach a point where the river flows on almost flat bed of the wide valley creating sand banks alongside. It is like any big river in plains with pebbles and sand around. In the sunny weather, it felt as if it was some kind of wonderland. Elated by the sight of valley, we spent some quite moment by the side of river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1935/45274006722_5ddaa3ef9c_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;group photo&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Omkar, Anshul, me, Ashish aka RawHash, Vijay, Petri Ultich (Peter), Sanjay Gupta, Chetram, Hari, Kannan Kasturi, Satyajit Patnaik, Pratibha Rahi.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a perfect spot for group photo and in fact everyone was posing around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1965/43507803430_f47b77f421_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of us went ahead and some decided to walk barefoot on the riverbed and enjoy while it lasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1919/44600166834_e593c6712a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Everyone wanted to stay a little more.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The wide exapanse of valley and calm flow of Parbati river was intoxicating and satisfying at the same time. Everyone wanted to stay a little more.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1941/43507803850_136caebc96_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Parvati River at its widest&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Parvati River at its widest&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1977/43518884390_8a809352ca_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The valley closes in front of us with snow laden peaks.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The valley closes in front of us with snow laden peaks.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far the weather was with us, but when we were nearing the Mantalai Lake, the starting point of Parbati River, weather suddenly started closing in on us. It turned cloudy and windy which was giving us chills. While waiting for others, we visited the temple by the lake which houses a Shivling in open air surrounded by cairns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1919/44600167174_acacc28001_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mantalai Temple and lake behind&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Mantalai Temple and lake behind&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we moved towards the next camping site, further up by the lake, light rain started. As soon as we reached the campsite weather was again clear. Many of us attributed this sudden change in weather to the ritualistic prayers offerred at the temple by the lake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1946/44600169604_d5900fcaab_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The sunset was beautiful and the reflection of peaks in the lake drew us to our cameras.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The sunset was beautiful and the reflection of peaks in the lake drew us to our cameras.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mantalai-4100m-to-parbati-base-camp-4940m&quot;&gt;Mantalai (4100m) to Parbati Base Camp (4940m)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weather was clear in the morning, and we were all ready for our highest altitude gain(~ 800m) of the trek. We start by climbing the mountain slope along side the lake. It is a continuous climb and from the top we get the see the panaromic view of lake. It was fascinating to see the different colors of small lake formed in the Mantalai glacier. One would wonder how is it possible that these small lakes are so close to each other but have such difference in color. Some of these ponds seem to have turquoise blue and some were green in color and some had muddy appearance. I wonder about the physics and geology behind that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1955/43507806210_85fb71af65_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Glacial lakes formed in the Mantalai&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Glacial lakes formed in the Mantalai&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After climbing the mountaintop by the lake, we pushed further through the morains crossing a stream coming from the glacier near the pass. The weather was with us so far. It was bright sunny day when we reached base camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1906/43507806710_5aaea677a5_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Parvati Valley side base camp&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Parvati Valley side base camp&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The campsite was some rocky patch between the boulders just before the thick tabletop like glacier. I took some time to wash myslef in the glacial stream nearby while the sun was still with us. The peak overlooking the Mantalai lake, was playing hide and seek in clouds and some of us amused by it, were busy capturing it in a timelapse video. Sitting on a boulder, Ashish was busy creating a 360 degree view of the campsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were left with only 300m of climb and everything seemed to be in our favor so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around midnight, I woke up with a sound of susurration. I really hoped that sound to be of a stream flowing nearby. Maybe, sound of stream is more clear in the night, I thought. This is when I heard someone beating on the tent nearby. My worst fears had come true. It is snowfall! I had been waking every hour since then and the continued snowfall was adding to my fears. In such weather, they might actually decide to turn back and not cross the pass. It would’ve disappointing to back after coming this far and after so many days of trek. I hoped that they deicde to use the reserve day which we had in our plan if it is not advisable to cross the pass tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1975/45274706342_9996331b44_b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Base camp in morning&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Base camp in morning&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;parbati-base-camp-4940m-via-pin-parbati-pass-5300m-to-shepherds-camp--4300m&quot;&gt;Parbati Base Camp (4940m) via Pin Parbati Pass (5300m) to Shepherds camp (~ 4300m)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was all rocky and dry yesterday, was covered with snow in the morning. Snowfall was incessant. Rohit, Hari and Chetramji decided to march ahead instead of waiting the snow out. I overheard someone saying that we don’t have much kerosene oil left with us as well and going back will take longer. It is better to cross the pass before snow piles on. My hands were freezing in unpitching the tents and my thin fleece gloves were not helping either. We continued as per the plan. Hari was leading the way prodding along with stick. After few minutes on the snow, when glacier started, he suggested that we rope ourselves up as it’s become very difficult to identify the crevasses. It would’ve slowed the whole group if every one was roped up, so three of us (Rohit, Har and me) roped up to move ahead making way for others. Hari was leading the way. It was complete whiteout below the pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1971/43507800510_23cdf4ce58_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Roped up&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After negotiating first crevasse, Cheeku who was leader of the porter group was called upon by Hari to lead the way. Cheeku was crossing this pass sixth time this year. He knew this terrain as back of his hand and was very instrumental in identifying the path and crevasses too. However, some porters who went ahead behind Cheeku did go in the crevasse but were pulled out in time. We were trying our best to negotatite the crevasses with the support of the makeshift arrangement of fixed ropes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1957/44600162944_55bddf87c0_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Porters marching ahead in green and yellow&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Porters marching ahead in green and yellow&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While working with the ropes, my thin fleece gloves were complete wet and I had to squeeze the water out of the gloves. It was freezing, and I hoped I didn’t get frost bite. Around 11:30, we touched the pass. There wasn’t much to see around in this incessant snowfall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1961/45274002712_1df192d218_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;At Pin Parvati Pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;At Pin Parvati Pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a long way ahead, so we hurried towards the other side of pass in Pin Valley without staying much on the pass. There are many crevasses in the glacier at this side of pass as well and these were now completely hidden by the snowfall. Whenever Cheeku identified a creavasse, a shout goes out to us three to take up positions on both sides of creavsse to fix the rope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had already decided to skip the usual camping site (Pin Base camp) and keep going down to reach the next one, a Shepherd’s camp. By the time we crossed Pin river, our shoes and clothes were completely wet and it was becoming difficult to stand. I didn’t even bother to remove the socks to cross the river. It was better to keep walking to keep warm. When we reached the campite, the dinner tent was set up. A stove was put to keep us warm. Snowfall was nowhere to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had hoped that Spiti would be dry at this time of year, but weather was defying all the odds. We didn’t want to bother with pitching our tents and everyone except few decided to spend the night in dinner tent. In night, Rohit came to us and said that he will start early next morning for Mudh and try to arrange a conveyance to pick others midway. I asked Rohit if I can be of any help and can accompany him to which he said yes. Before sleeping, I noticed that my sleeping bag along with everyone others was soaking wet too. I had put it in a dry pack which didn’t help. For tomorrow, we had decided to go to Mudh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;shepherds-camp--4300m-to-mudh-3800-m&quot;&gt;Shepherds Camp (~ 4300m) to Mudh (3800 m)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As per plan I started with Rohit around 8:30 towards Mudh. There was someone from porter group as well to show us the way. Hari and Chetramji were to follow the course with other members after sometime. We needed to hurry to reach Mudh, else vehicle wouldn’t reach near the roadhead in time to pick others. The sandy and fragile soil in the mountains of Spiti Valley were frequently showing signs of landslide and sometimes we had to cross active landslides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1926/43508483600_6f2a0f4c02_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our shoes were already wet and clothes were wet again. Around 11:30 we touched the roadhead. This is under construction road in the valley, and Mudh village is way ahead. Some more kilometers ahead from roadhead, there is a &lt;em&gt;nullah&lt;/em&gt; (Pagal Nala) which flows over the road and the stream is so ferocious and strong that vehicles coming from Mudh can’t cross this stretch. We were supposed to bring the vehicle till this point. We crossed the Pagal Nala with on a small makeshift footover bridge down the stream. We had reached a landmark. On a normal day, this trek would’ve successfully ended here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started freezing when we stopped for lunch near Pagal Nallah. Ahead on the road of Pagal Nala, there were many small landlides and we wondered if a vehicle could reach here or not. It was long and arduous walk and felt tougher than yesterday. Today was a definitely a long stretch, more than 25KM and it was again freezing in the afternoon. 
After hours of walking on the road slong with Pin River, Mudh village was finally on the sight. Nevertheless, it took another hour to reach the village.
There was another wide and ferocious stream was waiting for us just before the village. The sheer muddy color and the sound of it sent chills down the spine. Rohit took the lead and we held each others hand to cross the stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reached Mudh around 3:30 PM. The only phone(BSNL satellite phone) available in the village wasn’t working. It had been snowing in the valley since last two days and phone works with solar powered batteries only, which are dead by now. We asked the owner of the public telephone, who also owned a home stay (Tara) for help in arranging a vehicle to pick others along the trail. People in village were surprised to listen to our story and even enquired if someone is already dead. Some went on to suggect that we were foolish to cross the pass. There were others stuck since 2 days waiting go anywhere outside the village. The owner of Tara cafe muttered, “agar gadi nhi gayi to wo log to mar jayenge”. He rushed to arrange two tractors and a JCB excavator to clear up the road. Rohit was frantically trying to contact Hari over the walkie talkie. He was able to connect to Hari around 5:30 and Hari told us that everyone is safe. By 6:30, 3 more of trekmates along with some porters have arrived in the village but many were still left way behind. I was told by these guys that the tractor won’t be able to come back as there had been recent landslides. The helpful people of village were waiting with tea and hot water on the road. They immediately took these guys in their homes and even offered dry clothes.  It was already dark. I went with the JCB excavator again to see if I can be any help. I was already feeling guilty for not going along with the tractor. Riding the JCB, wading through the raging nullah; we caught up the tractors around a kilometer ahead waiting for help to come. There were two big landslides completely covering the road. While JCB started clearing the road, I walked ahead to see others. The guys on tractor told that everyone else has taken a shortcut to reach the village and must’ve reached village by now. These guys were not willing to leave the tractor behind on the road in fear of landslides which may occur anywhere in the stretch. I waited till the JCB cleared the road and tractors (one without headlight) were shown its way to the village. When I reached village again, everyone had reached already. The dog Jackie, who was following us had also reached in the village running behind the tractor and was safe in the village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;two-days-of-waiting-in-mudh-village&quot;&gt;Two Days of waiting in Mudh Village&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1970/43507800260_509e232ee3_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A view from Mudh village after weather clears&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A view from Mudh village after weather clears&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The snowfall had never stopped, but Rohit was able to convey the information about our safety next day. We started getting news about the havoc this weather had created. The roads were closed everywhere and we had no other option than to wait till the road to Kaza(A popular place in Spiti and headquarter of Spiti subdivision) opens. These two days, we had a good time in the village enjoying what was available for us. After a day, the cafe were serving only their home stay guests as food had become scarce in the village. The weather was now clear after two days in Mudh. Road were getting repaired and we made our way to Kaza. Road to Manali via Rohtang pass was broken at many places and there was no sign of it getting repaired in near future. The road to Shimla via, Reckong Peo was open next day and we made our way home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this last stretch of my road trip, I was heading back having collected the most memorable and cherishable memories, must say, a long due present to my own self.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2018/09/30/pin-parvati-pass/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2018/09/30/pin-parvati-pass/</guid>
        
        <category>kullu</category>
        
        <category>spiti</category>
        
        <category>kaza</category>
        
        <category>mudh</category>
        
        
        <category>organised</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Devariyatal - Chandrashila Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After my last trek to Hampta Pass, I couldn’t get any leave from office due to work and had lost precious trek months of August, September and
October. 
It was towards end of November, when I finally got a chance to plan a trek.
One of my office colleague, Shweta had been asking to go on a trek. 
She was eager to see what a trek would be like. 
I was little skeptical, since she had no prior experience of trek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had not been to Tungnath before, so I chose to trek to Chandrashila starting from Deoriyatal via Rohini Bugyal. 
It was also suitable trek in a way that it is not difficult for new trekkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1944/43478504700_4db80bbeb3_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Tungnath&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Tungnath&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tungnath is the highest Shiva temple in the world and is one of the five and the highest Panch Kedar temples located in the mountain range 
of Tunganath in Rudraprayag district, in the Indian state of Uttarakhand. The Tunganath (literal meaning: Lord of the peaks) mountains form the 
Mandakini and Alaknanda river valleys. 
Located at an altitude of 3,680 m (12,073 ft), and just below the peak of Chandrashila, Tungnath temple is the highest Hindu shrine dedicated to 
Lord Shiva. 
The temple is believed to be 1000 years old and is the third (Tritiya Kedar) in the pecking order of the Panch Kedars. 
It has a rich legend linked to the Pandavas, heroes of the Mahabharata epic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started from New Delhi to Haridwar on Friday, 25th Nov’16 via train and we reached Haridwar at 4 in the morning. 
The bus stand was near by so we walked towards Bus stand soon after having tea at Railway station to catch a bus to Joshimath, Chamoli. 
After 6 hours of journey, we reached Rudraprayag. 
From there we took a cab to Sari village (Starting point of trek) as there aren’t frequent transport options towards Ukhimath road. 
Sari is located near Ukhimath in Rudraprayag district.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;first-day-of-trek-towards-devariyatal-fromsari&quot;&gt;First day of trek towards Devariyatal from Sari&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1947/45293509741_d3dd0ee92d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;First day of trek towards Devariyatal from Sari&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;First day of trek towards Devariyatal from Sari&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reached the village named Sari around 2 PM and soon we started off to Devariyatal. 
Trek to Devariyatal is roughly 3 km climb from this village. 
In little more than an hour, we reached Devariyatal . 
There weren’t many people camping that day. 
In fact, there were only two tents pitched except ours. 
The lake Devariyatal is beauty of it’s own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1909/43478509650_5b5d90a179_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Deoriyatal Lake&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Deoriyatal Lake&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A clear view of peak like Mt. Chaukhambha, and reflections of surrounding trees in it’s calm water could hardly be matched by any other camping site. 
It is also unmatched in terms of it’s distance from nearest civilization with Sari village being just 2 km downhill. 
We put our bags and tents nearby the lake and decided to take stroll along the boundary of lake. 
The sun was about to set, and the surrounding peaks were getting a golden hue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1946/43478511470_a34a50f77e_b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;With every moment of setting sun, mountains were getting heavenly.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;With every moment of setting sun, mountains were getting heavenly.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We rushed to a place to get a best possible view but couldn’t have enough of it. 
It felt like as if it had been a long since I was away from mountains. 
Shweta also was very happy to be here. 
In her words, this place can make a person breathe a new life in themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1903/45293510531_436d597ced_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;View of Mt. Chaukhambha from Lake&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;View of Mt. Chaukhambha from Lake&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before dark, we located a site near the lake and pitched our tents. 
The sky was soon filled with stars where we sat under in appreciation.
I have one thing to admit, you can see the most beautiful night sky in the mountains. 
You never get to see a sky full of stars in city and it is such a treat to the eyes and soul. 
Sitting there for a long, the night was turning cold and breezy, but we really didnt want to go anywhere.
But since everthing closes early in mountain, we started for dinner in a nearby shop.
There while having dinner, we asked about the route to Chandrashila via Rohini Bugyal from the shopkeeper. 
He told us to take a guide as there was very less or no water along the route and there was nobody going through that route these days. 
In my little experience of trekking, I had never taken a guide before but this time was different. 
I needed to be more responsible than before. 
I was not sure, how easy this was going to be for somebody new to trekking. 
We may have to keep on trekking if we couldn’t find water along the way till we find any. 
Shweta was ready to accept these difficulties. 
After talking to others in the shop, it was clear to us that water sources along the way had dried up and we may face difficulties because of that. 
Everybody except us, were going to Tungnath from Chopta which was too mainstream for me and it never gives me a feeling of fulfillment to take such routes. 
While having dinner, I asked if I could get a guide for the rest of the trek. 
The shopkeeper told us that he knows someone in the village, who would take INR 1000 per day and we also have to rent a tent and sleeping bag for
him. 
We decided to think over it in night and went back to our tents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;second-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;Second day of Trek&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1975/45293507411_2ee15fda2c_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chaukhambha, early morning at Devariyatal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Chaukhambha, early morning at Devariyatal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We woke up early and packed our bags and tents.
There was a hut of forest guard nearby who gave us the required camping permits. 
What mattered the most was to complete the trek without any unnecessary difficulties. 
While having breakfast, I asked the shopkeeper to arrange for the guide he was talking about last night. 
Meanwhile he was on his way to Devariyatal from home (Sari village), we arranged for his tent and sleeping bag along with some utensils and food items.
Being extra careful with water, we bought some extra bottles in case we didn’t find any water on the way.
Our guide, Umendra Singh Bhatt, turned up almost after an hour and we started as soon as he arrived. 
Our first stop was Rohini Bugyal and the trail leading to Rohini Bugyal was not long. 
It ascends moderately till Jhandi Dhar (a ridge with a flag at the top) and passes through a dense jungle thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1969/45293505071_01390cc226_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;On the way to Rohini Bugyal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;On the way to Rohini Bugyal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our right side, we constantly had a view of Sari village. 
Contrary to what was told, we encountered running streams on our way. 
After Jhandi Dhar, the jungle becomes dense and beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1930/45293506261_3e4122519d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;On the way to Rohini Bugyal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;On the way to Rohini Bugyal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1927/45293503531_d6e431c392_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trail was so rewarding and beautiful that every now and then, I just couldn’t stop myself from halting and clicking pictures on the way. 
We easily reached Rohini Bugyal in 4–5 hours and we decided to halt for the day.
While roaming around the campsite, we could see that this place had few abandoned huts which were left not more than a month ago. 
There was a small stream of water near the place where we decided to camp. 
Umendra collected some dry woods from nearby place and created a makeshift fireplace with some stones and started to prepare tea. 
After having tea, we went around to fetch some more wood for night and cooking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was curious to know about the places around, so soon after having tea and maggi, we went for a stroll. 
From our location the view of Trishul peak was blocked by a mountain. 
Umendra told us that on this mountain, there is a lake called Bisuri Tal which is a high altitude glacial lake.
I think it may’ve been known as Vasuki Tal originally. 
Though there already is one Vasuki Tal in Gangotri Valley and one in Kedarnath Valley.
From Rohini Bugyal, a straight trail leads to Bisuri Tal, whereas the trail on the right with initial ascent and then steep descent goes towards Akash Kamini stream coming from Chandrashila.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1969/43478508360_e33417f6bc_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rohini Bugyal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Rohini Bugyal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being one of the lesser know trek, Bisuri Tal offers a very close view of Trishul peak and it usually takes two more days from Rohini Bugyal to reach Bisuri Tal.
If time allowed, I was eager to go on this one as soon as we complete the Chandrashila trek. 
There isn’t much information on Bisuri Tal on internet.
We roamed around the meadow in the evening and as the sun was about to set, the cast it was creating on the mountains was giving such a fascinating view that it was literally a treat to watch. 
Soon it turned dark and we returned near the camp, where we sat near the fireplace to discuss the next course of actions and we decided to start early the next day so as to reach Bhurjgali early and continue trekking to Chandrashila after leaving our heavy rucksacks at the shop whoes owner was Umendra’s friend. 
With this plan, next day was going to be little long. 
It had more ascent than before. 
Umendra went to sleep early and we sat there talking near the fireplace till there was no firewood left. 
After sometime, with not much left to do, we went on towards our tents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;third-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;Third day of trek&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1968/43478506340_aa67f9f3cd_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got up early, around 6, in the morning and packed our tents and bags.
Umendra had already started preparing tea for all of us. After having some tea and biscuit, we left Rohini Bugyal to start our last day of the
trek. 
Past Rohini Bugyal, trail descends steeply towards Akash Kamini stream. On this descend, Shweta started having problems with her knee which made her little slow.&lt;br /&gt;
She continued anyway and we soon reached the Akashkamini stream. 
It originates near the Chandrashila peak. 
After walking for around 2 hours we halted near lower Bhurjgali. 
There were few abandoned huts around where we stayed for a while and had our lunch maggi. 
Umendra seemed to be a very good cook. We both agreed, that we never had maggi tastier than this. :yum:
It took nearly three hours for us to reach Bhurjgali.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1948/45293512041_90d45ef3f3_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Near lower Bhurjgali&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Near lower Bhurjgali&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here onwards, this trail merges in a trail coming from Chopta. 
In fact Chopta was about a km from here. 
There was a shop nearby where we left our rucksacks and had some tea. 
Soon we left for Tungnath and Chandrashila. 
It is well laid path with carved steps and railings etc.
What disappointed me most was the amount of garbage on the way. 
The task of collecting garbage on the way became more difficult than any other of my treks. 
Umendra was also helping in collecting the garbage. 
We were discussing, what could Lord Tungnath offer to those who come and throw garbage around. 
In an hour or so, we reached Tungnath, though the temple was closed for the season. 
We offered our prayers and roamed around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1949/45293508461_d57875480c_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;With our guide Umendra Singh Bhatt&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;With our guide Umendra Singh Bhatt&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There we met other people who had come there from Chopta. 
We stayed there for a while and then started ahead for Chandrashila.
As there was no snow, so it didn’t take much time to reach Chandrashila.
There was a small temple up there. As soon as we reached there, all of us offered our prayers to the lord and went ahead with watching the amazing view of mountains. 
It had been a long time, that I had visited a place which offers such a panoramic view of mountains peaks. 
We could see a complete 180 degree view of majestic peaks of Garhwal. 
Umendra told about the various peaks we can see from there and the places around. 
I had been to the summit of Mt. DKD-II which could also be seen from there. 
Chandrashila also offers a clear view of Mt. Nanda Devi. 
From Jaonli to Nanda Devi, every peak was clear to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1916/43478512180_f55053bfeb_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A panoramic view from Chandrashila&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A panoramic view from Chandrashila&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was carrying my binoculars which also helped me explore these peaks more precisely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1946/43478510220_d595bcf5ee_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this time of our stay at Chandrashila, we found ourselves sitting and watching the peaks around. 
When we were content enough, we started our descent towards Bhurjgali. After walking for almost an hour, we reached Bhurjgali and there we had our lunch and started descending towards Chopta. 
From Chopta we took a cab to Sari village which Umendra had already called. 
After a drive of almost 40–45 minutes, we reached Sari, where we stayed for the night before leaving for Haridwar next morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to admit, though we went in an off season, Devariyatal - Chandrashila was by far one of the most beautiful trails I have ever trekked and was contended wiht the beauty i saw in such a short trek.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 25 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2017/11/25/devariyatal-chandrashila-trek-log/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2017/11/25/devariyatal-chandrashila-trek-log/</guid>
        
        <category>chopta</category>
        
        <category>tungnath</category>
        
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kuari pass Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I had been to Devariyatal — Chandrashila trek in November ‘16.
New year was coming so was planning to celebrate in a different way and what better can it be than mountains and their evenings.
One of my office colleague, Akash had shown interest to come along on a trek.
Another colleague Shweta, was also interested in trekking in Himalayas.
Shweta had done a trek with me before but Akash was new to this.
I thought of trekking to Kuari pass, which offers a close view of Nanda Devi, Dunagiri and Hathi - Ghoda parbat and also its suitable for novice trekkers and many trekking organizations run batches along this route.
So, we wouldn’t be alone if we couldn’t find any guide for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started our journey from Delhi on Wednesday, 28th Dec, 2016 on train.
Upon reaching Haridwar Railway Station, we took a Uttarakhand Roadways bus to Joshimath.
Though trek starts from Auli, we figured that accommodation in Auli would cost us more due to increase in tourist influx around year end.
We needed to see if we could get a guide in Joshimath.
By evening of Thursday, 29th Dec, 2016, we reached Joshimath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this long journey we didn’t have much time left to get a guide and make arrangements of food on the trek.
Our topmost priority was to get a guide which would help us with the trek route.
We found one from a local tourist organization.
Immediately after that, he helped us get all the forest permits needed for camping and trekking.
With the consultation of our guide, we bought and packed all the ration needed for a seemingly 4 day long trek to Kuari pass from Auli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;First day of trek&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1901/44571704304_6af8935cc5_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Start of trek from Auli&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Start of trek from Auli&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next morning we started with our guide Nima Sherpa and by the time, we reached Auli via cab, it was 08:30 AM.
According to itinerary, we were to camp in Gorson Bugyal on first day of trek.
Soon we reached Gorson Bugyal but Nima kept on walking further and I figured that there is no nearby water source around to camp here.
I decided not tell others so early and was happy in way that we are saving time and I may get some days to go on another trek around here (As always, I get greedy when it comes to mountains) .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gorson Bugyal offers a spectacular view of Nanda Devi. Though it was little cloudy, but I was happy to see Nanda Devi so clear.
Gorson Bugyal is too soon to camp for the day in my opinion. As we moved further through the meadow, clouds were all around us and we could no longer see peaks other than Hathi Ghoda and Dunagiri on our left.
Sun played hide and seek behind the clouds as we moved towards Chitrakantha forest area.
After a walk of 6 hours, we were entering into Chitrakantha forest.
Akash had some sign of tiredness but was elated when told that we didn’t stop at Gorson Bugyal due to nonavailability of water and are reaching Chitrakantha/Tali camping site in few minutes.
All this time he had been wondering about the distance travelled and the time to reach Gorson Bugyal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1936/31419831688_e3af38ef4d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Camps of Himalayan Snow Runners&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Camps of Himalayan Snow Runners&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Camping sites of Chitrakantha forest was already full with the camps of Indiahikes and Himalayan Snow Runners.
We found a little space nearby where we could pitch our tents. Nima decided to stay in a cave like place nearby where he had set up the kitchen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1944/44571700604_eaea0ce901_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kitchen&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kitchen&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had started from Auli after our breakfast and were hungry by the time we reached Chitrkantha around 2:30 PM. 
Nima quickly made tea for all of us and then we went on exploring around, while Nima had started preparing dinner.
When sun was about to set, we crammed around a little bonfire made by Nima discussing our next day plans.
Nima was planning to camp in Khullar next day before reaching Kuari pass.
Akash had some urgent work in office and was not in favour of reaching Kuari pass in 2 days.
Nima proposed an alternative plan to leave our tents pitched and start early morning to Kuari pass with our daypacks to come back before evening to Chitrkantha itself.
Everybody agreed to this plan.
I was little reluctant because I feared that we may not reach Kuari pass early morning to have a clear view of mountains around.
I had ample time and didn’t want to rush it but I gave up eventually.
Nima had prepared Dal-Chawal that night.
The utensils were small and dal wasn’t enough for 4 people.
Nima insisted us to have all of the dal as he would fetch some more from the kitchen of Himalayan Snow Runners where his friends were working.
Our little bonfire was about to die, so we decided to call it a day and moved towards our tents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;second-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;Second Day of Trek&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1932/31419830198_6831985953_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hathi Ghoda Parvat and other peaks&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Hathi Ghoda Parvat and other peaks&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We woke up early in the morning and after little breakfasts and prepared a daypack with water and a jacket.
Akash decided to brush his teeth and was little behind so I asked Shweta and Nima to move ahead.
Few minutes later, I hastened with Akash to catch up with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1966/31419826428_c6349d31b0_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Near Khullar camping site, towards Kuari pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Near Khullar camping site, towards Kuari pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Near Khullar camping site, towards Kuari pass&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was past 7:30 in the morning. We were rushing to reach Kuari pass before it gets cloudy and passed others along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1971/44571697034_a1116d19de_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Second day of trek&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Second day of trek&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around 10:30 when we passed a glacial stream before the slope of Kuari pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1927/44571707924_9f869742d0_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A glacial stream before the slope of Kuari pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A glacial stream before the slope of Kuari pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The view of the huge valley and the Pangarchulla peak in the vicinity was very enticing.
I enquired Nima about the climb of Pangarchulla.
He told me to come after the snow.
Climb to Pangarchula is easier when there is snow as there are many boulders on the way.
The cold breeze had become strong and and cloud had started to cover the sun.
Soon we reached the top of Kuari pass to have complete 270deg view of surrounding.
I had an app “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.peakfinder.org/?lat=30.4453&amp;amp;lng=79.5756&amp;amp;azi=47&amp;amp;zoom=4&amp;amp;ele=3805&quot;&gt;PeakFinder&lt;/a&gt;” installed to identify the peaks in view from any location.
I was little disappointed as array of clouds always covered the the peaks behind Dunagiri and Hathi Ghora.
We stayed there at the top for an hour or so while sun played hide and seek behind the clouds.
Even for a moment, the warmth of sun in such ice cold breeze was greatly appreciated by us.
It seemed that weather was not going to get any clearer and it might snow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1949/44571699164_8f544ae655_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kuari pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kuari pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a little stay there, we started back. The other group from some trek organization had been resting way behind the glacial stream.
While coming back, they met us near the glacial stream.
We suggested few of those trekkers to hurry as they might get caught in bad weather while coming back.
It looked like this group had many novice trekkers, not mentally prepared enough for adverse conditions which might come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wind was getting stronger and stronger and carried snowflakes along with it.
Shweta had developed knee pain while descending and was walking slow.
I asked Nima to go ahead and prepare lunch for us. We were walking little slow but reached Chitrakantha around 3 PM.
Lunch was served and Akash went ahead to take a nap while Shweta and I stayed near the fireplace.
To pass time I decided to roast the rest of the tomatoes and potatoes and prepared “chokha” with great help of Shweta for all of us to be served
in dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1969/31419825288_0a34e56edb_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;New year eve, dinner prepared&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;New year eve, dinner prepared&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway we were going back tomorrow.
We clicked pictures in the cave while Nima went off with some of his friends to celebrate new year.
Two goats were brought from the nearby village for 31st December night.
Akash was amused to think whether he could ask in their kitchen to share some of mutton with him.
Nima was back around 9 and asked us to have our dinner so that he could be free to be with his friends.
I was happy to hear some kind words about “chokha” from Nima.
We thought of keeping ourselves awake till 12 in night that day but our eyes were getting heavy by 10 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;third-day-of-trek&quot;&gt;Third Day of Trek&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got up on the morning of this very beautiful new year 2017 (elated), we had started back to Dhak from where we could take a cab to Joshimath.
It was 11:30 AM when everybody reached Dhak.
After waiting a while when we could not get any transport, I asked Nima to call a cab to pick us up which came after half an hour.
There weren’t any buses to Haridwar in afternoon so we decided to stay in Joshimath that night to catch an early bus to Haridwar next morning.
We reached Joshimath in the evening, where we freshend up, had a sumptuous meal and roamed around this small little paradise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more photos, our &lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/photos/BzfZadUGLftwrM8Y6&quot;&gt;Kuari pass album&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/12/28/kuari-pass-trek-log/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/12/28/kuari-pass-trek-log/</guid>
        
        <category>chamoli</category>
        
        <category>joshimath</category>
        
        <category>auli</category>
        
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mountaineering Institutes in India</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Although there are many other institutes in India, but these two are the most sought ones. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.indmount.org&quot;&gt;Indian Mountaineering Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, which is apex national body in this field lists 5 institutes on it’s webpage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hmidarjeeling.com/&quot;&gt;Himalayan Mountaineering Institute (HMI), Darjeeling, West Bengal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nimindia.net/&quot;&gt;Nehru Institute Of Mountaineering (NIM), Uttarkashi, Uttarakhand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adventurehimalaya.org/&quot;&gt;Atal Bihari Vajpayee Institute of Mountaineering and Allied Sports (ABVMAS), Manali, Himachal Pradesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jawaharinstitutepahalgam.com/&quot;&gt;Jawahar Institute of Mountaineering (JIM), Pahalgam, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iismgulmarg.in/&quot;&gt;Indian Institute of Skiing and Mountaineering, Gulmarg, Jammu &amp;amp; Kashmir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than these 5, there are few more institutes which conducts courses
in mountaineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sonam Gyatso Mountaineering Institute (SGMI), Gangtok, Sikkim&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nimasdirang.com/&quot;&gt;Nation Institute of Mountaineering and Allied Sports, Dirang, West Kameng, Arunachal Pradesh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pnsmti.org&quot;&gt;Pt. Nain Singh Rawat Mountaineering Institute, Munsiyari, Uttarakhand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from this, there are some internation organisations working in similar domain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nols.edu&quot;&gt;The National Outdoor Leadership School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/10/15/mountaineering-institutes-in-india/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/10/15/mountaineering-institutes-in-india/</guid>
        
        <category>Manali</category>
        
        <category>Darjeeling</category>
        
        <category>Uttarkashi</category>
        
        <category>Gulmarg</category>
        
        <category>West Kameng</category>
        
        
        <category>organised</category>
        
        <category>course</category>
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>mountaineering</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hampta Pass and Chandratal Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was exploring some extended weekend treks as my office colleagues also wanted to come along. 
After searching and negotiating a lot, no agreeable trek couldn’t be decided and now that I have to travel
solo, I finally decided to go for Hampta Pass and Chandratal.
Hampta pass trek starts from Manali, Himachal Pradesh. 
It is a small pass on Pir Panjal range of Himalayas, between Lahaul and Kullu valley in Himachal Pradesh. 
Vertical rock walls, water falls, hanging glaciers, tiny lakes, peaks rising above 6000 m are main characteristics of this trek. 
I was very excited about this trek because I was finally getting another chance to see Chandratal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kiran was also in town and ready for a weekend trek. 
We left Delhi on Thursday, 14 July so that we had an extra day before next week starts.
Bus to Manali was running late and we reached there around 11A.M. 
After having heavy lunch around noon, we took a cab for Jobra. 
It takes an hour and forty hairpin bends to arrive at Jobra, time would have been 2 PM by then.
As soon as we arrived we left, as we had planned to reach Balu Ka Ghera on our first day of trek and it was already late. 
It had rained earlier in the day and path was slippery till Chika village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1927/45243668192_77b56aef6b_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In few hours of trek and after crossing few streams we reached Jwara. 
Clouds were all around us due to which visibility was very poor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1954/45243661482_a07ff1b414_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balu ka ghera was still like an hour far from Jwara. 
There wasn’t much daylight left and it could rain anytime. 
We decided to pitch our tents in Jwara. 
In the backdrop, we had a vertical rocky cliff with a nice view of waterfall. 
There was a shop in Jwara from where we got ourselves nice dinner for the night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1926/31418933588_a2f962e624_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Our tents in Jwara&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Our tents in Jwara&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1918/45243667192_879f49476e_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Campsite at Jwara&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Campsite at Jwara&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was Saturday, June 16th. We started for Balu ka Ghera early morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1938/30354220177_9b40139bd4_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;It was all misty from the beginning which was giving the whole
valley a mystic look.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;It was all misty from the beginning which was giving the whole valley a mystic look.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we reached Balu Ka Ghera, it started raining heavily.
After more than an hour of wait and meanwhile having lunch (the one we packed from the shop when we camped a night before) in Balu Ka Ghera, when the rain didn’t stop; we prepared ourselves to walk in rain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1921/45243663902_2eb5e3a18a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Open Valey near Balu ka Ghera&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Panaromic View of Open Valey near Balu ka Ghera&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After few hours of walk, we arrived at Balu Ka Ghera.
There was a Dutch couple already there, whom we met in Jwara.
We started from Balu Ka Ghera together. 
They were thinking of returning back from the pass but we had plans to go further. 
Before the ascent to pass starts, there is a big lake where we bid them goodbye and continued our journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1941/31418931088_cb010c559a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Small lake on the way up to pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Small lake on the way up to pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In heavy rain, the stream beside us was ferocious which actually accompanied us all along the trek in the valley. 
After crossing some boulders, we were welcomed by the glacier. 
In such low visibility, it was getting difficult to find our way forward. 
Kiran was incessantly asking whether we are on the right path or not. 
We followed the tracks of mules on the glacier and reached the plateau. 
It was real cloudy and it seemed that we had lost our way there. 
Trying to look closely for tracks and deciding which we to go, we were munching on the biscuits we had and it seemed, that we had to go back and follow the track more closely. 
On our left was a vertical rocky cliff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1905/45243665242_dbee6381d5_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The valley, clouds ahead on the pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The valley, clouds ahead on the pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was there when I heard some sound of mules walking somewhere nearby. 
I rushed towards the noise, though between so dense clouds, it was being difficult to figure out. Following the mule sound, I heard voice of a man controlling the mules. 
We shouted and asked whether anybody is there. 
The mules were gone and lost in the clouds by then. 
After few minutes, someone replied to our hello. When we rushed towards the sound, it was the same dutch couple with their guide. 
The lady told me, that they decided to cross the pass same day.
We were just few meters away from the trail, but without their help we definitely would’ve gone in the wrong direction.
This could’ve lost us at least few precious hours. 
We were actually few meters away from the trail. 
It’s just that the trail makes an unusual bend towards left while going up at the highest point of trek which we would have easily figured out, had the sky been clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1944/30354221347_cdc869abd1_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Towards Shiagoru From Hampta Pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Towards Shiagoru From Hampta Pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With them, we started our descent to Shiagoru which was steep and little slippery due to rains. 
The rain was little less in this part of valley (Lahaul). If it was a normal day, we could’ve had a nice view of Indrasan peak which was right to us while climbing down. 
We were descending to Lahaul Valley. 
The arrangements were already there for the night in Shiagoru for the Dutch couple. 
We decided to trek further down to Chhatru. 
Kiran had to go back next day for Delhi on Sunday to join office. 
The stream in Shiagoru had grown strong due to continuous rain that day. 
It’s a flat area fed from glacier; it wasn’t deep but certainly was cold. 
Having crossed the stream with our hands joined, we took off for Chhatru. 
From Shiagoru to Chhatru, it’s a long walk but easy descent. 
The sun was about to set when we reached Chhatru roadhead. 
Chhatru is on the way to Kaza from Manali. We pitched our tents, and were invited for dinner by trek organizers from Bikat adventures who were also camping there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1943/31418932038_7346bfa310_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Before Chhatru&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Before Chhatru&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early morning, we had a quick breakfast in Chhatru. 
There were few truck drivers having tea. 
When they were about to leave, I asked them for a drop to Batal. 
I started my journey ahead with them after saying goodbye to Kiran who was waiting for a conveyance that he can get to Manali.
Chhatru to Batal isn’t very far, but due to road conditions it was already afternoon when I reached Batal. 
After having lunch in Batal, I enquired for the directions to Chandratal. People suggested me to go to Kunzum pass and start a near downhill trek from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1954/45243660572_e0e46021cf_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took there advice, as it was clear that the road from Batal to Chandratal was only preferred for vehicles. 
Those truck drivers were still there having lunch. I joined them again when they left for Kaza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon I was in Kunzum la, and it was raining when I reached there. 
There was no one who could tell me the way to Chandratal, though there was a board with signboard of Chandratal. 
I just decided to follow the path behind the board. 
It was well laid trail till I reached a point from where I had a view of valley. 
At this point the trail ended and I had nowhere to go. I could see tents far in the valley, but there was a very steep descent. I tried to go down that path, but had to to turn back as it was very slippery. 
When many attempts to find a better way to the valley failed I had to retrace the path back so as to find some alternative way. I was sure that I was on right path to Chandratal. 
After few meters of travelling back, there was a trail sharp left climbing towards the nearby hill. 
I took that and climbed the hill to see around. 
From there, I could see the trail going further inside the valley. Thanking god, I trotted down the trail. 
All along the way, the weather was clear and I had a nice view of valley and Chandra river valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1968/45243666192_3c907bf02c_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chandra river valley&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Chandra river valley&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the Chandratal was in sight. 
I aimed to reach Chandratal with some buffer time to explore. 
It was not allowed to camp there but there were many people camping around Chandratal. 
There was no authority to control this. 
While trekking from Kunjum La to Chandratal, I did not find any kiosk or office where one could find any kind camping permits etc. 
The visitors of Chandratal, mostly were with some trek organization on four wheelers with exceptions of few bikers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1948/31418928728_2991bfc2b9_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Chandra Taal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Chandra Taal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chandratal was still very beautiful, clean and peaceful.
The small stream emanating from Chandratal and a wooden bridge looks like a setting from a fairy tale. I sat there around half an hour. 
When sun had set, I turned back towards Batal road looking for a place to camp. 
Most of the good places nearby were completely occupied by private organizations which was little disheartening. 
Anyhow I was able to find a place to camp besides some Paragon camping site marking the end of yet another trek of mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next day was the journey back home day and I started my return walk to Batal. 
On the way to Batal from Chandratal, I got a lift by a jeep accompanying bikers till Batal and from there I was able get hold of another jeep going towards Manali. 
Buses are not very reliable on this route. 
By afternoon, I was in Manali where I had lunch and explored the market until it was time for bus to Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/07/18/hampta-pass-and-chandratal-trek-log/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/07/18/hampta-pass-and-chandratal-trek-log/</guid>
        
        <category>chandratal</category>
        
        <category>hampta pass</category>
        
        <category>Manali</category>
        
        <category>Spiti</category>
        
        
        <category>self</category>
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Indrahar Pass Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In our previous treks we had been travelling light and walking long miles a day thus helping us do treks with less leaves from work.
Planning first trek of 2016, I was thinking of something in Himachal Pradesh and then I got my hands on Depi Chaudhary’s Himalaya trek maps.
It’s very detailed one and I spent hours studying it. Hoping to combine two short duration treks, I thought of Indrahar pass(4350 m) in Dhauladhar Range between Kangra and Chamba valleys, and Kugti Pass (5050m) in Chamba. 
Indrahar pass is popular among trekkers but Kugti pass is less travelled with altitude of significant 5000+ meters and this required some travelling by road as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also thought of doing Minkiani pass from Laka cave after coming down from Indrahar pass. 
Depi Chaudhary’s map was showing a route to Minkiani pass from Laka cave which is little beyond Snow point cafe but we zeroed down on Indrahar pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1950/45244309202_ae64aefd4d_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kiran in the back, Akshay in the left and me in the right&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kiran in the back, Akshay in the left and me in the right&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My always ready travel buddies Kiran and Akshay were willing to join for this trek though Akshay wasn’t much updated on the diversions which I and Kiran were planning to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1927/44381470365_b1fe49ddd9_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With thought to first reach Indrahar pass and later decide what next, we left Delhi on Thursday, 12th May. 
Akshay wanted to see Bhagsu waterfall, so we started our day with that. We were told about a path leading to Triund via Upper Bhagsu village. 
There was a small puddle where it used to be a pond. 
We started for Triund around 12. It was a steep climb till we merged into Triund trek route. 
It was a hot day and there weren’t enough trees for shade. 
We had our lunch in Triund and soon decided to leave for Snowline Cafe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Akshay was little reluctant to walk that day and I was slowly giving up hope to reach Lahesh cave the same day. 
I sincerely wished that we reach Lahesh cave on the same day after halting for a while at Snowline cafe for food but by the time everybody reached Snowline, we decided to camp there and leave for Indrahar pass early next morning. 
We all were carrying our separate tents but the night got very windy and Kiran had to sleep in Akshay’s tent as his tent fell due to wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1927/44571403854_65bc4a75cf_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Snowline Cafe&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Our camp at Snowline Cafe&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the night we were informed of snow conditions on the trail and were advised to take a guide. 
We were told that an ice axe might be needed to carve out steps in a glacier which falls very steep from peak. 
There was small group of people who attempted to reach Indrahar pass a day before with a guide but they had to come back from few 100 meters before pass due to snow condition and weather. 
Though, short on money we couldn’t have been able to afford guide that day and we started little late around 8:30 AM on Friday contrary to what we had planned. 
There were two more people leaving that day from Snowline Cafe for the pass. 
They even had an ice axe and were even planning to cross the pass that day.
I was hopeful that if we followed them, we would be able to get to the top. 
They left before us. Akshay was not willing to continue, though he came along us for a stroll till Laka Cave area. 
Negotiating the Laka glacier took a little time and Akshay didn’t want to continue, so he decided to walk back from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1973/44571401674_aaf7d0fa08_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;it look a little time .. though it was fun&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;it look a little time .. though it was fun&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1912/44571402614_5749d2327a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;waterfall near lahesh cave&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;waterfall near lahesh cave&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We followed the trail and cairns on the way. The path was not very clear, sometimes we had to look around to be sure that we are on the right track. 
We continued our walk but Ken and his friend (other group we met at snowline) were nowhere to be seen by now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1979/44381469845_ef12ddec4a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were steps carved in glacier. 
Kiran and I  hesitantly crossed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slowly and steadily, we were making progress, finding it a little difficult to follow the track, though sure that it was the right path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top seemed very close. I saw a severed head of what looked like a goat and blood patches on the trek. 
I couldn’t think of any reason of what killed it that way. 
Kiran was uneasy after seeing that and was feeling tired so he asked me go ahead without him. 
It was past noon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1978/44381471795_1c5bca5013_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The top seemed very close.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The top seemed very close.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weather seemed to coming in heavily. Suddenly it was all dark and cloudy. 
It was difficult to see what lies ahead. Kiran was far behind and I was not able to find trail further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1973/44381471155_3712c2e739_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Seems close&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markers were pointing towards a glacier which was very steep. 
It wasn’t very wide but there were no footsteps. 
Suddenly it started to hail. 
I feared of it getting worse as there was no place for me to hide so I decided to turn back and be content with the progress made on the trek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With time, the hailing slowed down but there wasn’t much time to change the decision for that day. 
Few hours after we reached Snowline Cafe, Ken and his friends also came back and they managed to reach the top. 
I sat there and pondered what went wrong. 
Why did I turn back when I knew there wasn’t much left till the top, I was almost there. 
While talking to the cafe owner, he suggested that had we started little early, we could’ve got company of local Gaddi people, who crossed that pass frequently with their goats and sheeps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1916/44571403194_78cbe4917f_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;At center is the severed head of goat&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;At center is the severed head of goat&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recollecting all what I have seen on the way, I asked the shop owner at cafe about the severed head of goat. 
He told me that Gaddi’s kill the goat which walk slowly because if they are left behind, these goats may die with hunger.
We returned back from Snowline next day on Saturday to McLeodganj. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/photos/BKgE4Gx6LAX5YYnc9&quot;&gt;Here is our shared photo album&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;next-attempt&quot;&gt;Next Attempt&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It had been two weeks since my last unsuccessful attempt to complete the trek, the thought of not able to complete that trek was constantly bothering me. 
With a constant feeling of “ I shouldn’t have given up so easily “, I knew I won’t be able to plan any other trek unless I
complete this one so I decided to make another attempt to reach the top atleast. 
It was Friday, 3rd of June when I left alone for McLeodganj. 
My only camera; my mobile gave in due to charging problems. 
I didn’t even carry my tent this time and decided to stay in caves only. 
There was another cave on the other side near Chatta where I would be staying, if I were to cross the pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all the thoughts and will, I started off for Lahesh cave on Saturday Morning. Rested for a while at snowline cafe, I left for Lahesh cave after having lunch. 
I was in luck as there few gaddis who were to cross that pass tomorrow. Next morning, I heard calls of those shepherds while I was getting ready and I tagged along with them. 
Those sheeps were really slow while walking. 
I was following them and sometimes tried to help them controlling the sheeps. 
When I reached the point from where I turned back last time; I had to go ahead of these sheeps as they nearly came to a halt. 
Few local people were coming down from the top where they had gone to offer prayers.&lt;br /&gt;
Walking further more for around half an hour I was at the top. 
The lead shepherd was sitting there and enjoying the view of Chamba valley.
Breathing lively and cherishing what beautiful the view was, there is another thought going in back of my mind and I was wondering what would be the view of the other side from the top. 
Heavenly it was, much more than what I imagined. 
The steep descent from pass goes to a vast flat plateau covered with snow. 
From there one can see Pir panjal range and Mani Mahesh peak. 
Few minutes later another group joined us. 
We all stayed around for an hour and roamed around to see the view of valley from different spots. 
After an hour, clouds started rising from the valley and with rising clouds, we too started back. 
And in a short while, it started hailing and raining heavily. 
We continued our descent slowly and cautiously as the path was now slippery due to rain. 
And then we heard the sound of loud thunder and saw frequent lighting around. 
It continued all along the way and rain got heavier.
We had to take shelter and Lahesh cave was nearest to our rescue. 
After an hour it stopped raining and we again started walking down to Snowline cafe. 
I was having lunch over there when it started raining again, actually this time it was pouring. 
When it slowed down, I too started my journey back slowly towards Mcleodganj. 
It was already dark when I reached the town and I had to no other option than to stay over night in Mcleodganj due to non-availability of bus. 
I was happy that I reached the pass which gave me many sleepless nights because I left it incomplete last time. 
I still wished to cross the pass to see what lies on the other side; but I was travelling too light for that.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/05/12/indrahar-pass-trek-log/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2016/05/12/indrahar-pass-trek-log/</guid>
        
        <category>indrahar</category>
        
        <category>lahesh - chamba</category>
        
        <category>minkiani</category>
        
        <category>laka</category>
        
        <category>chata</category>
        
        <category>dharmshala</category>
        
        <category>kinnaur</category>
        
        <category>mcleodganj</category>
        
        <category>triund</category>
        
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
        <category>self</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Har ki Doon Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Just a week left for the year to change to 2016 and holidays were lined up, I was in the search of a winter trek, had Kauri pass and Har ki doon in my mind.
A month ago Kiran and I had just been to Hemkund Sahib and Valley of Flowers.
Another friend Dalima, was also willing to join us in our next trek as she needed an escape from city life.
Har ki doon is well known as one of the most popular winter treks in Uttarkashi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started from Delhi to Dehradun on the night of 26th December. 
After reaching Dehradun, we couldn’t find any conveyance to Sankri so we travelled ahead to Rishikesh and from there we took a bus to Sankri.
It was long ride of around 11 hours and by the time we reached Sankri, sun was about to set.
Sankri is a small and quiet place.
Due to heavy trekking season, accommodations were already full but after some search we were able to find a place to stay.
After enjoying dinner and some talks with fellow trekkers, we headed for some last minute purchase, booked the jeep to Taluka (Starting point of our trek).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around 8 AM, when we reached Taluka. 
It was a cold morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1974/43478712280_4fea6269d9_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;River&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;River&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just after walking few miles from Taluka, we were on the beautiful trail that goes along the river Supin.
The gentle sound of river flowing all along with you was very comforting and refreshing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1954/43478711330_903a22cff2_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Trail goes along the river&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Trail goes along the river&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking on the trails, we crossed a bridge on Supin river and started our steep climb to a village names, Osla. 
It was around 4 PM when we reached Osla and the village welcomed us with a very picturesque landscape.
From the river bed it seems as if people have made nests in the mountains. All the houses were of same color, made of wood which blends with the background perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1928/43478712870_3567a0db98_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Osla Village&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Osla Village&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started with just the breakfast, we had not eaten anything till now.
I got some maggi and biscuits from a shop in the village.
A man from village offered to prepare maggi for us while we talked to the children who flocked around us asking different questions.
The village was very small and there aren’t many people in the village. 
Those with whom we talked, were very keen on having us as their guest, but we were carrying our own tents.
So, we decided to have dinner with the old man who prepared maggi for us and pitched our tent outside his home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1902/43478710730_4c24f61108_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The contrast of Seema and Osla&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The contrast of Seema and Osla&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was cold out there, so Dalima stayed with one of the family in their house.
These houses were made of wood and housed a hearth made of mud in the room. 
Just above the hearth roof open to make room for smoke. 
There is a place to store wood and hay below the house.
Dalima’s knee problem had aggravated and she decided to take some rest the next day and we decided to go ahead.
So, we enquired about the logistics needed and arranged food for the rest of our trek. 
We left Dalima with the family with the promise to be back as soon. All of them were happy to have her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next day morning (Tuesday it was), we started off early after wrapping up our tents. 
Crossing Kalkatiyadhar campsite, we reached Har ki doon by afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1950/43478709010_44f3a46fc4_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Trail after Osla Village&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Trail after Osla Village&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a sunny day and there weren’t much trees on the trail. 
The trail just before the Har ki doon was enchanting and covered with snow with beautiful little streams joining Tons river and trees around. 
Har ki doon valley is a big amphitheatre which lies in the valley of majestic Swargarohini peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1921/43478714530_f1efb39a9f_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Har Ki Doon&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Har Ki Doon&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an inexplicable experience to see such a close view of Swargarohini peak. 
I couldn’t take my eyes off from the Swargarohini peak and was immersed in the thoughts of how Pandavas who attempted to climb the peak in Mahabharata era.
This trail is believed to be taken by Pandavas who attempted to go to heaven with their bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1944/43478713930_5692be0047_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Juandhar Glacier&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Juandhar Glacier&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting there for a while and munching all what Kiran got, we took water and essential stuff in our daypack and sent off to explore towards Juandhar glacier in the valley.
We walked inside the valley until sun started to set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1917/43478709830_c60123676b_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sunset in Har Ki Doon&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sunset in Har Ki Doon&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We pitched our tents beside the forest rest house and requested the caretaker of the rest house for the dinner. 
We watched the setting sun sitting on the big boulder near campsite. 
Soon the night turned cold and windy.
We spent most of the time in the kitchen before going to sleep, talking about what lies further on the trail and treks in the area.
I wanted to do the Borasu pass next time which lies further on the trail and take a diversion to Ruinsairatal which is around 14 km from Osla village and thats when I did Bali Pass which goes via Ruinsaira Taal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We woke up at 7 AM the next morning and soon started our retreat after wrapping our tents. 
It was an easy descent and we walked on scout’s pace. 
Dalima was eagerly waiting for us in the village where we had lunch around 11.
It was not long when we reached Taluka.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still had two spare days left and we could’ve attempted for Kedarkantha trek. 
But on the other hand, we thought New year parties with friends in Delhi are also cool and we left for Delhi the next morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://goo.gl/photos/xyArwdXxLzjtvKWDA&quot;&gt;Here is the link to our shared album.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2015/12/30/har-ki-doon-trek-log/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2015/12/30/har-ki-doon-trek-log/</guid>
        
        <category>winter trek</category>
        
        <category>swargarohini</category>
        
        <category>ruinsaira</category>
        
        <category>osla</category>
        
        <category>har ki doon</category>
        
        <category>puani garaat</category>
        
        <category>sankri</category>
        
        <category>tons</category>
        
        <category>borasu</category>
        
        <category>uttarkashi</category>
        
        <category>seema</category>
        
        <category>kedarkantha</category>
        
        <category>juandhar</category>
        
        <category>kalkatiyadhar</category>
        
        <category>supin</category>
        
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
        <category>self</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Valley of Flowers and Hemkund Sahib Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Having completed a quick trek to Roopkund in Dussehra vacations, I wanted to do another one in Deepawali as I had no plans of going home.
Kiran was also in Gurgaon too so we had 5 days to do something. 
I proposed going to Joshimath and doing some of treks among Kauri Pass(Curzon Trail) or Hemkund Sahib and Valley Of flowers (Valley of flowers and Hemkund Sahib were already closed by then for the winter season).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zeroing down to Hemkund Sahib and Valley Of flowers and we started but there were very few buses on the route due to Deepawali.  
We managed our way to Joshimath by changing buses and eventually booking a cab from Karnaprayag. 
It was night when we arrived Joshimath. 
To start trekking for Valley Of Flowers &amp;amp; Hemkund Sahib early morning, it would have been better if we stayed in Govind ghat that night but the cab driver was asking for a lot to go there so we decided to stay in Joshimath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1901/44542585784_288a21c4ea_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Trail&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Trail&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next morning, after asking about the route, we left for Govind ghat around 8 in morning.
Govind ghat is situated at the confluence of rivers Alaknanda and Lakshman Ganga. 
The route going through Bhyundar valley is well paved and goes through a dense forest with Bhyundar Ganga on the right side.
After 3-4 hours walk we reached Bhyundar village.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1908/45214702512_d1220bb7da_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Along Bhyundar village to Ghangharia&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Along Bhyundar village to Ghangharia&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no one in the village except one shop and 3-4 labours working on a home. 
While having our lunch, we enquired about the trail further ahead. 
The shopkeeper told us that there is absolutely no one beyond this point in Ghangharia or Hemkund Sahib and everything is closed. 
He also warned us about the bears and leopards in the area and gave us few crackers and some kerosene to light up fire in night.
After getting few chapatis packed with pickle, soon we left for Ghangharia. 
On our way, two dogs tagged along with us after getting lured by Kiran with biscuits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1923/30325745437_e1d440dcf0_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hathi Parbat as seen from Bhyundar Village&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Hathi Parbat as seen from Bhyundar Village, A trail to Kakbhushundi lake starts from here towards this mountain&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking through the dense forest, it was past 2 P.M. when we reached Ghangharia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1944/30325743477_fe4cba760a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ghangharia&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Ghangharia&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a significant place along this trek, with lots of houses on both sides of street; but everything was closed. 
It gave the whole place an eerie look. 
After hiding our bags in the gallery of a rest house, we left for Valley of Flowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1968/45264796211_8a26135876_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Towards Valley Of Flowers From Ghangharia, The Pushpawati river gorge&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Towards Valley Of Flowers From Ghangharia, The Pushpawati river gorge&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trek goes through the dense forest on left side and Pushpawati river gorge on the right. 
The Pushpawati river joins Bhuyandar Ganga near Ghangharia to form Lakshman Ganga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dogs walking with us chased the herd of grey langurs herds whenever they see them. 
Climbing our way after crossing Pushpawati river and walking through the dense forests with some snow along the trail; we reached Valley of Flowers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1955/43450314680_44d2905d6f_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Valley of Flowers in mid November&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Valley of Flowers in mid November&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flora in the valley was completely dried except few green patches here and there. 
We roamed inside this deserted valley, enjoying the view and clicking pictures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1936/44542575914_3aab105d33_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some walk inside the valley, we rested near the grave of Joan Margaret Legge (1885 - 1939) who died while collecting samples here. 
The sun was about to set, so we turned back towards Ghangharia. 
It was completely dark when we reached there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We picked some woods from the street and lit up a fire with the help of kerosene. 
Sitting there, the dogs occasionally barked and ran along the street. 
Kiran feared that something is around and tried to look towards the way these dogs ran with torch. 
We only had 6 chapatis to eat and I suggested we all (including the dogs dutifully prtecting us) eat them the next morning for breakfast as we needed enough energy to climb Hemkund Sahib.
After few hours of warming ourselves with fire, we decided to get some sleep. 
I kept the fire burning and pitched our tents in the gallery of the rest house. 
Dogs kept barking and running all night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1940/43450309710_29e5de7a8b_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The footsteps&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The footsteps&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next day morning, after sharing our breakfast with dogs, we started for Hemkund Sahib. 
It was a continuous 6 km climb till the top. 
After 3 kms, treeline ends and the path was snowy. 
The bridge on the way was disassembled so we found an alternate route nearby to go further. 
After the bridge there are stairs and there also is an alternate way. 
The stairs were steep and completely covered with snow but the alternate path is longer and not so steep. 
There was snow everywhere. 
After crossing the nullah, when I started on the stairs, I noticed foot steps of some big animal which walked before us on that path. 
Kiran found the path slippery and decided to take the alternate route. 
I climbed the stairs cautiously, wondering if some bear is waiting for me above but was later assured that this could not be the case as the dogs went ahead and waited for me at the end of stairs. 
Kiran continued negotiating the snow, while I reached the gurudwara. 
After few mins, Kiran reached there and meanwhile I roamed around the serene Hemkund lake taking pictures with my mobile which still retained it’s juice in airplane mode. With the gentle breeze, the crystal clear rippling water of the lake was making sounds creating a serene and magical surroundings. 
We sat there on a stone by the lake for few minutes in silence and watched around. 
The dogs were lying on the snow basking in the sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1905/45264793711_6da7566a6f_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Homkund Lake&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Homkund Lake&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 11 AM, we started trekking back for Govind ghat. 
It was a long way ahead and we both were hungry. 
We picked our bags up from Ghangharia, where we stayed last night and continued the descent, talking about having big lunch at Bhyundar. 
The shopkeeper was waiting for us; when we reached there in noon. 
After lunch and little rest in Bhyundar, we returned the kerosene and the crackers which we didn’t use.
It was necessary to reach Govind Ghat by evening, so as to stay in Joshimath that night.
Around 6 PM, when we reached Govind Ghat it was dark. 
With some luck, we managed to catch a jeep coming from Badrinath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still had a day left after these two trek days. 
And having this very crazy habit of doing more, going ahead, a thought popped in my mind of doing Kauri pass.
It was at least 28 km one way which we decided could not be managed in the remaining time, we ended our trek with this only.
Next day we ended our trip after visiting Badrinath temple and stayed overnight in Joshimath.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2015/11/18/valley-of-flowers-and-hemkund-sahib-trek/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2015/11/18/valley-of-flowers-and-hemkund-sahib-trek/</guid>
        
        <category>govind ghat</category>
        
        <category>ghangharia</category>
        
        <category>valley of flowers</category>
        
        <category>chamoli</category>
        
        <category>joshimath</category>
        
        <category>pushpawati</category>
        
        <category>bhyundar</category>
        
        <category>hemkund</category>
        
        <category>bhyundar ganga</category>
        
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
        <category>self</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Roopkund Trek</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of my friend asked me if I had any plans for Dussehara vacations.
I wasn’t having any, so he asked me about Roopkund as it can be done in two days, which we would be left with after taking out the travel time from Delhi. 
Being an extended weekend, I really wanted to go out somehwere and could not think of a place.
The friend who seeded this though got little sick and dropped out so now, there were three of us for the trek. 
Me, Kiran (from Bombay) and Silva (from Brazil).
Kiran and I were very enthusiastic to complete this trek and we chalked out our trek plan to make it possible. 
Silva had done a trek to Tungnath with Kiran and my friend Akshay few week back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we started on Wednesday; the cab picked me up around 10:30 in the night. 
After a whole night and day drive, next day we reached village Wan around 5 p.m. and to make most of our lost time, we started the trek that day itself, after arranging for our driver’s accomodation. 
We did get few advices for not leaving for trek at such hours, but we went on to stay on our chalked plan (we just had 4 days to complete this trek).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calling ourselves bad mofos; we went past the Wan village down to the bridge on river Neelganga. 
By then it was completely dark. 
Holding our torches, we started to climb. 
Our aim was, to reach Bedini around 11 in night. 
Even though, we were advised against it in the village, we thought that it is better to utilize this time in trek than to stay. 
It was around 10 p.m.; when we reached first camping site Gharoli Patal, Bedini was still 3 km. 
But after staying there for few mins for snacks; we decided to camp there only as it was very cold and windy and we were tired too because of the long journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1972/44571862604_02c22b0ffb_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A view from Bedini Bugyal&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A view from Bedini Bugyal&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next morning we started our day early (around 6) by leaving for Bhojbasa.
We were happy that stopping at Gharoli Patal, the previous night, didn’t cost us much time when we reached Bedini. 
There we stopped for almost half an hour, admiring the beauty of vast meadows and clicking few clicks; we left for our next stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1956/30355258427_8553d501d3_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;On the way to Patharnachuni&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;On the way to Patharnachuni&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1936/44571860264_683a71889a_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;On the way to Patharnachuni&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around lunch, that we reached Patharnachuni.
Soon after having food, we left for our final stop, Bhojbasa. 
Walking forward there was a steep ascent to Kalu Vinayak, Silva was walking a bit slow by then. 
Kiran and I discussed, if he could walk with Silva and I’ll come back to carry the bag from Bhojbasa. 
I tried walking fast and reached Bojbasa early, where I left the bag and rushed back towards Kalu Vinayak.
Kiran and Silva were resting there. 
Silva was feeling better now and didn’t let me carry his bag.
We all walked together to bhojbasa and managed to reach well before evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did a little walk around the campsite for acclimatization , having tea and water. 
We pitched our tents inside the forest hut. 
Although a lot colder, it was less windy than Bedini here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1920/44571862004_9149484e92_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Beyond Junargali&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Beyond Junargali&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next morning, we started for Roopkund around 6. 
We packed our tents and left our bag there in the hut. 
It was that cold and windy that some ice started to appear inside water bottle. 
After one and a half hour walk, we reached Roopkund.
It was Silva’s first experince of such altitude and cold and hence he was walking with slow and steady pace, catching his breath every now and then. 
There was some firewood left from previous fire; which I lit and warmed ourselves while waiting for Silva. 
Soon Silva arrived and after resting there for a while, we left for Junargali. 
After few minutes of climb, we reached Junargali. 
It was windy was clear in Junargali with magnificent view of Mt.Trisul(7120m) and Nandaghunti(6309m).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://c2.staticflickr.com/2/1975/45244744532_f78f0de022_o.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jorawar Gali Pass&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Jorawar Gali Pass&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The door like structure with bell hanging by it looked very inviting. 
A thought came to my mind for going ahead from there to Hemkund but we were running short of time. 
We needed to move back as soon as we can if wanted to make it back to Wan village by night. 
Inspite of his slow speed, Silva really wanted to climb up to Junargali so we waited there (stairs towards Shila Samudra) for him, collecting litter there
left by previous trekkers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about an hour or so stay at Junargali, we started our way back to Bhojbasa. 
We stopped for some munching anf there we found another group of three people, who had similar plans of reaching Wan today. 
I really wanted to go via Ali Bugyal; but that would have required 2-3 hours more than usual and it seemed, that it was too late for that. 
When we reached Pattahrnachuni in an hour or so, Silva was walking good. 
It was now sunset time when we reached Gharoli Patal. 
After taking a lot of shortcuts on descents; my legs were tired. 
I was exhausted and had very less control on my legs. 
By the time we reached Neelganga bridge, it was already dark and I was out of water and thirsty till that time. 
I waited there with other group for Kiran and Silva.
We started our last patch of trek to Wan village. 
When we reached the village from Neelganga bridge, it seemed that we lost our way which we took before. 
After asking for directions and wasting around 2 hours, we managed to reach roadside around 9:30 p.m. where our cab driver was waiting for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took little more than two trek days for this trek from Wan village to Roopkund. 
Looking back, I think that if we had one more day, one day stay at Ali Bugyal would have given the perfect finish to this trek.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2015/11/17/roopkund-trek/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2015/11/17/roopkund-trek/</guid>
        
        <category>nanda ghunti</category>
        
        <category>bedini</category>
        
        <category>roopkund</category>
        
        <category>junargali</category>
        
        <category>trishul</category>
        
        <category>chamoli</category>
        
        <category>pataharnachuni</category>
        
        <category>gharoli patal</category>
        
        <category>lohajung</category>
        
        <category>wan</category>
        
        
        <category>trek</category>
        
        <category>self</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>HMI, Darjeeling vs. NIM, Uttarkashi</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is one of those questions which comes to mind when going for a mountaineering course in India. 
Having done my &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2009/04/11/basic-mountaineering-course-hmi/&quot;&gt;BMC from HMI&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2014/10/14/advance-mountaineering-course-nim/&quot;&gt;AMC from NIM&lt;/a&gt;, I got some idea about the training in these two institutes. 
Here is what I thought of HMI and NIM in terms of :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;organization&quot;&gt;Organization&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both HMI and NIM are run by Ministry of Defence, GOI in collaboration
with respective state governments. So, in terms and objective and
philosophy and in training programs both are same. In my personal
opinion, the past principals and the present principal (Col. Ajay
Kothiyal) of NIM  seem more active and devoted to the institute. NIM
played major role in rescue and rehabilitation work in the time 2013
Uttarakhand disaster. This was also widely covered in media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rock-climbing-area&quot;&gt;Rock Climbing area&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest asset of NIM is that it has a vast rock climbing area in
Tekhla. In this area, there are variety of rock features of varying
degree of difficulty. Trainees have plenty of time to practice rock
climbing techniques on these features. In HMI, there weren’t much rock
faces to climb. For rock climbing, it has Tenzing Rock and Gombu Rock in
the outskirts of Darjeeling. They try to compensate this later in the
course with the big boulders available around the base camp. So rest of
the training in rock craft happens in Base camp area of HMI which is in
Chaurikhang, Sikkim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HMI’s artificial wall seem definitely bigger than those in NIM and
everything else is more or less same. Maybe because HMI installed these
walls after NIM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;glacier-for-training-of-ice-climbing-techniques&quot;&gt;Glacier for training of ice climbing techniques&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rathong glacier, training area of HMI has lot more ice walls to
practice than the Dokrani glacier of NIM. Both the glaciers are receding
very fast and trainees need to walk to the training area everyday which
takes some time and energy. Dokrani glacier of NIM, has lot of moraine
covering the ice walls and around the snout of the glacier where most of
the training happens there isn’t much blue ice. I saw plenty of smoking
blue ice in Rathong glacier. It has big fields of blue ice around the
training area. Although advance courses in NIM goes to a different
training area upwards in the glacier for 2 days for their advance ice
craft which has sufficient ice walls and relatively cleaner ice.
Overall, in terms of ice walls available on which we get to train, HMI
has lot better than NIM. Maybe in future, NIM may think of to change the
base camp to get better area for ice craft. It would be more appropriate
for NIM, to move the base camp to the place where they have their
advance base camp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;technical-equipments-and-training&quot;&gt;Technical Equipments and Training&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was unanimously established among my course-mates of AMC who did
their BMC from HMI that NIM provides more and advance technical
equipments than HMI. In case of HMI advance techniques or use of advance
equipments are mostly demonstrated by instructors but in NIM you’ll get
a chance to practice with/on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;trek-to-base-camp&quot;&gt;Trek to Base Camp&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a fact that, to reach the base camp; the trek in HMI is tougher
than that in NIM. In both institutes, it takes 3 days to reach base
camp. The trek in HMI goes on relatively higher altitude than NIM and
are longer on everyday. Situated on higher altitude than NIM, the base
camp of HMI offers more splendid view of surrounding peaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;accomodation&quot;&gt;Accomodation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hostel of HMI and NIM are both well maintained and have all the
required facilities. If you are pursuing basic course, you get to stay
in barrack made of metal sheets and wood in HMI. It’s all tent in NIM
for both basic and advance courses outside the campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;location-of-institute&quot;&gt;Location of Institute&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, roaming in and around Darjeeling has better experience
than Uttarkashi. So, location wise, HMI wins and it also has bigger area
with a zoo in it’s campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;hmi-contact-info&quot;&gt;HMI Contact Info:&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;POSTAL ADDRESS&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
PRINCIPAL &lt;br /&gt;
Himalayan Mountaineering Institute &lt;br /&gt;
Jawahar Parvat&lt;br /&gt;
Darjeeling-734 101 (WB), India&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
TRAINING OFFICE: 0354 2254087/2254299 &lt;br /&gt;
PRINCIPAL : 91 354 2254083&lt;br /&gt;
FAX No:91 354 2253760&lt;br /&gt;
Email: hmi_darj@rediffmail.com/hmidarj@gmail.com &lt;br /&gt;
Website: &lt;a href=&quot;https://hmidarjeeling.com/&quot;&gt;https://hmidarjeeling.com/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;nim-contact-info&quot;&gt;NIM Contact Info&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;POSTAL ADDRESS&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
PRINCIPAL, &lt;br /&gt;
Nehru Institute Of Mountaineering &lt;br /&gt;
Uttarkashi - 249193, &lt;br /&gt;
Uttarakhand (India) &lt;br /&gt;
Tel: +911374 - 222123, 224663, 223580 &lt;br /&gt;
Fax: +911374 - 222344 &lt;br /&gt;
Email: nimutk2004@gmail.com &lt;br /&gt;
Website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nimindia.net/&quot;&gt;http://www.nimindia.net/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2014/10/22/hmi-darjeeling-vs-nim-uttarkashi/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://ghumakkad.github.io//blog/2014/10/22/hmi-darjeeling-vs-nim-uttarkashi/</guid>
        
        <category>Darjeeling</category>
        
        <category>Uttarkashi</category>
        
        <category>BMC</category>
        
        <category>NIM</category>
        
        <category>HMI</category>
        
        <category>AMC</category>
        
        
        <category>blog</category>
        
        <category>mountaineering</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
